                 PCT: Point cloud transformer                                                                                                   199
                                     Zheng-Ning Liu received his bachelor                                Shi-Min Hu is current a professor in
                                     degree    in   computer     science   from                          the Department of Computer Science
                                     Tsinghua University in 2017.         He is                          and Technology, Tsinghua University,
                                     currently a Ph.D. candidate in the                                  Beijing, China. He received his Ph.D.
                                     Department of Computer Science and                                  degree from Zhejiang University in 1996.
                                     Technology, Tsinghua University. His                                His research interests include digital
                                     research interests include 3D computer                              geometry processing, video processing,
                                     vision, 3D reconstruction, and computer                             rendering, computer animation, and
                graphics.                                                           computer-aided geometric design. He has published more
                                                                                    than 100 papers in journals and refereed conferences. He
                                                                                    is the Editor-in-Chief of Computational Visual Media, and
                                                                                    on editorial boards of several journals, including Computer
                                     Tai-Jiang Mu is currently an assistant         Aided Design and Computer & Graphics. He is a senior
                                     researcher at Tsinghua University, where       member of IEEE and ACM, and Fellow of CCF and SMA.
                                     he received his B.S. and Ph.D. degrees         Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative
                                     in computer science and technology             Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which
                                     in 2011 and 2016, respectively.        His     permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduc-
                                     research interests include computer            tion in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate
                                     vision, robotics, and computer graphics.       credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link
                                                                                    to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes
                                                                                    were made.
                                     Ralph R. Martin received his Ph.D.                The images or other third party material in this article are
                                     degree from Cambridge University in            included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless
                                     1983.     He is currently a emeritus           indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material
                                     professor with Cardiﬀ University. He           is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and
                                     has authored over 250 papers and 14            your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or
                                     books, covering such topics as solid and       exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission
                                     surface modeling, intelligent sketch input,    directly from the copyright holder.
                                     geometric reasoning, reverse engineering,         To view a copy of this licence,              visit  http://
                and various aspects of computer graphics. He is a Fellow of         creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.
                the Learned Society of Wales, the Institute of Mathematics          Other papers from this open access journal are available
                and its Applications, and the British Computer Society. He          free of charge from http://www.springer.com/journal/41095.
                is currently the Associate Editor-in-Chief of Computational         To submit a manuscript, please go to https://www.
                Visual Media.                                                       editorialmanager.com/cvmj.
