                Computational Visual Media
                https://doi.org/10.1007/s41095-021-0229-5                                 Vol. 7, No. 2, June 2021, 187–199
                Research Article
               PCT: Point cloud transformer
                                   1                    1                       1                   1                        2
               Meng-Hao Guo , Jun-Xiong Cai , Zheng-Ning Liu , Tai-Jiang Mu , Ralph R. Martin , and
               Shi-Min Hu1( )
               c
               TheAuthor(s) 2021.
               Abstract The irregular domain and lack of ordering           and rigid transformations to ensure invariance under
               make it challenging to design deep neural networks for       permutations and rotations. Inspired by strong
               point cloud processing. This paper presents a novel          progress made by convolutional neural networks
               framework named Point Cloud Transformer (PCT) for            (CNNs) in the ﬁeld of image processing, many recent
               point cloud learning. PCT is based on Transformer,           works [2–5] have considered to deﬁne convolution
               whichachieveshugesuccessinnaturallanguageprocessing          operators that can aggregate local features for point
               and displays great potential in image processing.      It    clouds. These methods either reorder the input point
               is inherently permutation invariant for processing a         sequence or voxelize the point cloud to obtain a
               sequence of points, making it well-suited for point cloud    canonical domain for convolutions.
               learning. To better capture local context within the           Recently, Transformer [6], the dominant framework
               point cloud, we enhance input embedding with the             in natural language processing, has been applied
               support of farthest point sampling and nearest neighbor      to image vision tasks, giving better performance
               search.  Extensive experiments demonstrate that the          than popular convolutional neural networks [7, 8].
               PCTachieves the state-of-the-art performance on shape        Transformer is a decoder–encoder structure that
               classification, part segmentation, semantic segmentation,    contains three main modules for input (word)
               and normal estimation tasks.                                 embedding, positional (order) encoding, and self-
               Keywords 3D computer vision; deep learning; point            attention.   The self-attention module is the core
                            cloud processing; Transformer                   component, generating reﬁned attention feature for
                                                                            its input feature based on global context. First, self-
               1    Introduction                                            attention takes the sum of input embedding and
               Extracting semantics directly from a point cloud is          positional encoding as input, and computes three
               an urgent requirement in some applications such as           vectors for each word: query, key, and value through
               robotics, autonomous driving, augmented reality, etc.        trained linear layers.    Then, the attention weight
               Unlike 2D images, point clouds are disordered and            between any two words can be obtained by matching
               unstructured, making it challenging to design neural         (dot-producting) their query and key vectors. Finally,
               networks to process them. Charles et al. [1] pioneered       the attention feature is deﬁned as the weighted
               PointNet for feature learning on point clouds by             sum of all value vectors with the attention weights.
               using multi-layer perceptrons (MLPs), max-pooling,           Obviously, the output attention feature of each word
                                                                            is related to all input features, making it capable
                1 BNRist,    Department of Computer Science and             of learning the global context.       All operations of
                  Technology, Tsinghua University, Beiing 100084, China.    Transformer are parallelizable and order-independent.
                  E-mail:    M.-H. Guo, gmh20@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn;        In theory, it can replace the convolution operation
                  J.-X. Cai, junxiong20@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn; Z.-N. Liu,   in a convolutional neural network and has better
                  lzhengning@gmail.com; T.-J.Mu,taijiang@tsinghua.edu.cn;   versatility. For more detailed introduction of self-
                  S.-M. Hu, shimin@tsinghua.edu.cn ( ).                     attention, please refer to Section 3.2.
                2 Cardiﬀ University, Cardiﬀ CF243AA, UK. E-mail:              Inspired by the Transformer’s success in vision
                  ralph@cs.cf.ac.uk.
                Manuscript received: 2021-03-04; accepted: 2021-03-26       and NLP tasks, we propose a novel framework PCT
                                                                        187
