                                                           NatL Acad. Sci. USA
                                              Proc.               pp. 2554-2558, April 1982
                                              Vol. 79,
                                              Biophysics
                                              Neural networks and physical systems with emergent collective
                                              computational abilities
                                                          (associative memory/parallel processing/categorization/content-addressable memory/fail-soft devices)
                                             J. J. HOPFIELD
                                              Division ofChemistry and Biology, California Institute ofTechnology, Pasadena, California 91125; and Bell Laboratories, Murray Hill, New Jersey 07974
                                              Contributed byJohnJ. Hopfweld, January 15, 1982
                                             ABSTRACT                                   Computational properties ofuse to biological or-                                                                                            calized content-addressable memory or categorizer using ex-
                                              ganisms or to the construction of computers can emerge as col-                                                                                                                        tensive asynchronous parallel processing.
                                              lective properties of systems-having a large number of simple                                                                                                                         The general content-addressable memory of a physical
                                              equivalentcomponents (orneurons). Thephysicalmeaningofcon-                                                                                                                            system
                                              tent-addressable memory is described by an appropriate phase                                                                                                                          Suppose that an item stored in memory is "H. A. Kramers &
                                              space flow of the state of a system. A model of such a system is                                                                                                                      G. H. Wannier Phys. Rev. 60, 252 (1941)." A general content-
                                              given, based on aspects ofneurobiology but readily adapted to in-                                                                                                                     addressable memory would be capable ofretrieving this entire
                                              tegrated circuits. The collective properties ofthis model produce                                                                                                                     memory item on the basis ofsufficient partial information. The
                                              a content-addressable memory which correctly yields an entire                                                                                                                         input "& Wannier, (1941)" might suffice. An ideal memory
                                              memoryfromanysubpartofsufficient size. The algorithm for the                                                                                                                                                      with errors and retrieve this reference even from the
                                              time evolution ofthe state ofthe system is based on asynchronous                                                                                                                      could deal
                                              parallel processing. Additional emergent collective properties in-                                                                                                                    input "Vannier, (1941)". In computers, only relatively simple
                                              clude some capacity for generalization, familiarity recognition,                                                                                                                      forms ofcontent-addressable memory have been made in hard-
                                              categorization, error correction, and time sequence retention.                                                                                                                        ware (10, 11). Sophisticated ideas like error correction in ac-
                                              Thecollective properties are onlyweakly sensitive to details ofthe                                                                                                                    cessing information are usually introduced as software (10).
                                              modeling or the failure of individual devices.                                                                                                                                               There are classes ofphysical systems whose spontaneous be-
                                              Given the dynamical electrochemical properties ofneurons and                                                                                                                          havior can be used as a form of general (and error-correcting)
                                              their interconnections (synapses), we readily understand schemes                                                                                                                       content-addressable memory. Consider the time evolution of
                                              that use a few neurons to obtain elementary useful biological                                                                                                                          a physical system that can be described by a set of general co-
                                              behavior (1-3). Our understanding of such simple circuits in                                                                                                                           ordinates. A point in state space then represents the instanta-
                                              electronics allows us to plan larger and more complex circuits                                                                                                                         neous condition of the system. This state space may be either
                                              which are essential to large computers. Because evolution has                                                                                                                          continuous or discrete (as in the case ofN Ising spins).
                                              no such plan, it becomes relevant to ask whether the ability of                                                                                                                              Theequations ofmotion ofthe system describe aflowin state
                                              large collections of neurons to perform "computational" tasks                                                                                                                          space. Various classes offlow patterns are possible, but the sys-
                                              may in part be a spontaneous collective consequence ofhaving                                                                                                                           tems ofuse for memory particularly include those that flow to-
                                              a large number ofinteracting simple neurons.                                                                                                                                           wardlocally stable points from anywhere within regions around
                                                     In physical systems made from a large number ofsimple ele-                                                                                                                      those points. A particle with frictional damping moving in a
                                              ments, interactions among large numbers of elementary com-                                                                                                                             potential well with two minima exemplifies such a dynamics.
                                              ponents yield collective phenomena such as the stable magnetic                                                                                                                                If the flow is not completely deterministic, the description
                                              orientations and domains in a magnetic system or the vortex                                                                                                                            is more complicated. In the two-well problems above, if the
                                              patterns in fluid flow. Do analogous collective phenomena in                                                                                                                           frictional force is characterized by atemperature, it must also
                                              a system of simple interacting neurons have useful "computa-                                                                                                                           produce a random driving force. The limit points become small
                                              tional" correlates? For example, are the stability ofmemories,                                                                                                                         limiting regions, and the stability becomes not absolute. But
                                              the construction of categories of generalization, or time-se-                                                                                                                          as long as the stochastic effects are small, the essence of local
                                              quential memory also emergent properties and collective in                                                                                                                             stable points remains.                                                            described by many coordinates
                                              origin? This paper examines a new modeling ofthis old and fun-                                                                                                                                Consider a physical system state vector X. Let the
                                              damental question (4-8) and shows that important computa-                                                                                                                              X1 XN, the components of a                                                                                **.                       if the system
                                                                                                                                    arise.                                                                                           have locally stable limit points Xa, Xb,                                                                          Then,                             system
                                              tional properties spontaneously                                                                    and the details of neuro-                                                           is started sufficiently near any Xa, as at X = Xa + A, it will
                                                     All modeling is based on details,                                                                                and incompletely                                               proceed in time until X                                                 Xa. We can regard the information
                                              anatomy and neural function are both myriad                                                                                          of the emer-                                      stored in the system as the vectors Xa, Xb,                                                                                      .   The starting
                                              known (9). In many physical systems, the nature                                                                                                 inserted                               point X = Xa + A represents a partial knowledge of the item
                                               gent collective properties is insensitive to the details                                                                                             sound                            Xa, and the system then generates the total information Xa.
                                               in the model (e.g., collisions are essential to generate                                                                                                                                     Any physical system whose dynamics in phase space is dom-
                                              waves, but any reasonable interatomic force law will yield ap-                                                                                                                          inated by a substantial number oflocally stable states to which
                                               propriate collisions). In the same spirit, I will seek collective                                                                                                                      it is attracted can therefore be regarded as a general content-
                                               properties that are robust against change in the model details.                                                                                                                        addressable memory. The physical system will be a potentially
                                                     The model could be readily implemented by integrated cir-                                                                                                                        useful memory if, in addition, any prescribed set of states can
                                              cuit hardware. The conclusions suggest the design of a delo-                                                                                                                            readily be made the stable states ofthe system.
                                               Thepublication costs ofthis article were defrayed in part by page charge                                                                                                               The model system                                                will be called neurons. Each neuron i
                                               payment. This article must therefore be hereby marked "advertise-                                                                                                                      The processing devices of                                                                                    and Pitts                                      = 0
                                               ment" in accordance with 18 U. S. C. §1734 solely to indicate this fact.                                                                                                               has two states like those                                                 McCullough                                                   (12): Vi
          Downloaded from https://www.pnas.org by 50.47.140.49 on December 30, 2025 from IP address 50.47.140.49.                                                                                                      2554
﻿                                                          Biophysics: Hopfield                                                                                                                      Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 79 (1982)                                       2555
                                         ("not firing") and Vi = 1 ("firing at maximum rate"). When neu-                                                              computation (20, 21). Complexcircuitry is easy to plan but more
                                         ron i has a connection made to it from neuron j, the strength                                                                difficult to discuss in evolutionary terms. In contrast, our model
                                         ofconnection is defined as Tij. (Nonconnected neurons have Tij                                                               obtains its emergent computational properties from simple
                                              0.) The instantaneous state ofthe system is specifiedby listing                                                         properties of many cells rather than circuitry.
                                         the N values of Vi, so it is represented by a binary word of N                                                               The biological interpretation of the model
                                         bits.                                                                                                                        Most neurons are capable ofgenerating a train ofaction poten-
                                              The state changes in time according to the following algo-                                                              tials-propagating pulses ofelectrochemical activity-when the
                                          rithm. For each neuron i there is a fixed threshold U,. Each                                                                average potential across their membrane is held well above its
                                          neuron i readjusts its state randomly in time but with a mean                                                               normal resting value. The mean rate at which action potentials
                                          attempt rate W, setting                                                                                                     are generated is a smooth function ofthe mean membrane po-
                                                                                 1                                                                                    tential, having the general form shown in Fig. 1.
                                                                       Vi        °           IT.,V.                                                      ]                 The                        information sent to
                                                                            Vi0if joi                           < Ui                                                  in a         biological                                              other neurons often lies
                                          Thus, each neuron randomly and                                                                                              one short-time average of the firing rate (22). When this is so,
                                          whether it is above or below                                      asynchronously evaluates                                          can neglect the details of individual action potentials and
                                                                                                 threshold and readjusts accord-                                      regard Fig. 1 as a smooth input-output relationship. [Parallel
                                          ingly. (Unless otherwise stated, we choose Ui = 0.)                                                                         pathways carrying the same information would enhance the
                                              Although this model has superficial similarities to the Per-                                                            ability of the system to extract a short-term average firing rate
                                          ceptron (13, 14) the essential differences are responsible for the                                                          (23, 24).]
                                          new results. First, Perceptrons were modeled chiefly with                                                                        Astudy ofemergent collective effects and spontaneous com-
                                          neural connections in a "forward" direction A -> B -* C -- D.                                                               putation must necessarily focus on the nonlinearity of the in-
                                          The analysis of networks with strong backward coupling                                                                      put-output relationship. The essence ofcomputation is nonlin-
                                                             proved intractable. All our interesting results arise                                                    ear logical operations. The particle interactions that produce
                                          as consequences ofthe strong back-coupling. Second,                                                                         true collective effects in particle dynamics come from a nonlin-
                                          tron studies usually made a random net ofneurons deal Percep-                                                               ear dependence offorces on positions ofthe particles. Whereas
                                          with a real physical world and did not ask the questions directly                                                           linear associative networks have emphasized the linear central
                                          to finding the more abstract emergent computationalessential                                                                 region (14-19) of Fig. 1, we will replace the input-output re-
                                          ties. Finally, Perceptron modeling required                                                        proper-                   lationship by the dot-dash step. Those neurons whose operation
                                          rons like a conventional digital computer.                                       synchronous neu-                            is dominantly linear merely provide a pathway of communica-
                                          for such global synchrony and, given the There is no evidence                                                                tion between nonlinear neurons. Thus, we consider a network
                                          propagation, there would be no way to delays ofnerve signal                                                                  of"on or off" neurons, granting that some ofthe interconnec-
                                          effectively. Chiefly computational                                        use global synchrony                               tions may be by way ofneurons operating in the linear regime.
                                          in spite ofasynchrony have                                      properties which can exist                                       Delays in synaptic transmission (ofpartially stochastic char-
                                                                                            interesting implications in biology.                                       acter) and in the transmission ofimpulses along axons and den-
                                          The information storage algorithm                                                                                            drites produce a delay between the input of a neuron and the
                                          Suppose we wish to store the set of states V8, s = 1                                                 n. We                   generation of an effective output. All such delays have been
                                          use the storage prescription (15, 16)                                                                                        modeled by a single parameter, the stochastic mean processing
                                                                                                                                                                       time 1/W.
                                                                                                                                                                           The input to a particular neuron arises from the current leaks
                                                                          Tij=            (2V - 1)(2Vj - 1)                                           [2]              of the synapses to that neuron, which influence the cell mean
                                                                                      S                                                                                potential. The synapses are activated by arriving action poten-
                                          but with Tii = 0. From this definition                                                                                       tials. The input signal to a cell i can be taken to be
                                                          Tijjs =E                       -1)                                                                                                                            ITijvj                                                      [5]
                                                                                (2V,                 I VJ(2Vj-1)                      Hjs.            [3]
                                          The mean value of the bracketed term in Eq. 3 is 0 unless s                                                                  where Tij represents the effectiveness ofa synapse. Fig. 1 thus
                                          - s', for which the mean is N/2. This pseudoorthogonality
                                          yields
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      /
                                                                    > TiVs               (Hs')         (2Vs' - 1) N/2                                 [4]                                      Q                                   ~~~~~~~~~/
                                                                     i                                                                                                                     0                                      ,
                                          and is positive ifVW' = 1 and negative ifVf' = 0. Except for the                                                                                P°                            I       I'
                                          noise coming from the s # s' terms, the stored state would al-                                                                            0 a)-jaz-Present Model
                                          ways be stable under our processing algorithm.                                                                                             W                        t                   --Linear Modeling
                                              Such matrices T,. have been used in theories of linear asso-                                                                          w
                                          ciative nets (15-19) to produce an output pattern from a paired                                                                                 .'C
                                          input stimulus, S1 -* 01. A second association S2 -° 02 can be
                                          simultaneously stored in the same network. But the confusing
                                          simulus 0.6 Si + 0.4 S2 will produce a generally meaningless                                                                                     E -0.1 /                                            0
                                          mixed output 0.6 01 + 0.4 02 Our model, in contrast, will use                                                                                          Membrane Potential (Volts) or "Input"
                                          its strong nonlinearity to make choices, produce categories, and
                                          regenerate information and, with highprobability, will generate                                                                 FIG. 1.        Firing rate versus membrane voltage for a typical neuron
                                          the output 01 from such a confusing mixed stimulus.                                                                          (solid line), dropping to 0 for large negative potentials and saturating
                                              Alinear associative net must be connected in a complex way                                                               for positive potentials. The broken lines show approximations used in
                                          with an external nonlinear logic processor in order to yield true                                                            modeling.
       Downloaded from https://www.pnas.org by 50.47.140.49 on December 30, 2025 from IP address 50.47.140.49.
﻿                   2556       Biophysics: Hopfield                                                                 Proc. NatL Acad. Sci. USA 79 (1982)
                    becomes an input-output relationship for a neuron.                             The third behavior seen was chaotic wandering in a small
                       Little, Shaw, and Roney (8, 25, 26) have developed ideas on               region of state space. The Hamming distance between two bi-
                    the collective functioning ofneural nets based on "on/off" neu-              nary states A and B is defined as the number ofplaces in which
                    rons and synchronous processing. However, in their model the                 the digits are different. The chaotic wandering occurred within
                    relative timing of action potential spikes was central and re-               ashort Hammingdistanceofoneparticularstate. Statisticswere
                    sulted in reverberating action potential trains. Our model and               done on the probability pi ofthe occurrence ofa state in a time
                    theirs have limited formal similarity, although there may be                 ofwandering around this minimum, and an entropic measure
                    connections at a deeper level.                                               ofthe available states M was taken
                       Most modeling ofneural learning networks has been based
                    on synapses ofageneral type describedby Hebb(27) and Eccles                                        In M= -2 pi In pi.                          [9]
                    (28). The essential ingredient is the modification of T; by cor-
                    relations like                                                               AvalueofM =25wasfoundforN= 30. Theflowinphasespace
                                          AT41 = [Vi(t)Vj(t)]average                   [6]       produced by this model algorithm has the properties necessary
                                                                                                for a physical content-addressable memory whether or not T
                    where the average is some appropriate calculation over past                  is symmetric. with N = 100
                    history. Decay in time and effects of            or [Vj(t)]avg are also         Simulations                  were much slower and not quan-
                                                            [Vi(t)]avg                           titatively pursued. They showed qualitative similarity to N =
                    allowed. Model networks with such synapses (16, 20, 21) can                  30.
                    construct the associative T., ofEq. 2. We will therefore initially              Why should stable limit points or regions persist when Tij
                    assume that such a Ty1 has been produced by previous experi-                 # Tjj? If the algorithm at some time changes Vi from 0 to 1 or
                    ence (or inheritance). The Hebbian property need not reside                  vice versa, the change of the energy defined in Eq. 7 can be
                    in single synapses; small groups ofcells which produce such a                split into two terms, one ofwhich is always negative. The second
                    net effect would suffice.                                                    is identical if Ty1 is symmetric and is "stochastic" with mean 0
                       The network of cells we describe performs an abstract cal-                if Tij and Tji are randomly chosen. The algorithm for Tij # Tj,
                    culation and, for applications, the inputs should be appropri-               therefore changes E in a fashion similar to the way E would
                    ately coded. In visual processing, for example, feature extrac-              change in time for a symmetric Tij but with an algorithm cor-
                    tion should previously have been done. The present modeling                  responding to a finite temperature.
                    mightthenberelatedtohowanentityorGestaltisremembered                            About 0.15 N states can be simultaneously remembered be-
                    or categorized on the basis of inputs representing a collection             fore error in recall is severe. Computer modeling of memory
                    of its features.                                                             storage according to Eq. 2 was carried out for N = 30 and N
                    Studies of the collective behaviors of the model                             = 100. n random memory states were chosen and the corre-
                    The model has stable limit points. Consider the special case T               sponding T.9 was generated. Ifa nervous system preprocessed
                    = Tji, and define                                                            signals for efficient storage, the preprocessed information
                                                                                                 wouldappearrandom (e.g., the coding sequences ofDNAhave
                                          E =-2                                        [7]       arandomcharacter). Therandom memoryvectorsthus simulate
                                                          TijVjVj                                efficiently encoded real information, as well as representing our
                                                     ioj                                         ignorance. The system was started at each assigned nominal
                    AE due to AV1 is given by                                                    memory state, and the state was allowed to evolve until
                                                                                                 stationary.results are shown in        2. The statistics are
                                          AE = -AVi         Tij Vj                     [8]          Typical                        Fig.                      averages
                                                        joi'                                     over both the states in a given matrix and different matrices.
                    Thus, the algorithm for altering Vi causes E to be a monotoni-               Withn=5, theassignedmemorystatesarealmostalways stable
                    cally decreasing function. State changes will continue until a               (and exactly recallable). For n = 15, about halfofthe nominally
                    least (local) E is reached. This case is isomorphic with an Ising            remembered states evolved to stable states with less than 5 er-
                    model. Tij provides the role ofthe exchange coupling, and there              rors, but the rest evolved to states quite different from the start-
                    is also an external local field at each site. When T.j is symmetric          ing points.           be understood from an              ofthe effect
                    but has a random character (the spin glass) there are known to                  Theseresults can                             analysis
                    be many (locally) stable states (29).                                        ofthenoise terms. In Eq. 3, H' is the "effective field" on neuron
                       Monte Carlo calculations were made on systems ofN = 30                    i when the state ofthe system is s', one ofthe nominal memory
                    and N = 100, to examine the effect of removing the T.1 = T.                  states. The expectation value of this sum, Eq. 4, is ±N/2 as
                    restriction. Each element ofT., was chosen as a random number                appropriate. The s # s' summation in Eq. 2 contributes no
                    between -1 and 1. The neural architecture of typical cortical                mean, but has a rms noise of[(n - 1)N/2]'2-a. For nN large,
                    regions (30, 31) and also of simple ganglia of invertebrates (32)            this noise is approximately Gaussian and the probability of an
                    suggests the importance of 100-10,000 cells with intense mu-                 error in a single particular bit of a particular memory will be
                    tual interconnections in elementary processing, so our scale of                                P=       1          e-x2/2a2 dx.
                    Nis slightly small.                                                                                      2                                     [10]
                       The dynamics algorithm was initiated from randomly chosen                                                   N/2
                    initial starting configurations. For N = 30 the system never
                    displayed an ergodic wandering through state space. Within a                 For the case n = 10, N = 100, P = 0.0091, the probability that
                    time ofabout 4/W it settled into limiting behaviors, the com-                a state had no errors in its 100 bits should be about eC0O9'    0.40.
                    monest being a stable state. When 50 trials were examined for                In the simulation of Fig. 2, the experimental number was 0.6.
                    a particular such random matrix, all would result in one of two                 The theoretical scaling of n with N at fixed P was demon-
                    or three end states. A few stable states thus collect the flow from          strated in the simulations going between N = 30 and N = 100.
                    most ofthe initial state space. A simple cycle also occurred oc-             The experimental results of half the memories being well re-
                    casionally-for example, .       A -* B -- A --    B                          tained at n = 0.15 N and the rest badly retained is expected to
    Downloaded from https://www.pnas.org by 50.47.140.49 on December 30, 2025 from IP address 50.47.140.49.
﻿                                                                                                 Biophysics: Hopfield                                                                                                                                                                                                                  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 79 (1982)                                                                                         2557
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             The modelwas studied by using a "clipped" Tij, replacing T4,
                                                                                      1.0                                                                                                                                                                                            in Eq. 3 by ± 1, the algebraic sign ofTij. The purposes were to
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      examinethenecessityofalinearsynapsesupposition (bymaking
                                                                                    0.5                                              N- 100                                                                                                                                           ahighly nonlinearone) and to examine the efficiency ofstorage.
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      Only N(N/2) bits of information can possibly be stored in this
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      symmetricmatrix. Experimentally, forN = 100, n =9, the level
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      of errors was similar to that for the ordinary algorithm at n =
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      12. The signal-to-noise ratio can be evaluated analytically for
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      this clipped algorithm and is reducedby afactorof(2/r)1"2 com-
                                                                                     0.5                                              n= 10                                                                                                                                           paredwiththeunclippedcase. Forafixed errorprobability, the
                                                                                                                                      N= 100                                                                                                                                          number ofmemories must be reduced by 2/ir.
                                                                         2&          0.2                                                                                                                                                                                                      With the 4 algorithm and the clipped Tij, both analysis and
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      modeling showed that the maximal information stored for N
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       = 100occurredataboutn = 13. Some errorswerepresent, and
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      the Shannon information stored corresponded to about N(N/
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       8) bits. memories can be                                                                                       added to Ti.. The addition
                                                                                      0.2                                              n=1                                                                                                                                                    New                                                                  continually                                                         the                              and
                                                                                      0.2                                              N= 100                                                                                                                                          ofnewmemoriesbeyondthecapacity overloads                                                                                                                   system
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       makesall memorystates irretrievable unless there is aprovision
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       for forgetting old memories (16, 27, 28).                                                                                        will itself cause for-
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              The saturation ofthe possible size of Tij
                                                                                                                 3            6             9                  10-              20- 30- 40- >49                                                                                        getting. Let the possible values of TY be 0, ± 1, ±2, ±3, and
                                                                                                                                                                   19              29 39 49                                                                                            Tt, be freely incremented within this range. If Tij = 3, a next
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       increment of +1 would be ignored and a next increment of
                                                                                                                 Nerr = Number of Errors in State                                                                                                                                       -1 would reduce Tij to 2. When Ty, is so constructed, only the
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       recent memory states are retained, with a slightly increased
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       noise level. Memoriesfrom the distantpastare no longer stable.
                                                                             FIG. 2.                  The probability distribution of the occurrence of errors in                                                                                                                       Howfar into the past are states remembered depends on the
                                                                       the location of the stable states obtained from nominally assigned                                                                                                                                               digitizing depth ofT., and 0,                                                                    ,   ±3is an appropriate level for
                                                                       memories.                                                                                                                                                                                                        N = 100. Other schemes can be used to keep too many mem-
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        ories from being simultaneously written, but this particular one
                                                                       be true for all large N. The information storage at a given level                                                                                                                                                is attractive because it requires no delicate balances and is a
                                                                       ofaccuracy can be increased by afactor of2 by ajudicious choice                                                                                                                                                  consequence ofnatural hardware.
                                                                       of individual neuron thresholds. This choice is equivalent to                                                                                                                                                            Real neurons need not make synapses both of i -- j and j
                                                                       using variables ip = ±1, Tij =                                                                       1,,u4,4j, and a threshold level                                                                                      i. Particular synapses are restricted to one sign ofoutput. We
                                                                       of 0.                                                                                                                                                                                                            therefore askedwhether Tij = Tjj is important. Simulationswere
                                                                               Given somearbitrary starting state, what is the resultingfinal                                                                                                                                           carried out with only one ij connection: if T- $0, T.i = 0. The
                                                                       state (or statistically, states)? To study this, evolutions from ran-                                                                                                                                            probability of making errors increased, but the algorithm con-
                                                                       domly chosen initial states were tabulated for N = 30 and n                                                                                                                                                      tinued to generate stable minima. A Gaussian noise description
                                                                        = 5. From the (inessential) symmetry of the algorithm, if                                                                                                                                                       of the error rate shows that the signal-to-noise ratio for given
                                                                        (101110                        ) is an assigned stable state, (010001 .) is also stable.                                                                                                                         n and N should be decreased by the factor 1/F2, and the sim-
                                                                       Therefore, the matrices had 10 nominal stable states. Approx-                                                                                                                                                     ulations were consistent with such a factor. This same analysis
                                                                        imately 85% ofthe trials ended in assigned memories, and 10%                                                                                                                                                     shows that the system generally fails in a "soft" fashion, with
                                                                        ended in stable states ofno obvious meaning. An ambiguous 5%                                                                                                                                                     signal-to-noise ratio and error rate increasing slowly as more
                                                                        landed in stable states very near assigned memories. There was                                                                                                                                                   synapses fail.                                                                                                  are confused and tend to
                                                                        a range of a factor of 20 of the likelihood of finding these 10                                                                                                                                                          Memories too close to each other memories should be
                                                                        states.                                                                                                                                                                                                          merge. ForN = 100, apairofrandom                                                                                                                                                sep-
                                                                               The algorithm leads to memories near the starting state. For                                                                                                                                              arated by 50 ± 5 Hamming units. The case N = 100, n = 8,
                                                                        N=30, n = 5, partially random starting states were generated                                                                                                                                                     was studied with seven random memories and the eighth made
                                                                        by random modification of known memories. The probability                                                                                                                                                        up a Hamming distance of only 30, 20, or 10 from one of the
                                                                        that the final state was that closest to the initial state was studied                                                                                                                                           other seven memories. At a distance of30, both similar mem-
                                                                        as a function of the distance between the initial state and the                                                                                                                                                  ories were usually stable. At a distance of20, the minima were
                                                                        nearest memory state. For distance c 5, the nearest state was                                                                                                                                                    usually distinct but displaced. At a distance of 10, the minima
                                                                        reached more than 90% ofthe time. Beyond that distance, the                                                                                                                                                      were often fused.
                                                                        probability fell off smoothly, dropping to a level of0.2 (2 times                                                                                                                                                       The algorithm categorizes initial states according to the sim-
                                                                        random chance) for a distance of 12.                                                                                                                                                                             ilarity to memory states. With a threshold of0, the system be-
                                                                                The phase spaceflow is apparently dominated by attractors                                                                                                                                                haves as a forced categorizer.
                                                                        which are the nominally assignedmemories, each ofwhich dom-                                                                                                                                                             The state 00000 ... is always stable. For a threshold of0, this
                                                                        inates a substantial region around it. The flow is not entirely                                                                                                                                                  stable state is much higher in energy than the stored memory
                                                                        deterministic, and the system responds to an ambiguous start-                                                                                                                                                    states and very seldom occurs. Adding a uniform threshold in
                                                                        ing state by a statistical choice between the memory states it                                                                                                                                                   the algorithm is equivalent to raising the effective energy ofthe
                                                                        most resembles.                                                                                                                                                                                                  stored memories compared to the 0000 state, and 0000 also
                                                                                Were it desired to use such a system in an Si-based content-                                                                                                                                             becomes a likely stable state. The 0000 state is then generated
                                                                        addressable memory, the algorithm should be used and modi-                                                                                                                                                       by any initial state that does not resemble adequately closely
                                                                        fied to hold the known bits ofinformation while letting the oth-                                                                                                                                                 one of the assigned memories and represents positive recog-
                                                                         ers adjust.                                                                                                                                                                                                     nition that the starting state is not familiar.
           Downloaded from https://www.pnas.org by 50.47.140.49 on December 30, 2025 from IP address 50.47.140.49.
﻿                   0rl
                   ,2558      Biophysics: Hopfield                                                                Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 79 (1982)
                      Familiarity can be recognized by other means when the                    nervous systems may be the spontaneous emergence of new
                   memory is drastically overloaded. We examined the case N                    computational capabilities from the collective behavior oflarge
                   = 100, n = 500, in which there is a memory overload ofafactor               numbers ofsimple processing elements.
                   of25. None ofthe memory states assigned were stable. The ini-                  Implementation of a similar model by using integrated cir-
                   tial rate ofprocessing ofa starting state is defined as the number          cuits would lead to chips which are much less sensitive to ele-
                   of neuron state readjustments that occur in a time 1/2W. Fa-                 mentfailureandsoft-failure thanarenormalcircuits. Suchchips
                   miliar and unfamiliar states were distinguishable most of the               wouldbewastefulofgatesbutcouldbemademanytimeslarger
                   time at this level ofoverload on the basis ofthe initial processing          than standard designs at a given yield. Their asynchronous par-
                   rate, which was faster for unfamiliar states. This kind offamil-            allel processingcapabilitywouldprovide rapidsolutionsto some
                   iarity can only be read out of the system by a class ofneurons               special classes ofcomputational problems.
                   or devices abstracting average properties of the processing                    TheworkatCalifornia Institute ofTechnology was supported
                   group.                                                                       by National Science Foundation Grant DMR-8107494. This is in part
                      For the cases so far considered, the expectation value of Tij             bution no. 6580 from the Division of Chemistry and            contri-
                   was 0 for i # j. A set of memories can be stored with average                Engineering.                                               Chemical
                   correlations, and Ty = Cij # 0 because there is a consistent in-
                   ternal correlation in the memories. If now a partial new state               1.  Willows, A. 0. D., Dorsett, D. A. & Hoyle, G. (1973)J. Neu-
                   Xis stored                                                                        robiol 4, 207-237, 255-285.
                                      = (2Xi-1)(2Xj-1)           -- k < N           [ill        2.   Kristan, W. B. (1980) in Information Processing in the Nervous
                                 ATUj                         Q~                                     System, eds. Pinsker, H. M. & Willis, W. D. (Raven, New York),
                   using only k of the neurons rather than N, an attempt to re-                     241-261.    W.                               111-144.
                   construct it will generate a stable point for all N neurons. The             3.   Knight, B.     (1975) Lect. Math. Life Sci. 5,
                   values of Xk+l-.XN*    that result will be determined primarily              4.   Smith, D. R. & Davidson, C. H. (1962)J. Assoc. Comput. Mach.
                   from the sign of                                                                 9, 268-279.           in                and            ed.
                                                                                                5.   Harmon, L. D. (1964)    Neural Theory      Modeling,     Reiss,
                                                   k                                                 R. F. (Stanford Univ. Press, Stanford, CA), pp. 23-24.
                                                 ECij Xj                            [12]        6.   Amari, S.-I. (1977) Bio. Cybern. 26, 175-185.
                                                 j=1                                            7.   Amari, S.-I. & Akikazu, T. (1978) Biol Cybern. 29, 127-136.
                   and X is completed according to the mean correlations of the                 8.   Little, W. A. (1974) Math. Biosci. 19, 101-120.
                                                                                                9.   Marr, J. (1969)J. Physiol 202, 437-470.
                   other memories. The most effective implementation ofthis ca-                10.   Kohonen, T. (1980) Content Addressable Memories (Springer,
                   pacity stores a large number ofcorrelated matrices weakly fol-                    NewYork).       Biol             19-31.
                   lowed by a normal storage ofX.                                              11.   Palm, G. (1980)      Cybern. 36,
                      AnonsymmetricT..canleadtothepossibility thataminimum                     12.   McCulloch, W. S. & Pitts, W. (1943) BulL Math Biophys. 5,
                   will be only metastable and will be replaced in time by another             13.   115-133.M. &          S.                     An Introduction to
                   minimum. Additional nonsymmetric terms which could be eas-                        Minsky,       Papert,    (1969) Perceptrons:
                                                                                                     Computational Geometry (MIT Press, Cambridge, MA). Wash-
                   ily generated by a minor modification of Hebb synapses                       14.  Rosenblatt, F. (1962) Principles ofPerceptrons (Spartan,
                                                                                                     ington, DC).                           the Nobel             on
                                         = A > (2Vs+1 - 1)(2Vj- 1)                  [13]       15.   Cooper, L. N. (1973) in Proceedings of           Symposium
                                   ATU                                                               Collective Properties ofPhysical Systems, eds. Lundqvist, B. &
                                               S                                                     Lundqvist, S. (Academic, New York), 252-264.
                   wereaddedtoT . WhenAwasjudiciouslyadjusted, the system                       16.  Cooper, L. N., Liberman, F. & Oja, E. (1979) Biol Cybern. 33,
                   would spend a while near V. and then leave and go to a point                 17.  9-28.               C.        Proc.     Soc. London Ser. B
                   near V,+,. But sequences longer than four states proved im-                       Longuet-Higgins, J.    (1968)      Roy.                    171,
                   possible to generate, and even these were not faithfully                     18.  327-334.            C.        Nature                104-105.
                   followed.                                                                         Longuet-Higgins, J.    (1968)         (London) 217,
                                                                                                19.  Kohonen, T. (1977) Associative Memory-A System-Theoretic
                   Discussion                                                                        Approach (Springer, New York).          181-198.
                                                                                               20.   Willwacher, G. (1976) Biol Cybern. 24,
                   Inthemodelnetworkeach"neuron"haselementaryproperties,                       21.   Anderson, J. A. (1977) Psych. Rev. 84, 413-451.      Res.
                   and the network has little structure. Nonetheless, collective               22.   Perkel, D. H. & Bullock, T. H. (1969) Neurosci.           Symp.
                   computational properties spontaneously arose. Memories are                        Summ. 3, 405-527.              850-864.
                   retained as stable entities or Gestalts and can be correctly re-             23.  John, E. R. (1972) Science 177,            L.        Brain Res.
                                                                                                24.  Roney, K. J., Scheibel, A. B. & Shaw, G.      (1979)
                   called from any reasonably sized subpart. Ambiguities are re-                     Rev. 1, 225-271.       G. L.       Math. Biosci.     281-289.
                   solved on a statistical basis. Some capacity for generalization is           25.  Little, W. A. & Shaw,        (1978)              39,  146-150.
                   present, and time ordering of memories can also be encoded.                  26.  Shaw, G. L. & Roney, K. J. (1979) Phys. Rev. Lett. 74,
                   These properties follow from the nature of the flow in phase                 27.  Hebb, D. 0. (1949) The Organization ofBehavior (Wiley, New
                   space produced by the processing algorithm, which does not                   28.  York).    G.        The                     Basis   Mind
                   appear to be strongly dependent on precise details ofthe mod-                     Eccles, J.   (1953)     Neurophysiological        of      (Clar-
                                                                                                     endon, Oxford).              D.             Rev.     4384-4403.
                   eling. This robustness suggests that similar effects will obtain             29.  Kirkpatrick, S. & Sherrington,   (1978) Phys.    17,
                   even when more neurobiological details are added.                            30.  Mountcastle, V. B. (1978) in The Mindful Brain, eds. Edelman,
                      Much ofthe architecture of regions of the brains of higher                     G. M. & Mountcastle, V. B. (MIT Press, Cambridge, MA), pp.
                   animals must be made from a proliferation of simple local cir-               31.  36-41.     P.  S. &          W.     H.         Brain Res.
                   cuits with well-defined functions. The bridge between simple                      Goldman,             Nauta,      J.     (1977)              122,
                                                                                                     393-413.                 Am.       61-70.
                   circuits and the complex computational properties of higher                  32.  Kandel, E. R. (1979) Sci.     241,
    Downloaded from https://www.pnas.org by 50.47.140.49 on December 30, 2025 from IP address 50.47.140.49.
