                                                Syntax-Guided Synthesis
                                 †                        ‡                          ‡                             †                             †
                   Rajeev Alur          Rastislav Bodik            Garvit Juniwal            Milo M. K. Martin        Mukund Raghothaman
                                    ‡                    ]                                ]                     ‡                            †
                 Sanjit A. Seshia       Rishabh Singh         Armando Solar-Lezama              Emina Torlak              Abhishek Udupa
                  †University of Pennsylvania           ‡University of California, Berkeley            ]Massachusetts Institute of Technology
                Abstract—The classical formulation of the program-synthesis       the potential of even greater impact on software quality than
             problem is to ﬁnd a program that meets a correctness speciﬁca-       program veriﬁcation. Classically, program synthesis is viewed
             tion given as a logical formula. Recent work on program synthesis    as a problem in deductive theorem proving: a program is
             and program optimization illustrates many potential beneﬁts          derived from the constructive proof of the theorem that states
             of allowing the user to supplement the logical speciﬁcation          that for all inputs, there exists an output, such that the desired
             with a syntactic template that constrains the space of allowed
             implementations. Our goal is to identify the core computational      correctness speciﬁcation holds (see [3]). Our work is motivated
             problem common to these proposals in a logical framework. The        by a recent trend in synthesis in which the programmer, in
             input to the syntax-guided synthesis problem (SyGuS) consists        addition to the correctness speciﬁcation, provides a syntactic
             of a background theory, a semantic correctness speciﬁcation          template for the desired program. For instance, in the pro-
             for the desired program given by a logical formula, and a            gramming approach advocated by the SKETCH system, a pro-
             syntactic set of candidate implementations given by a grammar.
             The computational problem then is to ﬁnd an implementation           grammer writes a partial program with incomplete details, and
             from the set of candidate expressions so that it satisﬁes the        the synthesizer ﬁlls in the missing details using user-speciﬁed
             speciﬁcation in the given theory. We describe three different        assertions as the correctness speciﬁcation [4]. We call such
             instantiations of the counter-example-guided-inductive-synthesis     an approach to synthesis syntax-guided synthesis (SyGuS).
             (CEGIS) strategy for solving the synthesis problem, report on        Besides program sketching, a number of recent efforts such as
             prototype implementations, and present experimental results on
             an initial set of benchmarks.                                        synthesis of loop-free programs [5], synthesis of Excel macros
                                    I. INTRODUCTION                               from examples [6], program de-obfuscation [7], synthesis of
                                                                                  protocols from the skeleton and example behaviors [8], synthe-
                In program veriﬁcation, we want to check if a program             sis of loop-bodies from pre/post conditions [9], integration of
             satisﬁes its logical speciﬁcation. Contemporary veriﬁcation          constraint solvers in programming environments for program
             tools vary widely in terms of source languages, veriﬁcation          completion [10], and super-optimization by ﬁnding equivalent
             methodology, and the degree of automation, but they all              shorter loop bodies [11], all are arguably instances of syntax-
             rely on repeatedly invoking an SMT (Satisﬁability Modulo             guided synthesis. Also related are techniques for automatic
             Theories) solver. An SMT solver determines the truth of              generation of invariants using templates and by learning [12]–
             a given logical formula built from typed variables, logical          [14], and recent work on solving quantiﬁed Horn clauses [15].
             connectives, and typical operations such as arithmetic and             Existing formalization of the SMT problem and the in-
             array accesses (see [1], [2]). Despite the computational in-         terchange format does not provide a suitable abstraction for
             tractability of these problems, modern SMT solvers are ca-           capturing the syntactic guidance. The computational engines
             pable of solving instances with thousands of variables due           used by the various synthesis projects mentioned above rely
             to sustained innovations in core algorithms, data structures,        on a small set of algorithmic ideas, but have evolved inde-
             decision heuristics, and performance tuning by exploiting            pendently with no mechanism for comparison, benchmarking,
             the architecture of contemporary processors. A key driving           and sharing of back-ends. The main contribution of this paper
             force for this progress has been the standardization of a            is to deﬁne the syntax-guided synthesis (SyGuS) problem in
             common interchange format for benchmarks called SMT-LIB              a manner that (1) captures the computational essence of these
             (see smt-lib.org) and the associated annual competition (see         recent proposals and (2) is based on more canonical formal
             smtcomp.org). These efforts have proved to be instrumental           frameworks such as logics and grammars instead of features
             in creating a virtuous feedback loop between developers and          of speciﬁc programming languages. In our formalization, the
             users of SMT solvers: with the availability of open-source           correctness speciﬁcation of the function f to be synthesized
             and highly optimized solvers, researchers from veriﬁcation           is given as a logical formula ϕ that uses symbols from a
             and other application domains ﬁnd it beneﬁcial to translate          background theory T. The syntactic space of possible im-
             their problems into the common format instead of attempting          plementations for f is described as a set L of expressions
             to develop their own customized tools from scratch, and the          built from the theory T, and this set is speciﬁed using a
             limitations of the current SMT tools are constantly exposed by       grammar. The syntax-guided synthesis problem then is to ﬁnd
             the ever growing repository of different kinds of benchmarks,        an implementation expression e ∈ L such that the formula
             thereby spurring greater innovation for improving the solvers.       ϕ[f/e] is valid in the theory T. To illustrate an application of
                In program synthesis, we wish to automatically synthesize         the SyGuS-problem, suppose we want to ﬁnd a completion of
             an implementation for the program that satisﬁes the given            a partial program with holes so as to satisfy given assertions.
             correctness speciﬁcation. A mature synthesis technology has          A typical SyGuS-encoding of this task will translate the
﻿             concrete parts of the partial program and the assertions into         to a ﬁrst order formula in the background theory with all
             the speciﬁcation formula ϕ, while the holes will be represented       its variables universally quantiﬁed, and (3) the universe of
             with the unknown functions to be synthesized, and the space           possible functions f is restricted to syntactic expressions
             of expressions that can substitute the holes will be captured         described by a grammar. We now elaborate on each of these
             by the grammar.                                                       points.
                Compared to the classical formulation of the synthesis               Background Theory: The syntax for writing speciﬁcations is
             problem that involves only the correctness speciﬁcation, the          the same as classical typed ﬁrst-order logic, but the formulas
             syntax-guided version has many potential beneﬁts. First, the          are evaluated with respect to a speciﬁed background theory
             user can use the candidate set L to limit the search-space for        T. The theory gives the vocabulary used for constructing
             potential implementations, and this has signiﬁcant computa-           formulas, the set of values for each type, and the interpretation
             tional beneﬁts for solving the synthesis problem. Second, this        for each of the function and relation (predicate) symbols in
             approach gives the programmer the ﬂexibility to express the           the vocabulary. We are mainly interested in theories T for
             desired artifact using a combination of syntactic and semantic        which well-understood decision procedures are available for
             constraints. Such forms of multi-modal speciﬁcations have the         determining satisfaction modulo T (see [1] for a survey).
             potential to make programming more intuitive. Third, the set          A typical example is the theory of linear integer arithmetic
             L can be used to constrain the space of implementations for           (LIA) where each variable is either a boolean or an integer,
             the purpose of performance optimizations. For example, to             and the vocabulary consists of boolean and integer constants,
             optimize the computation of the product of two two-by-two             standard boolean connectives, addition (+), comparison (≤),
             matrices, we can limit the search space to implementations that       and conditionals (ITE). Note that the background theory can
             use only 7 multiplication operations, and such a restriction can      be a combination of logical theories, for instance, LIA and the
             be expressed only syntactically. Fourth, because the synthesis        theory of uninterpreted functions with equality.
             problem boils down to ﬁnding a correct expression from the              Correctness Speciﬁcation: For the function f to be syn-
             syntactic space of expressions, this search problem lends itself      thesized, we are given the type of f and a formula ϕ as
             to machine learning and inductive inference as discussed in           its correctness speciﬁcation. The formula ϕ is a Boolean
             Section III. Finally, it is worth noting that the statement “there    combination of predicates from the background theory, in-
             exists an expression e in the language generated by a context-        volving universally quantiﬁed free variables, symbols from the
             free grammar G such that the formula ϕ[f/e] is valid in a             background theory, and the function symbol f, all used in a
             theory T” cannot be translated to determining the truth of a          type-consistent manner.
             formula in the theory T, even with additional quantiﬁers.               Example 1: Assuming the background theory is LIA, con-
                The rest of the paper is organized in the following manner.        sider the speciﬁcation of a function f of type int×int 7→ int:
             In Section II, we formalize the core problem of syntax-                          ϕ : f(x,y) = f(y,x) ∧ f(x,y) ≥ x.
             guided synthesis with examples. In Section III, we discuss                         1
             a generic architecture for solving the proposed problem us-           The free variables in the speciﬁcation are assumed to be
             ing the iterative counter-example guided inductive synthesis          universally quantiﬁed: a given function f satisﬁes the above
             strategy [16] that combines a learning algorithm with a ver-          speciﬁcation if the quantiﬁed formula ∀x,y.ϕ1 holds, or
             iﬁcation oracle. For the learning algorithm, we show how              equivalently, if the formula ϕ is valid.
                                                                                                                  1
             three techniques from recent literature can be adapted for our          Set of Candidate Expressions: In order to make the synthe-
             purpose: the enumerative technique generates the candidate            sis problem tractable, the “syntax-guided” version allows the
             expressions of increasing size relying on the input-output            user to impose structural (syntactic) constraints on the set of
             examples for pruning; the symbolic technique encodes parse            possible functions f. The structural constraints are imposed
             trees of increasing size using variables and constraints, and         by restricting f to the set L of functions deﬁned by a given
             it calls an SMT solver to ﬁnd a parse tree consistent with            context-free grammar GL. Each expression in L has the same
             all the examples encountered so far; and the stochastic search        type as that of the function f, and uses the symbols in the
             uniformly samples the set L of expressions as a starting point,       background theory T along with the variables corresponding
             and then executes (probabilistic) traversal of the graph where        to the formal parameters of f.
             two expressions are neighbors if one can be obtained from               Example 2: Suppose the background theory is LIA, and the
             the other by a single edit operation on the parse tree. We            type of the function f is int×int 7→ int. We can restrict the set
             report on a prototype implementation of these three algorithms,       of expressions f(x,y) to be linear expressions of the inputs
             and evaluate their performance on a number of benchmarks in           by restricting the body of the function to expressions in the
             Section IV.                                                           set L1 described by the grammar below:
                              II. PROBLEM FORMULATION                                       LinExp := x | y | Const | LinExp + LinExp
                At a high level, the functional synthesis problem consists         Alternatively, we can restrict f(x,y) to conditional expres-
             of ﬁnding a function f such that some logical formula ϕ               sions with no addition by restricting the body terms from the
             capturing the correctness of f is valid. In syntax-guided             set L2 described by:
             synthesis, the synthesis problem is constrained in three ways:         Term := x|y|Const|ITE(Cond,Term,Term)
             (1) the logical symbols and their interpretation are restricted
             to a background theory, (2) the speciﬁcation ϕ is limited              Cond := Term≤Term|Cond∧Cond|¬Cond|(Cond)
﻿             Grammars can be conveniently used to express a wide range           fundamentally increase the expressiveness of the notation,
             of constraints, and in particular, to bound the depth and/or the    it does offer signiﬁcant convenience in encoding real-world
             size of the desired expression.                                     synthesis problems.
                SyGuS Problem Deﬁnition: Informally, given the correct-            Let Expressions in Grammar Productions: The SMT-LIB
             ness speciﬁcation ϕ and the set L of candidates, we want            interchange format for specifying constraints allows the use of
             to ﬁnd an expression e ∈ L such that if we use e as                 let expressions as part of the formulas, and this is supported by
             an implementation of the function f, the speciﬁcation ϕ is          our language also: (let [var = e ] e ). While let-expressions
                                                                                                                  1    2
             valid. Let us denote the result of replacing each occurrence        in a speciﬁcation can be desugared, the same does not hold
             of the function symbol f in ϕ with the expression e by              when they are used in a grammar. As an example, consider
             ϕ[f/e]. Note that we need to take care of binding of input          the grammar below for the set of candidate expressions for
             values during such a substitution: if f has two inputs that the     the function f(x,y):
             expressions in L refer to by the variable names x and y, then               T := (let [z = U] z +z)
             the occurrence f(e ,e ) in the formula ϕ must be replaced
                                 1   2                                                   U := x|y|Const|U +U |U ∗U |(U)
             with the expression e[x/e1,y/e2] obtained by replacing x and
             y in e by the expressions e and e , respectively. Now we can
                                         1      2                                The top-level expression speciﬁed by this grammar is the
             deﬁne the syntax-guided synthesis problem, SyGuS for short,         sum of two identical subexpressions built using arithmetic
             precisely:                                                          operators, and such a structure cannot be speciﬁed using a
                  Given a background theory T, a typed function                  standard context-free grammar. In the example above, every
                  symbol f, a formula ϕ over the vocabulary of T                 let introduced by the grammar uses the same variable name. If
                  along with f, and a set L of expressions over the              the application of let-expressions are nested in the derivation
                  vocabulary of T and of the same type as f, ﬁnd an              tree, the standard rules for shadowing of variable deﬁnitions
                  expression e ∈ L such that the formula ϕ[f/e] is               determine which deﬁnition corresponds to which use of the
                  valid modulo T.                                                variable.
                Example 3: For the speciﬁcation ϕ presented earlier, if the        SYNTH-LIB Input Format: To specify the input to the
                                                    1                            SyGuS problem, we have developed an interchange format,
             set of allowed implementations is L1 as shown before, there         called SYNTH-LIB, based on the syntax of SMT-LIB2—the
             is no solution to the synthesis problem. On the other hand, if      input format accepted by the SMT solvers (see smt-lib.org).
             the set of allowed implementations is L2, a possible solution       The input for the SyGuS problem to synthesize the function f
             is the conditional if-then-else expression ITE(x ≥ y,x,y).          with the speciﬁcation ϕ in the theory LIA, with the grammar
                In some special cases, it is possible to reduce the deci-                                1
                                                                                 for the languages L is encoded in SYNTH-LIB as:
             sion problem for syntax guided synthesis to the problem of                              1
             deciding formulas in the background theory using additional              (set-logic LIA)
             quantiﬁcation. For example, every expression in the set L is             (synth-fun f ((x Int) (y Int)) Int
                                                                          1             ((Start Int (x y
             equivalent to ax+by+c, for integer constants a,b,c. If ϕ is the                              (Constant Int)
             correctness speciﬁcation, then deciding whether there exists an                              (+ Start Start)))))
             implementation for f in the set L1 corresponds to checking               (declare-var a Int)
             whether the formula ∃a,b,c.∀X.ϕ[f/ax + by + c] holds,                    (declare-var b Int)
             where X is the set of all free variables in ϕ. This reduction            (constraint (= (f a b) (f b a)))
             was possible for L because the set of all expressions in L               (constraint (>= (f a b) a))
                                 1                                          1         (check-synth)
             can be represented by a single parameterized expression in the        Optimality Criterion: The answer to our synthesis problem
             original theory. However, the grammar may permit expressions        need not be unique: there may be two expressions e1 and e2 in
             of arbitrary depth which may not be representable in this way,      the set L of allowed expressions such that both implementa-
             as in the case of L2.                                               tions satisfy the correctness speciﬁcation ϕ. Ideally, we would
                Synthesis of Multiple Functions: A general synthesis prob-       like to associate a cost with each expression, and consider the
             lemcaninvolve more than one unknown function. In principle,         problem of optimal synthesis which requires the synthesis tool
             adding support for problems with more than one unknown              to return the expression with the least cost among the correct
             function is merely a matter of syntactic sugar. For exam-           ones. A natural cost metric is the size of the expression. In
             ple, suppose we want to synthesize functions f (x ) and
                                                                   1  1          presence of let-expressions, the size directly corresponds to the
             f (x ), with corresponding candidate expressions given by
              2   2                                                              number of instructions in the corresponding straight-line code,
             grammars G and G , with start non-terminals S and S ,
                          1         2                              1        2    and thus such a metric can be used effectively for applications
             respectively. Both functions can be encoded with a single           such as super-optimization.
             function f (id,x ,x ). The set of candidate expressions is
                        12      1  2                                                              III. INDUCTIVE SYNTHESIS
             described by the grammar that contains the rules of G and
                                                                        1
             G along with a new production S := ITE(id = 0,S ,S ),                 Algorithmic approaches to program synthesis range over a
               2                                                       1   2
             with the new start non-terminal S. Then, every occurrence of        widespectrum, from deductive synthesis to inductive synthesis.
             f (x ) in the speciﬁcation can be replaced with f      (0,x ,∗)     In deductive program synthesis (e.g., [3]), a program is synthe-
              1   1                                               12     1
             and every call to f (x ) can be replaced with f (1,∗,x ).           sized by constructively proving a theorem, employing logical
                                  2  2                           12        2
             Although adding support for multiple functions does not             inference and constraint solving. On the other hand, inductive
﻿                 synthesis [17]–[19] seeks to ﬁnd a program matching a set                                        INITIALIZE       “Concept Class”, Initial Examples
                 of input-output examples. It is thus an instance of learning
                 from examples, also termed as inductive inference or machine
                 learning [20], [21]. Many current approaches to synthesis                                                             Candidate
                 blend induction and deduction [22]; syntax guidance is usually                                                         Concept
                 a key ingredient in these approaches.
                    Inductive synthesizers generalize from examples by search-                                    LEARNING                               VERIFICATION
                 ing a restricted space of programs. In machine learning, this                                   ALGORITHM                                   ORACLE
                 restricted space is called the concept class, and each element                                                    Counterexample
                 of that space is often called a candidate concept. The concept
                 class is usually speciﬁed syntactically. Inductive learning is                                   Learning Fails                         Learning Succeeds
                 thus a natural ﬁt for the syntax-guided synthesis problem
                 introduced in this paper: the concept class is simply the set L                              Fig. 1.   Counterexample-Guided Inductive Synthesis (CEGIS)
                 of permissible expressions.                                                           repair in the former case, and synthesizing an abstraction
                 A. Synthesis via Active Learning                                                      function in the latter (see [22] for a more detailed discussion).
                                                                                                          The deﬁning aspect of CEGIS is its example selection strat-
                    Acommon approach to inductive synthesis is to formulate                            egy: learning from counterexamples provided by a veriﬁcation
                 the overall synthesis problem as one of active learning using                         oracle. The learning algorithm, which is initialized with a
                 a query-based model. Active learning is a special case of                             particular choice of concept class L and possibly with an initial
                 machine learning in which the learning algorithm can control                          set of (positive) examples, proceeds by searching the space of
                 the selection of examples that it generalizes from and can                            candidate concepts for one that is consistent with the examples
                 query one or more oracles to obtain both examples as well as                          seen so far. There may be several such consistent concepts,
                 labels for those examples. In our setting, we can consider the                        and the search strategy determines the chosen candidate, an
                 labels to be binary: positive or negative. A positive example                         expression e. The concept e is then presented to the veriﬁcation
                 is simply an interpretation to f in the background theory                             oracle O , which checks the candidate against the correctness
                                                                                                                  V
                 T that is consistent with the speciﬁcation ϕ; i.e., it is a                           speciﬁcation. OV can be implemented as an SMT solver that
                 valuation to the arguments of the function symbol f along with                        checks whether ϕ[f/e] is valid modulo the theory T. If the
                 the corresponding valuation of f that satisﬁes ϕ. A negative                          candidate is correct, the synthesizer terminates and outputs this
                 example is any interpretation of f that is not consistent with ϕ.                     candidate. Otherwise, the veriﬁcation oracle generates a coun-
                 Werefer the reader to a paper by Angluin [23] for an overview                         terexample, an interpretation to the symbols and free variables
                 of various models for query-based active learning.                                    in ϕ[f/e] that falsiﬁes it. This counterexample is returned to
                    In program synthesis via active learning, the query oracles                        the learning algorithm, which adds the counterexample to its
                 are often implemented using deductive procedures such as                              set of examples and repeats its search; note that the precise
                 model checkers or satisﬁability solvers. Thus, the overall                            encoding of a counterexample and its use can vary depending
                 synthesis algorithm usually comprises a top-level inductive                           onthedetails of the learning algorithm employed. It is possible
                 learning algorithm that invokes deductive procedures (query                           that, after some number of iterations of this loop, the learning
                 oracles); e.g., in our problem setting, it is intuitive, although                     algorithm may be unable to ﬁnd a candidate concept consistent
                 not required, to implement an oracle using an SMT solver for                          with its current set of (positive/negative) examples, in which
                 the theory T. Even though this approach combines induction                            case the learning step, and hence the overall CEGIS procedure,
                 and deduction, it is usually referred to in the literature simply                     fails.
                 as “inductive synthesis.” We will continue to use this termi-                            Several search strategies are possible for learning a can-
                 nology in the present paper.                                                          didate expression in L, each with its pros and cons. In the
                    Consider the syntax-guided synthesis problem of Sec. II.                           following sections, we describe three different search strategies
                 Given the tuple (T, f, ϕ, L), there are two important choices                         and illustrate the main ideas in each using a small example.
                 one must make to ﬁx an inductive synthesis algorithm: (1)
                 search strategy: How should one search the concept class L?                           C. Illustrative Example
                 and (2) example selection strategy: Which examples do we
                 learn from?                                                                              Consider the problem of synthesizing a program which
                                                                                                       returns the maximum of two integer inputs. The speciﬁcation
                 B. Counterexample-Guided Inductive Synthesis                                          of the desired program max is given by:
                    Counterexample-guided inductive synthesis (CEGIS) [16],
                 [24] shown in Figure 1 is perhaps the most popular approach                                           max(x,y) ≥ x ∧ max(x,y) ≥ y ∧
                 to inductive synthesis today. CEGIS has close connections                                                 (max(x,y) = x∨max(x,y) = y)
                 to algorithmic debugging using counterexamples [19] and
                 counterexample-guided abstraction reﬁnement (CEGAR) [25].                                The search space is suitably deﬁned by an expression
                 This connection is no surprise, because both debugging and                            grammar which includes addition, subtraction, comparison,
                 abstraction-reﬁnement involve synthesis steps: synthesizing a                         conditional operators and the integer constants 0 and 1.
﻿             Expression to Veriﬁer                        Learned Test Input          Production              Component
                                                                                      E→ITE(B,E,E) Inputs:                    (i : B)(i ,i : E)
                        x                                   hx = 0,y = 1i                                                       1       2  3
                        y                                   hx = 1,y = 0i                                     Output:         (o : E)
                                                                                                              Spec:           o = ITE(i ,i ,i )
                        1                                   hx = 0,y = 0i                                                               1  2   3
                                                                                      B→E≤E                   Inputs:         (i ,i : E)
                      x+y                                   hx = 1,y = 1i                                                       1  2
                ITE(x ≤ y,y,x)                                     –                                          Output:         (o : B)
                                                                                                              Spec:           o = i ≤ i
                                                                                                                                   1     2
                                          TABLE I                                                              TABLE II
                           ARUNOFTHEENUMERATIVEALGORITHM                                            COMPONENTSFROMPRODUCTIONS
             D. Enumerative Learning                                               E. Constraint-based Learning
                The enumerative learning algorithm [8] adopts a dynamic              The symbolic CEGIS approach uses a constraint solver
             programming based search strategy that systematically enu-            both for searching for a candidate expression that works
             merates concepts (expressions) in increasing order of complex-        for a set of concrete input examples (concept learning) and
             ity. Various complexity metrics can be assigned to concepts,          veriﬁcation of validity of an expression for all possible inputs.
             the simplest being the expression size. The algorithm needs           We use component based synthesis of loop-free programs
             to store all enumerated expressions, because expressions of           as described by Jha et al. [5], [7]. Each production in the
             a given size are composed to form larger expressions in the           grammar corresponds to a component in a library. A loop-
             spirit of dynamic programming. The algorithm maintains a              free program comprising these components corresponds to an
             set of concrete test cases, obtained from the counterexamples         expression from the grammar. Some sample components for
             returned by the veriﬁcation oracle. These concrete test cases         the illustrative example are shown in Table II along with their
             are used to reduce the number of expressions stored at each           corresponding productions.
             step by the dynamic programming algorithm.                              The input/output ports of these components are typed and
                We demonstrate the working of the algorithm on the illus-          only well-typed programs correspond to well-formed expres-
             trative example. Table I shows the expressions submitted to           sions from the grammar. To ensure this, Jha et al.’s encod-
             the veriﬁcation oracle (an SMT solver) during the execution of        ing [5] is extended with typing constraints. We illustrate the
             the algorithm and the values for which the expression produces        working of this algorithm on the maximum of two integers
             incorrect results. Initially, the algorithm submits the expression    example. The library of allowed components is instantiated
             x to the veriﬁer. The veriﬁer returns a counterexample hx =           to contain one instance each of ITE and all comparison
             0,y = 1i, corresponding to the case where the expression              operators(≤,≥,=) and the concrete example set is initialized
             x violates the speciﬁcation. The expression enumeration is            with hx = 0,y = 0i. The ﬁrst candidate loop-free program
             started from scratch every time a counterexample is added. All        synthesized corresponds to the expression x. This candidate
             enumerated expressions are checked for conformance with the           is submitted to the veriﬁcation oracle which returns with
             accumulated (counter)examples before making a potentially-            hx = −1,y = 0i as a counterexample. This counterexample is
             expensive query to the veriﬁer. In addition, suppose the              added to the concrete example set and the learning algorithm
             algorithm enumerates two expressions e and e0 which evaluate          is queried again. The SMT formula for learning a candidate
             to the same value on the examples obtained so far, then only          expression is solved in an incremental fashion; i.e., the con-
             one of e or e0 needs to be considered for the purpose of              straint for every new example is added to the list of constraints
             constructing larger expressions.                                      from the previous examples. The steps of the algorithm on the
                Proceeding with the illustrative example, the algorithm then       illustrative example are shown in Table III.
             submits the expression y and the constant 1 to the veriﬁer. The         If synthesis fails for a component library, we add one in-
             veriﬁer returns the values hx = 1,y = 0i and hx = 0,y =               stance of every operator to the library and restart the algorithm
             0i, respectively, as counterexamples to these expressions. The        with the new library. We also tried a modiﬁcation to the
             algorithm then submits the expression x+y to the veriﬁer. The         original algorithm [5], in which, instead of searching for a
             veriﬁer returns the values hx = 1,y = 1i as a counterexample.         loop-free program that utilizes all components from the given
             The algorithm then submits the expression shown in the last           library at once, we search for programs of increasing length
             row of Table I to the veriﬁer. The veriﬁer certiﬁes it to be          such that every line can still select any component from the
             correct and the algorithm terminates.                                 library. The program length is increased in an exponential
                The optimization of pruning based on concrete counterex-
             amples helps in two ways. First, it reduces the number of             Iteration   Loop-free program        Learned counter-example
             invocations of the veriﬁcation oracle. In the example we have            1        o :=x                         hx = −1,y = 0i
             described, the correct expression was examined after only                          1
             four calls to the SMT solver, although about 200 expressions             2        o1 := x ≤ x
                                                                                               o :=ITE(o , y, x)             hx = 0,y = −1i
             were enumerated by the algorithm. Second, it reduces the                           2           1
             search space for candidate expressions signiﬁcantly (see [8]             3        o1 := y ≥ x
                                                                                               o :=ITE(o , y, x)                     –
             for details). For instance, in the run of the algorithm on                         2           1
             the example, although the algorithm enumerated about 200                                          TABLE III
             expressions, only about 80 expressions were stored.                            ARUNOFTHECONSTRAINTLEARNINGALGORITHM
﻿             fashion (1, 2, 4, 8, ···) for a good coverage. This approach      code, and (3) since we do not know the expression size n, we
             provides better running times for most benchmarks in our set,     run concurrent searches for different values of n, whereas the
             but it can also be more expensive in certain cases.               super-optimizer can use the size of the input program as an
             F. Learning by Stochastic Search                                  upper bound on program size.
               The stochastic learning procedure is an adaptation of the                   IV. BENCHMARKS AND EVALUATION
             algorithm recently used by Schufza et al. [11] for program           We are in the process of assembling a benchmark suite
             super-optimization. The learning algorithm of the CEGIS loop      of synthesis problems to provide a basis for side-by-side
             uses the Metropolis-Hastings procedure to sample expressions.     comparisons of different solution strategies. The current set
             Theprobability of choosing an expression e is proportional to a   of benchmarks is limited to synthesis of loop-free functions
             value Score(e), which indicates the extent to which e meets the   with no optimality criterion; nevertheless, the benchmarks
             speciﬁcation ϕ. The Metropolis-Hastings algorithm guarantees      provide an initial demonstration of the expressiveness of the
             that, in the limit, expressions e are sampled with probability    base formalism and of the relative merits of the individual
             proportional to Score(e). To complete the description of the      solution strategies presented earlier. Speciﬁcally, in this section
             search procedure, we need to deﬁne Score(e) and the Markov        we explore three key questions about the benchmarks and the
             chain used for successor sampling. We deﬁne Score(e) to be        prototype synthesizers.
             exp(−βC(e)), where β is a smoothing constant (set by default         • Complexity of the benchmarks. Our suite includes a
             to 0.5), and the cost function C(e) is the number of concrete          range of benchmarks from simple toy problems to non-
             examples on which e does not satisfy ϕ.                                trivial functions that are difﬁcult to derive by hand. Some
               We now describe the Markov chain underlying the search.              of the benchmarks can be solved in a few hundredths of
             Fix an expression size n, and consider all expressions in L with       a second, whereas others could not be solved by any of
             parse trees of size n. The initial candidate is chosen uniformly       our prototype implementations. In all cases, however, the
             at random from this set [26]. Given a candidate e, we pick a           complexity of the problems derives from the size of the
             node v in its parse tree uniformly at random. Let ev be the            space of possible functions and not from the complexity
             subexpression rooted at this node. This subtree is replaced by         of checking whether a candidate solution is correct.
             another subtree (of the same type) of size equal to |ev| chosen      • Relative merits of different solvers. The use of a
             uniformly at random. Given the original candidate e, and a             standard format allows us to perform the ﬁrst side-to-
                        0                                              0
             mutation e thus obtained, the probability of making e the              side comparison of different approaches to synthesis.
             new candidate is given by the Metropolis-Hastings acceptance           None of the implementations were engineered with high-
                        0                    0
             ratio α(e,e ) = min(1,Score(e )/Score(e)).                             performance in mind, so the exact solution times are not
               The ﬁnal step is to describe how the algorithm selects the           necessarily representative of the best that can be achieved
             expression size n. Although the solver comes with an option            by a particular approach. However, the order of magni-
             to specify n, the expression size is typically not known a priori      tude of the solution times and the relative complexity of
             given a speciﬁcation ϕ. Intuitively, we run concurrent searches        the different approaches on different benchmarks can give
             for a range of values for n. Starting with n = 1, with some            us an idea of the relative merits of each of the approaches
             probability pm (set by default to 0.01), we switch at each step        described earlier.
             to one of the searches at size n±1. If an answer e exists, then      • Effect of problem encoding. For many problems, there
             the search at size n = |e| is guaranteed to converge.                  are different natural ways to encode the space of desired
               Consider the earlier example for computing the maxi-                 functions into a grammar, so we are interested in observ-
             mum of two integers. There are 768 integer-valued expres-              ing the effect of these differences in encoding for the
             sions in the grammar of size six. Thus, the probability of             different solvers.
             choosing e = ITE(x ≤ 0,y,x) as the initial candidate                 To account for variability and for the constant factors
             is 1/768. The subexpression to mutate is chosen uniformly
             at random, and so the probability of deciding to mutate           introduced by the prototype nature of the implementations,
             the boolean condition x ≤ 0 is 1/6. Of the 48 boolean             we report only the order of magnitude of the solution times
             conditions in the grammar, y ≤ 0 may be chosen with               in ﬁve different buckets: 0.1 for solution times less than half
                                                      0                        a second, 1 for solution times between half a second and 15
             probability 1/48. Thus, the mutation e = ITE(0 ≤ y,y,x)           seconds, 100 for solution times up to two minutes, 300 for
             is considered with probability 1/288. Given a set of con-
             crete examples {(−1,−4),(−1,−3),(−1,−2),(1,1),(1,2)},             solution times of up to 5 minutes, and inﬁnity for runs that
                                                 0                         0   time out after 5 minutes.
             Score(e) = exp(−2β), and Score(e ) = exp(−3β), and so e              The benchmarks themselves are grouped into three cate-
             becomes the new candidate with probability exp(−β). If, on
             the other hand, e0 = ITE(x ≤ y,y,x) had been the mutation         gories: hacker’s delight problems, integer benchmarks, and
                                       0             0                         assorted boolean and bit-vector problems.
             considered, then Score(e ) = 1, and e would have become
             the new candidate with probability 1.                                Hacker’s delight benchmarks: This set includes 57 differ-
               Our algorithm differs from that of Schufza et al. [11] in       ent benchmarks derived from 20 different bit-manipulation
             three ways: (1) we do not attempt to optimize the size of         problems from the book Hacker’s Delight        [27]. These bit-
             the expression while the super-optimizer does so; (2) we          vector problems were among the ﬁrst to be successfully
             synthesize expression graphs rather than straight-line assembly   tackled by synthesis technology and remain an active area of
﻿                                                                                           Relative Performance on a Sample of  Hacker's Delight Benchmarks
                                1000
                              .
                              c
                              e
                                 100
                              s
                               
                              in
                               
                                  10
                              e
                              im
                              t
                                   1
                               
                              e
                              t
                              a
                                  0.1
                              xim
                                0.01
                              ro
                              p
                              p
                              a
                                                                                                                   Enumerative     Stochastic (median)  Symbolic
                                                  Relative Performance of  Integer Benchmarks                                                     Relative Performance of Bit-vector and Boolean Problems
                                          1000
                                                                                                                                          1000
                                                                                                                                         .
                                                                                                                                         c
                                                                                                                                         e
                                        .
                                                                                                                                         s
                                        c
                                                                                                                                          
                                                                                                                                           100
                                           100
                                        e
                                                                                                                                         in
                                        s
                                                                                                                                          
                                         
                                                                                                                                         e
                                        in
                                         
                                                                                                                                             10
                                            10
                                                                                                                                         im
                                        e
                                                                                                                                         t
                                                                                                                                          
                                        im
                                                                                                                                         e
                                        t
                                                                                                                                         t
                                         
                                                                                                                                         a
                                        e
                                                                                                                                              1
                                             1
                                        t
                                        a
                                                                                                                                         xim
                                                                                                                                         ro
                                        xim
                                                                                                                                            0.1
                                            0.1
                                                                                                                                         p
                                        ro
                                                                                                                                         p
                                                                                                                                         a
                                        p
                                        p
                                        a
                                                                                                                                           0.01
                                           0.01
                                                                                                                                                                   Enumerative     Stochastic (median)  Symbolic
                                                           Enumerative     Stochastic (median)  Symbolic
                                                                                  Fig. 2.       Selected performance results for the three classes of benchmarks
                      research [4], [5], [16]. For these benchmarks, the goal is to                                                            Integer benchmarks: These benchmarks are meant to be
                      discover clever implementations of bit-vector transformations                                                        loosely representative of synthesis problems involving func-
                      (colloquially known as bit-twiddling). For most problems,                                                            tions with complex branching structures involving linear inte-
                      there are three different levels of grammars numbered d0, d1                                                         ger arithmetic. One of the benchmarks is array-search,
                      and d5; level d0 involves only the instructions necessary for                                                        which synthesizes a loop-free function that ﬁnds the index of
                      the implementation, so the synthesizer only needs to discover                                                        an element in a sorted tuple of size n, for n ranging from
                      how to connect them together. Level d5, on the other extreme,                                                        2 to 16. This benchmark proved to be quite complex, as no
                      involves a highly unconstrained grammar, so the synthesizer                                                          solver was able to synthesize this function for n > 4. The max
                      must discover which operators to use in addition to how to                                                           benchmarks are similar except they compute the maximum of
                      connect them together.                                                                                               a tuple of size n.
                           Fig. 2 shows the performance of the three solvers on a sam-                                                         Fig. 2 shows the relative performance of the three solvers
                      ple of the benchmarks. For the Hacker’s Delight benchmarks                                                           on these benchmarks for sizes up to 4. With one exception, the
                      (hd) we see that the enumerative solver dominates, followed                                                          enumerative solver is the fastest for this class of benchmarks,
                      by the stochastic solver. The symbolic search was the slowest,                                                       followed by the stochastic solver. The exception was max3
                      failing to terminate on 29 of the 57 benchmarks. It is worth                                                         where the stochastic solver was faster.
                      mentioning, however, that none of the grammars for these                                                                 Boolean/Bit-vector benchmarks: The parity benchmark
                      problems required the synthesizer to discover the bit-vector                                                         computes the parity of a set of Boolean values. The different
                      constants involved in the efﬁcient implementations. We have                                                          versions represent different grammars to describe the set of
                      someevidence to suggest that the symbolic solver can discover                                                        Boolean functions. As with other benchmarks, the enumerative
                                                                                               32
                      such constants from the full space of 2                                        possible constants                    solver was always faster, whereas the symbolic solver failed
                      with relatively little additional effort. On the other hand, for                                                     on every instance. These results show the impact that different
                      many of these problems the magic constants come from a                                                               encodings of the same space of functions can have on the
                      handful of values such as 1, 0, or 0xffffffff, so it is                                                              solution time for both of the solution strategies that succeeded.
                      unnecessary for the enumerative solver to search the space of                                                        Unlike the hd benchmarks where the different grammars for
                      232 possible bit-vectors.                                                                                            a given benchmark were strict subsets of each other, in this
                           Finally, because these benchmarks have different grammars                                                       case the encodings AIG and NAND correspond to different
                      for the same problem, we can observe the effect of using                                                             representations of the same space of functions.
                      more restrictive or less restrictive grammars as part of the                                                             The Morton benchmarks, which involve the synthesis
                      problem description. We can see in the data that all solvers                                                         of a function to compute Morton numbers, are intended as
                      were affected by the encoding of the problem for at least some                                                       challenge problems, and could not be completed by any of
                      benchmark; although in some cases, the pruning strategies                                                            the synthesizers.
                      used by the solvers were able to ameliorate the impact of                                                                Observations: The number of benchmarks and the maturity
                      the larger search space.                                                                                             of the solvers are too limited to draw broad conclusions,
﻿               but the overall trend we observe is that the encoding of                      Acknowledgements: We thank Nikolaj Bjorner and Stavros
               the problem space into grammar has a signiﬁcant impact on                  Tripakis for their feedback. This research is supported by the
               performance, although the solvers are often good at mitigating             NSF Expeditions in Computing project ExCAPE (award CCF
               the effect of larger search spaces. We can also see that non-              1138996).
               symbolic techniques can be effective in exploring spaces of                                            REFERENCES
               implementations and can surpass symbolic techniques, espe-
               cially when the problems do not require the synthesizer to                  [1] C. Barrett, R. Sebastiani, S. A. Seshia, and C. Tinelli, “Satisﬁability
               derive complex bit-vector constants, which is true for all the                  modulo theories,” in Handbook of Satisﬁability, 2009, vol. 4, ch. 8.
               bit-vector benchmarks used. Moreover, we observe that the                   [2] L. M. de Moura and N. Bjørner, “Satisﬁability modulo theories: Intro-
                                                                                               duction and applications,” Commun. ACM, vol. 54, no. 9, 2011.
               enumerative technique was better than the stochastic search for             [3] Z. Manna and R. Waldinger, “A deductive approach to program synthe-
               all but two benchmarks, so although both implementations are                    sis,” ACM TOPLAS, vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 90–121, 1980.
                                                                                                                                  ´
               immature, these results suggest that it may be easier to derive             [4] A. Solar-Lezama, R. Rabbah, R. Bodık, and K. Ebcioglu, “Programming
                                                                                               by sketching for bit-streaming programs,” in PLDI, 2005.
               good pruning rules for the explicit search than an effective                [5] S. Gulwani, S. Jha, A. Tiwari, and R. Venkatesan, “Synthesis of loop-
               ﬁtness function for the stochastic solver.                                      free programs,” SIGPLAN Not., vol. 46, pp. 62–73, June 2011.
                 The symbolic solver used for these experiments represents                 [6] S. Gulwani, W. R. Harris, and R. Singh, “Spreadsheet data manipulation
                                                                                               using examples,” Commun. ACM, vol. 55, no. 8, pp. 97–105, 2012.
               one of many possible approaches to encoding the synthesis                   [7] S. Jha, S. Gulwani, S. A. Seshia, and A. Tiwari, “Oracle-guided
               problem into a series of constraints. We have some evidence                     component-based program synthesis,” in ICSE, 2010, pp. 215–224.
               that more optimized encodings can make the symbolic ap-                     [8] A. Udupa, A. Raghavan, J. V. Deshmukh, S. Mador-Haim, M. M. Martin,
                                                                                               and R. Alur, “TRANSIT: Specifying Protocols with Concolic Snippets,”
               proach more competitive, although there are still many prob-                    in PLDI, 2013, pp. 287–296.
               lems for which the enumerative approach is more effective.                  [9] S. Srivastava, S. Gulwani, and J. S. Foster, “From program veriﬁcation
               Speciﬁcally, we have transcribed all the hacker’s delight and                   to program synthesis,” in POPL, 2010, pp. 313–326.
                                                                                          [10] V. Kuncak, M. Mayer, R. Piskac, and P. Suter, “Software synthesis
               integer benchmarks into the input language of the Sketch                        procedures,” Commun. ACM, vol. 55, no. 2, pp. 103–111, 2012.
               synthesis system [24]. Sketch completed all but 11 of the hd               [11] E. Schkufza, R. Sharma, and A. Aiken, “Stochastic superoptimization,”
               benchmarks, and it was able to synthesize array-search                          in ASPLOS, 2013, pp. 305–316.
                                                                                                      ´
                                                                                          [12] M. Colon, S. Sankaranarayanan, and H. Sipma, “Linear invariant gener-
               up to size 7. This experiment is not an entirely fair comparison                ation using non-linear constraint solving,” in CAV, 2003, pp. 420–432.
               because, although Sketch uses a specialized constraint solver              [13] A. Rybalchenko, “Constraint solving for program veriﬁcation: Theory
               and carefully tuned encodings, the symbolic solver presented                    and practice by example,” in CAV, 2010, pp. 57–71.
                                                                                          [14] R. Sharma, S. Gupta, B. Hariharan, A. Aiken, P. Liang, and A. V. Nori,
               in this paper uses a direct encoding of the problem into                        “A data driven approach for algebraic loop invariants,” in ESOP, 2013,
               sequences of constraints and uses Z3, a widely used off-                        pp. 574–592.
               the-shelf SMT solver which is not as aggressively tuned for                [15] N. Bjørner, K. L. McMillan, and A. Rybalchenko, “On solving univer-
                                                                                               sally quantiﬁed Horn clauses,” in SAS, 2013, pp. 105–125.
                                                                                                                                  ´
               synthesis problems. Despite these limitations, the symbolic                [16] A. Solar-Lezama, L. Tancau, R. Bodık, S. A. Seshia, and V. Saraswat,
               solver was able to solve many of the benchmarks, providing a                    “Combinatorial sketching for ﬁnite programs,” in ASPLOS, 2006.
               lower bound on what can be achieved with a straightforward                 [17] E. M. Gold, “Language identiﬁcation in the limit,” Information and
                                                                                               Control, vol. 10, no. 5, pp. 447–474, 1967.
               use of off-the-shelf technology.                                           [18] P. D. Summers, “A methodology for LISP program construction from
                 Moreover, the enumerative solver was able to solve more                       examples,” J. ACM, vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 161–175, 1977.
               hd problems than even the more optimized symbolic solver.                  [19] E. Y. Shapiro, Algorithmic Program Debugging. Cambridge, MA, USA:
                                                                                               MIT Press, 1983.
               The problems where the enumerative solver succeeded but                    [20] D. Angluin and C. H. Smith, “Inductive inference: Theory and methods,”
               Sketch failed were the d5 versions of problems 11, 12, 14                       ACM Computing Surveys, vol. 15, pp. 237–269, Sep. 1983.
               and 15, which suggests that the enumerative solver was better              [21] T. M. Mitchell, Machine Learning.   McGraw-Hill, 1997.
                                                                                          [22] S. A. Seshia, “Sciduction: Combining induction, deduction, and structure
               at pruning unnecessary instructions from the grammar. On                        for veriﬁcation and synthesis,” in DAC, 2012, pp. 356–365.
               the other hand, the more optimized symbolic solver did have                [23] D. Angluin, “Queries and concept learning,” Machine Learning, vol. 2,
               a signiﬁcant advantage in the array-search benchmarks                           pp. 319–342, 1988.
                                                                                          [24] A. Solar-Lezama, “Program synthesis by sketching,” Ph.D. dissertation,
               which the enumerative solver could only solve up to size 4.                     University of California, Berkeley, 2008.
                                                                                          [25] E. M. Clarke, O. Grumberg, S. Jha, Y. Lu, and H. Veith,
                                        V. CONCLUSIONS                                         “Counterexample-guided abstraction reﬁnement for symbolic model
                 Aimed at formulating the core computational problem                           checking,” J. ACM, vol. 50, no. 5, pp. 752–794, 2003.
                                                                                          [26] B. McKenzie, “Generating strings at random from a context free
               common to many recent tools for program synthesis in a                          grammar,” 1997.
               canonical and logical manner, we have formalized the problem               [27] H. S. Warren, Hacker’s Delight.  Boston, MA, USA: Addison-Wesley
               of syntax-guided synthesis. Our prototype implementation of                     Longman Publishing Co., Inc., 2002.
               the three approaches to solve this problem is the ﬁrst attempt
               to compare and contrast existing algorithms on a common set
               of benchmarks. We are already working on the next steps in
               this project. These consist of (1) ﬁnalizing the input syntax
               (SYNTH-LIB) based on the input format of SMT-LIB2, with
               an accompanying publicly available parser, (2) building a
               more extensive and diverse repository of benchmarks, and
               (3) organizing a competition for SyGuS-solvers. We welcome
               feedback and help from the community on all of these steps.
