                      A large-scale benchmark for few-shot program induction and synthesis 
                                    *1                             *1                  1                 1                             1 
                      Ferran Alet       Javier Lopez-Contreras         James Koppel  Maxwell Nye  Armando Solar-Lezama 
                                                               1                          1                           1 
                                       Tomás Lozano-Pérez  Leslie Pack Kaelbling  Joshua B. Tenenbaum 
                                        Abstract 
                    A landmark challenge for AI is to learn fexible, 
                    powerful representations from small numbers of 
                    examples.  On an important class of tasks, hy-
                    potheses in the form of programs provide ex-
                    treme generalization capabilities from surpris-
                    ingly few examples. However, whereas large real 
                    image benchmarks have spurred progress in meta-
                    learning for deep networks, there is no compa-
                    rably big, real program-synthesis dataset.  This 
                    is because, while images are relatively easy to 
                    label from internet meta-data or annotated by non-
                    experts, generating meaningful input-output tests 
                    for program induction has proven hard to scale. 
                    In this work, we propose a new way of leverag-
                    ing a collection of programs with associated unit 
                    tests to create a much larger collection of test-
                    program pairs.  We do so by extracting subpro-
                    grams of each program and using the inputs of the 
                    overall program to get tests for each subprogram.            Figure 1. Extracting interesting subprograms from the Sieve of 
                    This allows us to create PROGRES, a large-scale              Erathostenes.  Some subprograms, like j  =  max (p, dn/pe) p, 
                    few-shot program-induction benchmark of real                 are byproducts that are not directly used by the overall program, 
                    programs and propose new challenges in this do-              but still implement purposeful functions. Line sub-sequences that 
                    main.  We analyze the effect of multiple design              break the nesting structure result in invalid subprograms. 
                    choices on transformer-based program induction 
                    and synthesis algorithms, pointing to shortcom-
                    ings of current methods and suggesting multiple 
                    avenues for future work. 
               1. Introduction 
               Note:  since the camera-ready, we have made a fnal ver-
               sion  of  the  dataset  with  more  programs  and  increased 
               diversity.  The dataset description is the same, but met-
               rics  and statistics change,  and get more detailed.  You 
               can fnd it the updated PDF and materials at:  https: 
               //lis.csail.mit.edu/progres.                                      Figure 2. Example of a task corresponding to the fltering subpro-
                  *                   1                                          gram in fgure 1. The text context describes the overall program in 
                   Equal contribution  Massachusetts Institute of Technology,    which the subprogram is embedded. The C++ function provides 
               Cambridge Massachusetts, USA. Correspondence to: Ferran Alet      a possible implementation. Even though we standardize variable 
               <alet@mit.edu>, Javier Lopez-Contreras <javierlc@mit.edu>.        names, there are still alternative implementations, such as using 
               Proceedings of the    th                                          while instead of for. The Program Expression Graph (only a
                                  38    International Conference on Machine      portion shown) provides a more canonical notation. 
               Learning, PMLR 139, 2021. Copyright 2021 by the author(s). 
﻿                                                   Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
               1.1. Motivation                                                  In a program induction task, input-output examples have 
               One of the distinctive abilities of human intelligence is        to satisfy two more properties beyond satisfying the pro-
               building fexible representations from small amounts of           gram’s pre-conditions. First, in the same way distribution 
               data (Lake et al., 2015). Neural networks provide power-         shift between training and test data affects performance in 
               ful representations, but require substantial amounts of data     a single-task, meta-training examples have to come from 
               to train.  To alleviate these needs, a set of few-shot learn-    the same distribution as meta-test examples. Therefore, if 
               ing challenges has catalyzed progress into building deep         we want our algorithms to generalize at deployment-time, 
               meta-learning systems. These systems generalize from few         they have to be meta-trained on real, non-random input-
               examples by learning powerful priors on large amounts of         output examples to avoid such a (meta-)domain shift. More-
               previous tasks (Hospedales et al., 2020).                        over, for each program, the overall set of input-output tests 
                                                                                must probe potential edge cases to distinguish the desired 
               Programs often provide extreme generalization capabilities       program from possible alternatives, both for specifcation 
               from surprisingly few examples, such as generalizing to          (training examples) and validation(testing) purposes.  In 
               larger arrays or numbers outside the training range. How-        PROGRES input-output examples come from propagating 
               ever, the combinatorial space of programs has proven hard        unit tests designed by humans; thus, we expect them to be 
               to search.  Machine learning can then be used to learn to        natural and cover most edge cases. 
               search more effciently, either by learning to predict (priors 
               over) programs from examples, or directly learning a pre-        1.2. Generating a large program induction benchmark 
               dictor that can answer future queries. To train such systems         from a real code-base 
               we need a dataset of program induction tasks.                    Large repositories of human-generated code are already 
               A program induction task is a supervised learning task           available, many with accompanying examples designed to 
               whose input-output examples come from a program. For             probe the possible ways each program could fail.  These 
               training tasks, we can optionally have access to the cor-        include many internal or open-source code-bases with unit 
               responding implementation of such program, which en-             tests. Programming competitions are another paradigmatic 
               ables learning to predict (priors over) programs from ex-        example: programmers compete to code solutions to a set 
               amples. Sometimes we can also have access to a text de-          of problems, and their solutions are checked on hidden 
               scribing other relevant context.  In this work, we present       input-output tests. PROGRES builds on programs from the 
               PROGRES (Programs from Real Executed Subproblems),               competitive programming website codeforces.com. 
               a large meta-dataset of program induction tasks, enabling        Directly using the programs and their test-cases from the 
               future methods in few-shot program induction and synthesis.      website as a benchmark has a number of downsides. First, 
               You can fnd an example of a task in fgure 2.                     programs written by humans are often signifcantly too com-
               Multiple methods have created large synthetic program in-        plex for current program induction methods to solve. Sec-
               duction datasets by sampling programs from a Domain Spe-         ond, even though CodeForces has millions of programs, they 
               cifc Language (DSL) and feeding them random inputs to            only implement ∼ 5, 500 different programming problems. 
               generate tests.  Because DSLs can generate an unlimited          In this work, we propose to leverage a program with an ac-
               amount of programs, this method provides an easy way             companying test suite (defning a program induction task) to 
               of creating large datasets.  This approach may work well         create a series of input-output examples for its subprograms. 
               for hand-crafted DSLs where the language is highly tuned         Subprograms are subsequences of the overall program that 
               to a specifc application.  There, a reasonable portion of        express an intermediate variable as a function of previous 
               valid programs implement sensible functions and shorter          variables. As illustrated in fgure 1, subprograms in a pur-
               programs tend to be more useful.  In contrast, in general-       poseful program are also likely to be useful. Moreover, by 
               purpose languages like C++, the subset of interesting and        being shorter and simpler, subprograms provide a useful 
               meaningful programs is an extremely small fraction of the        learning curriculum. Finally, since subprogram complexity 
               set of compiling C++ programs. Thus, it is essential to use      ranges from a single line of code to entire programs, they 
               real programs to learn about this set of interesting programs.   provide a relevant benchmark for both current and future 
               In addition to real code, having meaningful input-output         program induction methods. 
               tests has multiple advantages over evaluating random inputs.     In order to generate input-output examples for subprograms, 
               Many programs have implicit pre-conditions for them to run       we use a program interpreter to propagate the inputs of the 
               successfully. For instance, if we use an integer to index an     overall program line by line. Then, at each step in the execu-
               array, it has to be both positive and smaller than the array’s   tion, we capture the value of all the relevant variables. From 
               length; if a program compares two lists element-wise, the        these execution traces, we derive relevant input-output tests 
               input lists must have equal length.                              for each subprogram. For more information, see section 3.2. 
﻿                                                    Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
               We generate PROGRES by applying a C++ program inter-              Few-shot program induction and synthesis  Program 
               preter to programs solving the 5,500 problems from Code-          synthesis (Shaw et al., 1975; Solar-Lezama et al., 2006; 
               Forces.  This allows us to create a much larger dataset of        Gulwani et al., 2017) aims at generating code that satisfes 
               more than 200,000 few-shot program-induction tasks of             a set of input-output examples.  Typically, these methods 
               varying diffculty and style (sec. 3.4).  A careful analysis       are data effcient, often generalizing from few examples. 
               of baselines (sec. 4.3) shows that there is both an initial       However, the combinatorial space of programs is hard to 
               promise and a long road ahead in the quest for building           search, often restricting the capacity of the language or the 
               effective solutions to this problem.                              size of programs.  Machine learning, and deep learning 
               In summary, our contributions are the following:                  in particular, have been increasingly used to improve the 
                                                                                 search over programs (Parisotto et al., 2016; Kalyan et al., 
                 1.  We propose a generic method of building large, real         2018; Brockschmidt et al., 2018; Ellis et al., 2019; Nye et al., 
                    program induction and synthesis benchmarks.                  2020). In this work, we implement one of these methods, 
                                                                                 RobustFill (Devlin et al., 2017), as a baseline. We believe 
                 2.  We provide a new dataset of more than 200, 000 pro-         that the substantial increase in data will facilitate further 
                    gram induction tasks, with multiple challenges for the       progress in neural searchers. Finally, there have been demos 
                    program synthesis and few-shot learning communities.         using GPT-3 (Brown et al., 2020) to predict short programs 
                                                                                 from English descriptions. Inspired by this nascent line of 
                 3.  We analyse the effect of adding different types of data     research, we modify the LSTM in the original RobustFill by 
                    from PROGRES to a transformer-based algorithm.               a pretrained transformer (Lewis et al., 2019). 
               2. Related work                                                   Program induction datasets  There have been multiple 
               Learning to few-shot learn  meta-learning (Schmidhuber,           few-shot program induction datasets, such as those used in 
               1987; Bengio et al., 1995; Thrun & Pratt, 1998) aims at learn-    FlashFill (Gulwani, 2011; Gulwani et al., 2015) and Dream-
               ing priors from many tasks to generalize to a new task from       Coder (Ellis et al., 2020), as well as the Abstract Reasoning 
               small amounts of data. Most of these methods assume that          Challenge(ARC) (Chollet, 2019), a list functions bench-
               the input form is constant( (Iwata & Kumagai, 2020) being a       mark (Rule, 2020), or the SyGus competition (Alur et al., 
               recent exception) and few-shot learning datasets are mainly       2017). Although these benchmarks contain many interesting 
               image classifcation (Lake et al., 2015; Vinyals et al., 2016;     problems, they have been manually created by humans in-
               Ren et al., 2018; Antoniou et al., 2020; Chen et al., 2019;       stead of being automatically generated from real programs. 
               Triantafllou et al., 2019) or low-dimensional continuous          This creates a signifcant bias on the datasets (often being 
               regression (Finn et al., 2017; Bauza et al., 2019). Moreover,     captured by a relatively simple Domain Specifc Language) 
               deep learning-based meta-learning algorithms do not typi-         and restricts the amount of tasks to a few hundred tasks. In 
               cally generalize broadly outside the data distribution, espe-     contrast, our benchmark, PROGRES, contains more than 
               cially non-optimization-based approaches (Finn, 2018). To         200,000 tasks, two orders of magnitude more.  This will 
               improve this, more compositional methods to meta-learning         allow neural-based methods, often data-ineffcient, to learn 
               are increasingly being proposed (Alet et al., 2018; Bengio        to generalize or search in these domains. Larger program 
               et al., 2019; Ke et al., 2019; Mendez & Eaton, 2020; Ruis         datasets have been shown to be useful to learn to search (Ba-
               et al., 2020). PROGRES provides a relevant benchmark for          log et al., 2016; Shin et al., 2019).  However, in contrast 
               these compositional few-shot learning methods.                    to PROGRES, these programs were randomly generated 
                                                                                 from restricted DSLs, and therefore do not capture the struc-
               Neural program induction  Neural networks are univer-             ture of real programs. 
               sal approximators that have delivered great results in a wide 
               variety of felds.  Motivated by these successes, multiple         Datasets  leveraging  competitive  programming  code 
               works have applied neural or neuro-symbolic methods to            Data from programming competitions, and codeforces. 
               latent program induction, where programs are represented          com in particular, has been used before to build several 
               only implicitly, without any reference to a specifc DSL.          benchmarks.  Zavershynskyi et al. (2018) is probably closest 
               Many of these approaches propose neural architectures             to our benchmark, combining a mixture of crowd-sourced 
               inspired by computational modules (Graves et al., 2014;           descriptions of subprograms with input-output examples 
               Kurach et al., 2015; Reed & De Freitas, 2015; Joulin &            for the entire programs (not subprograms).  Kulal et al. 
               Mikolov, 2015; Graves et al., 2016; Dong et al., 2019; Li         (2019) improved and standardized the pseudo-code annota-
               et al., 2020), training weights end-to-end. However, most         tion with line-by-line annotations and learned to translate 
               of these works aim at learning a single task performed by         from single-line pseudo-code to instruction. While useful, 
               a program. In contrast, PROGRES measures the ability to           language annotations are hard to scale because they have 
               learn new tasks from few examples.                                to be crowd-sourced and require expertise. Moreover, they 
﻿                                                  Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
               sidestep the major diffculty of program induction, as using       2.  20 pairs of input-outputs examples, 10 for training and 
               a line-by-line description of the program in English reduces         10 for test, 
               the inference to a translation problem. Codeforces has also       3.  a C++ function that solves these pairs, optionally with 
               been used to build program repair tools. Tan et al. (2017)           variable names already standardized, 
               build a dataset of small fxes by leveraging consecutive sub-
               missions from users fxing their mistakes and  Kulal et al.        4.  a natural text describing the overall program the task 
               (2019) learn to fx compile errors by synthetically perturbing        has been extracted from, 
               correct programs and observing the compiler message. 
                                                                                 5.  a Program Expression Graph form that further standard-
               3. Description of the PROGRES dataset                                izes the C++ code (see subsec 3.3 for more details). 
               We  call  our  dataset  PROGRES:  Programs  from  Real          Figure 2 shows an illustration for a single task. 
               Executed Subproblems.                                           3.2. Implementation and design decisions 
               3.1. Structure of the dataset                                    In this section we provide an overview of how we obtained 
               In competitive programming there are regularly-scheduled        the data contained in PROGRES. The goal is to provide a 
               contests, each with multiple new problems for humans to         better understanding on the data distribution, explaining how 
               solve by coding their solutions as programs.  Each Code-        we computed the input-output examples as well as some lim-
               Forces problem consists of a short text describing a back-      itations of our pipeline, which effectively constrain the pro-
               story and the requirements for the program, as well as multi-   grams in our dataset to be in a (large) subset of C++. We ob-
               ple test-cases (some public, some private) that the submitted   tain the original C++ programs from codeforces.com, 
               program has to satisfy.  Because all user submissions are       leveraging the scraping and standarization done by SPoC 
               public, for each problem there are hundreds of available        and DrRepair (Kulal et al., 2019; Yasunaga & Liang, 2020). 
               programs that solve it, providing us with multiple pairs of     Since this scraping only contained simple programs solving 
               (program, test suite) such that the entire program satisfes     very easy problems, we performed an additional scraping 
               the test-cases. For each program we can obtain many sub-        to capture problems of all diffculties.  We obtain around 
               programs: valid segments of code contained in the original      300,000 programs; however, since C++ is a compiled lan-
               program, expressing an intermediate variable as a function      guage, it is not meant to be run line-by-line, which we 
               of other variables.  To be valid, a subprogram has to be        need to do to obtain the subprograms. This process imposes 
               correctly parenthesised: start and end at the same level of     some constraints, which restrict us to a subset of C++, which 
               nesting and never go to a level above where it started in the   around 60,000 of the scraped programs satisfy. The most rel-
               indentation nesting. For a correct subsequence of the overall   evant exclusions are classes, the queue and stack data-
               program, we defne potential outputs as the variables modi-      structures, and the instructions break and continue. To 
               fed on the last line and as inputs all the variables involved   effciently evaluate these programs we leveraged the MIT 
               in the computations on that sequence that are not created       supercloud (Reuther et al., 2018), parallelizing program 
               within the subprogram itself.                                   evaluations over 4800 CPU cores. 
               Given a subprogram, we can generate the data for a single       To interpret C++ we use the Cling C++ interpreter (Vassilev 
               task; consisting of 20 input-output pairs (10 training, 10      et al.). Cling performs an elaborate incremental just-in-time 
               test). We obtain these pairs by running the entire program      compilation that keeps modifying the abstract syntax tree 
               with a custom-made C++ interpreter based on Cling (Vas-         before executing the new line of code.  This allows us to 
               silev et al.)(more details in section 3.2) and observing the    execute pieces of code and check the values of variables in 
               intermediate values at every line. Note that the input distri-  between. Since these pieces of code have to be compiled, 
               bution has a rich structure, as it comes from inputs designed   they have to be self-contained: functions have to be defned 
               by humans after being processed by previous computations        entirely before being fed to Cling and loops and if statements 
               in the overall program. Moreover, we also have access to        have to be given as a block. This would restrict the type of 
               the natural text description of the overall program.  This      subprograms that we can obtain with vanilla Cling, since 
               text alone does not specify the subprogram, but serves as a     we would not be able inspect the intermediate values within 
               context to help guide the search.                               loops or functions. 
               In PROGRES, a task consists of the following information:       We therefore implemented our own emulator on top of Cling 
                                                                               to be able to obtain intermediate values for loops and if state-
                                                                               ments. Instead of feeding the entire if/while statement 
                 1.  a  type  signature  describing  the  variable  types      to Cling, the emulator frst sends its condition and then calls 
                    (int,string,int[],etc) of all inputs and outputs,          the appropriate code depending on whether the condition 
﻿                                                    Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
                                                        CONCODE         NAPS      SPoC     ARC  DreamCoder  SyGUS  PROGRES 
                       Programming language                 Java        UAST       C++       -         DSL          DSL         C++ 
                       Number of programs                2,184,310      17,477    18,356     -          215         829       274,612 
                       Lines per program                    4.4          21.7      14.7      -         14.1         20.0         3.3 
                       Additional input                documentation     –pseudocode–        -           -            -        context 
                       Number of induction tasks              -           485      784     1000         215         829       274,612 
                       Number of test cases (average)         -           7.5      38.6     4.3        15.0         100.0       235.1 
               Table 1. Comparison of PROGRESto other program-based datasets. Some datasets like CONCODE (Iyer et al., 2018), contain lots of 
               programs, but no tests for these programs. NAPS and SPoC, both based on CodeForces, have as many induction tasks as CodeForces 
               problems (not subproblems); it is worth noting, however, that they focus on going from pseudo-code to code, a more relevant description 
               than our context. Both ARC and DreamCoder have program induction tasks manually designed by humans, thus restricting their size. For 
               DreamCoder we estimated the numbers using the dataset of list functions, the dataset of towers and the dataset of physical equations. For 
               SyGus, we estimated the number of tasks looking at the largest competition in 2019 and the statistics on the programs described in Alur 
               et al. (2013). Finally, note that even though we standardize the programs to have 20 tests (10 train,10 test), we often have access to many 
               more, with an average of 235. 
               was satisfed or not. Note that these if/while conditionals        ing equivalence of programs that exhibit undefned behavior, 
               are often interesting quantities, and we also include them        as the C standard states e.g.: a program with integer overfow 
               as tasks, even though there is no explicit boolean variable       may exhibit any behavior. We hence use I/O equivalence, 
               created in the original program.                                  also called machine equivalence, where two programs are 
               We store these line by line executions for each input set to      equivalent if they have the same outputs for all inputs (on a 
               the overall program. These fles can then be parsed to gen-        specifc machine). 
               erate the tests for each subprogram. To keep the dataset to a     Slicing  when we extract a contiguous set of instructions 
               reasonable size and avoid very long inputs, we capped the         from the overall program, not all lines will affect the output 
               execution to 100KB of generated data and skipped programs         value of the intermediate variable of interest. We thus clean 
               generating lines of more than 1KB of data. This avoided           the unnecessary instructions to avoid making programs un-
               long programs of many executions and arrays of tens of            necessarily long and redundant; a process called slicing (Xu 
               thousands of integers, which are hard to process by most          et al., 2005; Tsantalis & Chatzigeorgiou, 2009). To slice, 
               ML methods and expensive to store for a dataset.                  we try removing lines from the bottom to the top, as well as 
               3.3. Finding equivalent programs                                  entire code blocks. If the code without those lines or code 
                                                                                 blocks still passes the test-cases, we remove them and keep 
                There are two type of equivalences in our dataset construc-      iterating until we cannot remove any more code. Going from 
               tion: subprogram equivalence implies the two implement            the bottom to the top allows us to remove pairs of redundant 
               the same function; program induction task equivalence im-         instructions where the bottom one depends on the top one. 
               plies that their programs are equivalent and they happen in 
               the same context (in our case, defned by the text represent-      Slicing and fnding classes of equivalent tasks  We frst 
               ing the overall problem). This difference is important, as in     partition tasks by CodeForces problem, since these will have 
               programming we often have to recognize the possibility of         different text context, as well as different input-output pairs. 
               reusing a known pattern in a new circumstance.                    To detect equivalent tasks within each CodeForces problem, 
                                                                                 we run the following steps: 
               Defning Program Equivalence  The same function can                  1.  We slice every program independently and standardize 
               be  implemented  by  many  different  programs.  As  the                the variables. 
               fnal step in the dataset construction,  we identify such            2.  We join programs that have the same implementation. 
               equivalence-classes of functions using a mixture of test-
               ing and theorem-proving. Programming language theorists             3.  We mark programs that pass each other test-cases as 
               have defned many notions of program equivalence. A clas-                potentially equivalent. This is an overapproximation 
               sic one, sometimes called “semantic equivalence," deems                 of the true equivalence relation. 
               two programs equivalent if they have the same preconditions         4.  We then cluster these candidates into programs proven 
               and, for all inputs satisfying these preconditions, they can            actually equivalent by using Yogo (Premtoon et al., 
               be proved to have the same output.                                      2020), a tool based on equality saturation (Tate et al., 
               Implementing this in an automated checker is a non-starter:             2009; Nelson & Oppen, 1980). This refnes the candi-
               the intended precondition of any subprogram is unknowable               date sets into an underapproximation of the true equiv-
               from the code alone. Further, this defnition disallows prov-            alence relation. 
﻿                                                     Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
               The upshot of the consecutive overapproximating and un-
                derapproximating phases is an excellent approximation to 
                the true equivalence relation, which is undecidable. Using 
                tests we can prove that two programs are not equivalent, 
                but not the opposite.  Using Yogo we can prove they are 
                equivalent, but not the opposite. This leaves only a small 
                set of ambiguous relations. 
               The rest of this section summarizes Yogo and how it proves 
                programs equivalent. 
                Equality Saturation and E-PEGs  An expression such 
                as x < y and  y < z can be rewritten into many equiva-
                lent forms using rules such as not(y <= x or  y <= z) 
                or even the redundant z > y and  y > x and  z > x. 
                E-graphs (equivalence graphs (Nelson & Oppen, 1980) 
                are a way to compactly represent the exponential number 
                of equivalent expressions that can be found by a set of 
                rewrite rules. From the initial expression Abstract Syntax 
               Tree(AST), equality saturation is performed, adding each 
                newly-discovered equivalent expression to the e-graph via 
                an extension of the union-fnd algorithm.                            Figure 3. Subset of some interesting signatures in our dataset, all 
                E-graphs are a powerful technique, but have traditionally           with at least 200 tasks. Color indicates the length distribution of 
                only been applicable to pure, loop-free programs. Program           programs for each signature. Most programs have few inputs and 
                Expression Graphs (PEGs) (Tate et al., 2009) are a new              output integers or booleans. There are programs doing array and 
                representation of programs that allows equational reason-           string manipulation, as well as some matrix operations. 
                ing and build e-graphs on arbitrary imperative programs. 
                Conceptually, PEGs can be thought of as being constructed           from few variables. There are other signatures that involve 
                by unrolling loops into an infnite tree, and then compactly         array, matrix and string manipulations, often conditioned on 
                representing this infnite-but-regular tree as a cycle in the        other variables like integers or individual characters. These 
                graph.  Equality saturation then yields an e-graph on the           are interesting as they often require to generalize to longer 
                PEG (or E-PEG), representing an exponentially-large space           computations as well as bigger data structures. 
                of equivalent programs. This was originally used for com-           Figure 4 shows the diffculty of our tasks along three differ-
                piler optimization, but Yogo (Premtoon et al., 2020) uses it        ent axis. First, many problems contain either if-statements 
                for code search — and now also for equivalence-checking.            or loops that require generalizing more than 10 times the 
                Yogo:  Equivalence Checking from E-PEGs  We cus-                    number of operations needed for training examples. Condi-
                tomized Yogo to work on our codebase.  Even though it               tional execution (characterized by nesting in C++) is often 
                originally only handled Java and Python, it is built on the         very hard for program induction techniques.  Our bench-
                Cubix (Koppel et al., 2018) multi-language infrastructure,          mark contains a wide variability of nesting quantities across 
                allowing us to add support for a subset of C that captures          different subprograms.Finally, our input and outputs follow 
                the subset of C++ in PROGRES, after some simple string              a very structured distribution, since they come from real 
                transformations, e.g.:  changing vector<int>  foo to                examples. For instance, most integers are small (note the 
                struct  vector  foo.  To check for equivalences be-                 logarithmic y axis), with positive numbers being more com-
                tween functions, we put them into a single E-PEG, assigning         mon. Moreover, special numbers like 100 and -100 are more 
                each the same start state. Then, we report two subprograms          common than numbers of similar magnitude. 
                as equivalent if equality saturation groups their return values     3.5. Accompanying environment 
                in the same equivalence class. 
                                                                                    In order to be able to test candidate programs, we include 
                3.4. Statistical analysis                                           a python interface to our C++ interpreter. The interface is 
                Figure 3 shows the variability of signatures on our bench-          easy to use and has two different modes: 
                mark. As expected, the most common signatures involve                 1.  We can run an entire C++ function on a set of inputs by 
                integer manipulations as well as classifcation problems                  passing the former as a string and the latter as a list of 
﻿                                                         Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
                Figure 4. (Left) We purposely bias the test to generalize to longer computations than those seen for training examples.This plot shows 
                the ratio of number of maximum number of lines executed for a test input vs maximum number of lines executed for a training input. 
                Programs without loops, where the ratio is 1, are ommitted.(Center) Depth of indentation execution (nested loops and if statements), 
                which often signifcantly affects the diffculty of program synthesis. (Right) number of times each integer in [-200,200] appears as an 
                input or output on a test-case. We can see that they follow a very intuitive distribution, with smaller integers being more popular, positive 
                numbers being more common than their negative counterparts and a peak at 100 and -100. 
                      strings. The interface then returns whether the function           us to judge the correctness of equivalent implementations of 
                      compiled and, if it did, a list of results for each input. In      the same function or implicit programs, like those described 
                      case of a runtime error or a timeout, it returns "Runtime          by neural networks.  More concretely, for each task, we 
                      error" or "Timeout" respectively.  This is useful for              give the method all 10 training examples and evaluate its 
                      approaches that use the environment as a black-box                 performance on the 10 test examples, only counting exact 
                      without interacting with individual instructions.                  answers. We can then measure the example accuracy (the 
                   2.  In contrast to traditional C++, we can run a program              fraction of correctly-solved test-cases across all meta-test 
                      line by line and return the appropriate variables with             tasks), and task accuracy (the fraction of tasks with all of 
                      new values. This mode is restricted to our subset of               their 10 test examples correctly predicted).  Note that, al-
                      C++ (that all programs in PROGRESbelong to), but                   though both measures are related, a method may have higher 
                      it is useful for methods that use partial executions to            task accuracy than another, while having lower example ac-
                      guide synthesis (Ellis et al., 2019).                              curacy. As described in previous work (Devlin et al., 2017), 
                                                                                         having a high example accuracy is more desirable when 
                                                                                         we are using the method on a per-example basis (like an 
                4. Benchmark                                                             auto-suggest tool) whereas task accuracy is more important 
                4.1. Evaluation protocol                                                 in cases where we would like the induced program to make 
                                                                                         an indeterminate number of predictions without having to 
                Our goal is to generalize to relevant subprograms from un-               check all of them. 
                seen programming contests. Therefore, we choose to divide 
                between meta-train, meta-validation and meta-test at the                 4.2. Baselines 
                level of contests: training takes contests <1000, validation             We evaluate multiple baselines, all based on the same core 
                between 1000 and 1249 and testing more than 1250. Some                   architecture (a large-scale language model), in order to bet-
                subprograms (especially short ones like "return v0+1") are               ter understand their differences. 
                repeated multiple times. If in a single problem (thus shar-
                ing the context text and often the same input-output pairs)              Fine-tuning a pre-trained language model to generate 
                there are multiple copies of the same subprogram, we merge               code  from  examples  Inspired  by  the  RobustFill  pro-
                them into a single task, pooling their input-output examples.            gram synthesis model (Devlin et al., 2017) and recent 
                Note that the same subprogram can be in different problems.              advances in language model pre-training, we build a neural 
                However, they will not be the same task, because both the                program synthesis baseline.  Our aim was to determine 
                input-output pairs and the context text will differ. Intuitively,        how well a state-of-the-art sequence-to-sequence neural 
                new programming tasks may require us to implement code                   program synthesis model could perform on our dataset. 
                we have seen before (like adding up all the elements in an               We  used  the  BART  (Lewis  et  al.,  2019)  pre-trained 
                array), but in a different context.                                      transformer  model  as  a  base,  and  fne-tuned  it  on  our 
                To judge the performance of a program for a single task, we              dataset to output programs.  The model takes as input 
                evaluate its performance on unseen test cases. This allows               the function header (which describes the type signature), 
﻿                                                              Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
                  as  well  as  the  support  set  examples  arranged  sequen-
                  tially,   i.e.,   [header]  |  [Input1];  [Output1] 
                  |  [Input2];  [Output2]  |  ...  [Input10]; 
                  [Output10]. The model is trained to output the program 
                  body.  At evaluation time, we perform a beam search of 
                  beam size 10,  and select the program out of those 10 
                  candidates which performs the best on the support set and 
                  execute that program on the query set to produce fnal 
                  predictions for each query example.  Note that executing 
                  programs on the support set allows us to perform a search 
                  over  the  possible  candidate  programs,  which  has  been 
                  shown  to  greatly  increase  the  performance  of  neural                      Figure 5. Dependence of example and task accuracy when only 
                  program synthesis techniques (Devlin et al., 2017). Figure 5                    evaluating the frst p ∈ [1, 10] programs coming from the beam 
                  shows how,  in our case,  it  signifcantly  improves  task                      search. Most of the the performance comes from the frst predic-
                  accuracy. To evaluate all program candidates we only need                       tion, but the rest provides a noticeable boost of more than one third 
                  to evaluate entire functions, instead interpreting the program                  in relative performance. 
                  line-by-line. We thus relied on cppyy (Lavrijsen & Dutta,                       less than one may expect. Human experiments in a prelimi-
                  2016) which provides effcient python-C++ bindings.                              nary version of this dataset indicated that their learning was 
                  We also test if additionally conditioning on the overall pro-                   also very fast, saturating at 5 examples. This also matches 
                  gram description text increases performance. In these exper-                    previous human experiments on inferring list-editing pro-
                  iments, we append the text to the examples.                                     grams (Rule, 2020). Therefore, it appears that there is also 
                  Transformer-based  end-to-end  prediction  Our  next                            a fundamental search problem, typical in program synthesis, 
                  baseline, also inspired by Devlin et al. (2017), is a program                   where the task space is exponential. 
                  induction model.  Using an architecture analogous to the                        Dependence on text context  Adding the text context im-
                  neural program synthesis model, we use neural models to                         proved performance by a surprisingly high amount: between 
                  perform neural program induction, i.e., given a training set                    16% relative improvent in example accuracy and 23% in 
                  of k input-output examples and a single test input, produce                     task accuracy.We did not observe any signifcant correlation 
                  the corresponding output. Instead of generating the target                      with the type signature, instead producing improvements 
                  code, the induction model is instead trained to approximate                     across the board.  Further research into more effectively 
                  the execution of the code directly. Our model is identical                      combining the two modalities of input is a promising area 
                  to the program synthesis model above, except that the test                      of future work. 
                  input example is prepended to the context string, and the 
                  model is trained to produce the target test output.                             4.4. Open challenges 
                  4.3. Discussion                                                                 The previous section highlights the need for better few-
                                                                                                  shot program induction and program synthesis methods. 
                  Comparison between program synthesis and program                                Moreover, this benchmark opens up multiple interesting 
                  induction  Somewhat surprisingly, in preliminary experi-                        challenges. We highlight a few: 
                  ments end-to-end program induction performed better than 
                  predicting the program as an intermediate.  However, the                        Graph  representations  of  programs  although  not 
                  order changed when we started slicing the programs, which                       explored  in  this  work,  the  inclusion  of  PEGs  in  PRO-
                  removed superfuous lines of code, making learning to syn-                       GRES  facilitates  the  evaluation  of  Graph  Neural 
                  thesize easier.  There, the synthesis approach has a great                      Networks (Scarselli et al., 2009; Bronstein et al., 2017; 
                  advantage, as it can generate the program and let it solve                      Battaglia et al., 2018) for code analysis at scale, an approach 
                  arbitrarily complex inputs.                                                     that has already shown promise (Li et al., 2019). 
                  This is specially the case for tasks returning collections                      Open-ended active learning  The ability of asking for 
                  (arrays, lists, strings, and matrices). This is understandable,                 useful labels would allow a program synthesis method to 
                  since , for collections, program induction had to generate                      interact with a human, improving the data effciency by 
                  long stretches of tokens without error, which is very hard to                   actively trying to resolve uncertainties. This topic has been 
                  do, especially for all inputs.                                                  explored in the past for program induction (Pu et al., 2018), 
                  Dependence on number of program examples  Perfor-                               but only in selecting from a small number of examples. 
                  mance consistently improves from 5 to 10 examples, but by                       Since we provide an environment and the true program, we 
﻿                                                       Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
                      Method          Pretrained    Text context     Example accuracy       Task accuracy     Entity task acc.    Collection task acc. 
                                                                          5-shot/10-shot     5-shot/10-shot     5-shot/10-shot          5-shot/10-shot 
                                          no           without             0.351 / 0.349      0.107 / 0.107       0.126 / 0.126          0.000 / 0.000 
                  BART-Robustfll                         with              0.340 / 0.338      0.114 / 0.116       0.135 / 0.137          0.000 / 0.000 
                     Induction                         without             0.477 / 0.492      0.210 / 0.223       0.248 / 0.263          0.001 / 0.001 
                                          yes            with              0.504 / 0.521      0.246 / 0.259       0.289 / 0.305          0.010 / 0.010 
                                          no           without             0.464 / 0.473      0.315 / 0.325       0.526 / 0.538          0.124 / 0.123 
                  BART-Robustfll                         with              0.510 / 0.516      0.363 / 0.370       0.560 / 0.565          0.240 / 0.249 
                     Synthesis                         without             0.570 / 0.579      0.420 / 0.429       0.622 / 0.633          0.285 / 0.283 
                                          yes            with              0.592 / 0.602      0.444 / 0.456       0.645 / 0.655          0.306 / 0.313 
                Table 2. 
                        Comparison of the different design choices based on BART-RobustFill. Synthesizing the program instead of directly predicting 
                the outputs gave the biggest boost. Interestingly, in previous versions of the dataset where the programs were not sliced, induction gave 
                better results, highlighting the need for clean code examples. Then, using the pretrained weights for the transformer has a very noticeable 
                positive effect. Having the text context consistently improves performance by a noticeable margin. Finally, going from 5 to 10 examples 
                gives a small, but positive boost to all methods. Note: since the camera-ready, we have made a fnal version of the dataset with more 
                programs and diversity. The dataset description is the same, but concrete metrics and statistics change. You can fnd it the updated PDF 
                and materials at: https://lis.csail.mit.edu/progres. 
                can use it as an oracle for active learning. However, this has        provide PROGRES, a meta-dataset of more than 200,000 
                the added challenge (and beneft) of being unconstrained,              tasks based on real programs, of a wide variety of problems 
                with the model generating its own queries.                            and input-output examples. Evaluations show a wide margin 
                                                                                      for improvements for current program induction and syn-
                Leveraging instructive examples and structured inputs                 thesis methods. The scale of data, two orders of magnitude 
                In classic Machine Learning we assume examples come                   larger than previous work, together with the inclusion of 
                from randomly sampling the input distribution. Therefore,             text contexts and a custom code interpreter open up many 
                most training examples lie at the conceptual center of the in-        possible avenues for future research. 
                put space. In contrast, our examples tend to be extremal, pok-
                ing at the edge-cases to differentiate the true program from          Acknowledgements 
                reasonable alternatives. Humans actively use the knowledge            We would like to thank Maria Bauza for her detailed and 
                that a teacher is giving them instructive examples to update          perceptive comments on the paper drafts and anonymous 
                their priors more effectively (Shafto et al., 2014). Construct-       reviewer #3 for their thorough, insightful review; both sig-
                ing algorithms capable of similar inferences is a promising           nifcantly improved our work. We would also like to thank 
                avenue for future work. Similarly, our inputs tend to pertain         Lauren Milechin and the MIT supercloud team, that allowed 
                to a class much smaller than that defned by their C++ type.           us to scale the computations required to generate the dataset. 
                For instance, for many problems, all integer inputs are posi-         We would also like to thank Wim Lavrijsen and Sumith Ku-
                tive, which makes some implementations easier. Being able             lal for their quick and detailed responses about cppyy and 
                to infer these conditions in the inputs and exploit them is           SPoC, respectively. Finally, we would like to thank Oriol 
                something human programmers often do and an avenue for                Vinyals and Charles Sutton for their comments about this 
                improving the performance of current systems.                         work and Eric Navarro and Marta Alet for their help parsing 
                                                                                      CodeForces problems. 
                Leveraging intermediate states for program synthesis                  We gratefully acknowledge support NSF grant 1723381; 
                Our environment can be run in interactive mode, receiv-               from AFOSR grant FA9550-17-1-0165; from ONR grant 
                ing individual (or groups of) instructions, and returning             N00014-18-1-2847; from GoodAI, from the Honda Re-
                the relevant variables that changed value. This facilitates           search Institute, from MIT-IBM Watson Lab; and from 
                program synthesis that inspects intermediate values to in-            SUTD Temasek Laboratories.  We also acknowledge the 
                form search, which has been shown to signifcantly boost               MIT SuperCloud and Lincoln Laboratory Supercomputing 
                performance (Ellis et al., 2019; Nye et al., 2020).                   Center for providing HPC resources that have contributed to 
                5. Conclusion                                                         the research results reported within this paper. Any opinions, 
                                                                                      fndings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in 
                We have presented a new way of scaling up few-shot pro-               this material are those of the authors and do not necessarily 
                gram induction and program synthesis benchmarks.  We                  refect the views of our sponsors. 
﻿                                                   Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
               References                                                       Chollet, F. On the measure of intelligence, 2019. 
               Alet, F., Lozano-Perez, T., and Kaelbling, L. P.  Modular        Devlin, J., Uesato, J., Bhupatiraju, S., Singh, R., Mohamed, 
                 meta-learning. In Proceedings of The 2nd Conference on            A.-r., and Kohli, P. Robustfll: Neural program learning 
                 Robot Learning, pp. 856–868, 2018.                                under noisy i/o. In International conference on machine 
               Alur,  R.,  Bodik,  R.,  Juniwal,  G.,  Martin,  M.  M.,            learning, pp. 990–998. PMLR, 2017. 
                 Raghothaman,  M.,  Seshia,  S.  A.,  Singh,  R.,  Solar-       Dong, H., Mao, J., Lin, T., Wang, C., Li, L., and Zhou, D. 
                 Lezama, A., Torlak, E., and Udupa, A.  Syntax-guided              Neural logic machines. arXiv preprint arXiv:1904.11694, 
                 synthesis. IEEE, 2013.                                            2019. 
               Alur,  R.,  Fisman,  D.,  Singh,  R.,  and Solar-Lezama,  A. 
                 Sygus-comp 2017: Results and analysis. arXiv preprint          Ellis, K., Nye, M., Pu, Y., Sosa, F., Tenenbaum, J., and Solar-
                 arXiv:1711.11438, 2017.                                           Lezama, A.  Write, execute, assess: Program synthesis 
               Antoniou, A., Patacchiola, M., Ochal, M., and Storkey,              with a repl. arXiv preprint arXiv:1906.04604, 2019. 
                 A. Defning benchmarks for continual few-shot learning.         Ellis, K., Wong, C., Nye, M., Sable-Meyer, M., Cary, L., 
                 arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.11967, 2020.                            Morales, L., Hewitt, L., Solar-Lezama, A., and Tenen-
               Balog, M., Gaunt, A. L., Brockschmidt, M., Nowozin, S.,             baum, J. B. Dreamcoder: Growing generalizable, inter-
                 and Tarlow, D. Deepcoder: Learning to write programs.             pretable knowledge with wake-sleep bayesian program 
                 arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.01989, 2016.                            learning. arXiv preprint arXiv:2006.08381, 2020. 
               Battaglia,  P.  W.,  Hamrick,  J.  B.,  Bapst,  V.,  Sanchez-    Finn,    C.       Learning  to  Learn  with  Gradients. 
                 Gonzalez, A., Zambaldi, V., Malinowski, M., Tacchetti,            PhD     thesis,    EECS       Department,      University 
                 A., Raposo, D., Santoro, A., Faulkner, R., et al.  Rela-          of   California,   Berkeley,    Aug  2018.           URL 
                 tional inductive biases, deep learning, and graph networks.       http://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/ 
                 arXiv preprint arXiv:1806.01261, 2018.                            TechRpts/2018/EECS-2018-105.html. 
               Bauza, M., Alet, F., Lin, Y.-C., Lozano-Pérez, T., Kaelbling,    Finn, C., Abbeel, P., and Levine, S. Model-agnostic meta-
                 L. P., Isola, P., and Rodriguez, A. Omnipush: accurate,           learning for fast adaptation of deep networks.  arXiv 
                 diverse, real-world dataset of pushing dynamics with rgb-         preprint arXiv:1703.03400, 2017. 
                 d video. arXiv preprint arXiv:1910.00618, 2019. 
               Bengio, S., Bengio, Y., and Cloutier, J. On the search for       Graves, A., Wayne, G., and Danihelka, I.  Neural Turing 
                 new learning rules for anns. Neural Processing Letters, 2         machines. arXiv preprint arXiv:1410.5401, 2014. 
                 (4):26–30, 1995.                                               Graves, A., Wayne, G., Reynolds, M., Harley, T., Dani-
                                                                                                              ´
               Bengio, Y., Deleu, T., Rahaman, N., Ke, R., Lachapelle,             helka, I., Grabska-Barwinska, A., Colmenarejo, S. G., 
                 S., Bilaniuk, O., Goyal, A., and Pal, C. A meta-transfer          Grefenstette, E., Ramalho, T., Agapiou, J., et al. Hybrid 
                 objective for learning to disentangle causal mechanisms.          computing using a neural network with dynamic external 
                 arXiv preprint arXiv:1901.10912, 2019.                            memory. Nature, 538(7626):471, 2016. 
               Brockschmidt, M., Allamanis, M., Gaunt, A. L., and Polo-         Gulwani, S. Automating string processing in spreadsheets 
                 zov, O.  Generative code modeling with graphs.  arXiv             using input-output examples. ACM Sigplan Notices, 46 
                 preprint arXiv:1805.08490, 2018.                                  (1):317–330, 2011. 
               Bronstein, M. M., Bruna, J., LeCun, Y., Szlam, A., and Van-      Gulwani, S., Hernández-Orallo, J., Kitzelmann, E., Muggle-
                 dergheynst, P. Geometric deep learning: Going beyond              ton, S. H., Schmid, U., and Zorn, B. Inductive program-
                 Euclidean data. IEEE Signal Processing Magazine, 34:              ming meets the real world. Communications of the ACM, 
                 18–42, 2017.                                                      58(11):90–99, 2015. 
               Brown, T. B., Mann, B., Ryder, N., Subbiah, M., Kaplan,          Gulwani, S., Polozov, O., Singh, R., et al. Program synthesis. 
                 J., Dhariwal, P., Neelakantan, A., Shyam, P., Sastry, G.,         Foundations and Trends® in Programming Languages, 4 
                 Askell, A., et al. Language models are few-shot learners.         (1-2):1–119, 2017. 
                 arXiv preprint arXiv:2005.14165, 2020. 
               Chen, W.-Y., Liu, Y.-C., Kira, Z., Wang, Y.-C. F., and Huang,    Hospedales, T., Antoniou, A., Micaelli, P., and Storkey, 
                 J.-B.  A closer look at few-shot classifcation.  arXiv            A.  Meta-learning in neural networks: A survey.  arXiv 
                 preprint arXiv:1904.04232, 2019.                                  preprint arXiv:2004.05439, 2020. 
﻿                                                  Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
              Iwata, T. and Kumagai, A. Meta-learning from tasks with         Li, Y., Gimeno, F., Kohli, P., and Vinyals, O. Strong general-
                 heterogeneous attribute spaces. Advances in Neural In-         ization and effciency in neural programs. arXiv preprint 
                 formation Processing Systems, 33, 2020.                        arXiv:2007.03629, 2020. 
              Iyer, S., Konstas, I., Cheung, A., and Zettlemoyer, L. Map-     Mendez, J. A. and Eaton, E.  Lifelong learning of com-
                 ping language to code in programmatic context.  arXiv          positional structures. arXiv preprint arXiv:2007.07732, 
                 preprint arXiv:1808.09588, 2018.                               2020. 
              Joulin, A. and Mikolov, T.  Inferring algorithmic patterns      Nelson, G. and Oppen, D. C.  Fast decision procedures 
                 with stack-augmented recurrent nets.  arXiv preprint           based on congruence closure.  J. ACM, 27(2):356–364, 
                 arXiv:1503.01007, 2015.                                        1980.  doi: 10.1145/322186.322198.  URL https:// 
                                                                                doi.org/10.1145/322186.322198. 
              Kalyan, A., Mohta, A., Polozov, O., Batra, D., Jain, P., and    Nye, M., Pu, Y., Bowers, M., Andreas, J., Tenenbaum, 
                 Gulwani, S.  Neural-guided deductive search for real-          J. B., and Solar-Lezama, A.  Representing partial pro-
                 time program synthesis from examples. arXiv preprint           grams with blended abstract semantics.  arXiv preprint 
                 arXiv:1804.01186, 2018.                                        arXiv:2012.12964, 2020. 
              Ke, N. R., Bilaniuk, O., Goyal, A., Bauer, S., Larochelle,      Parisotto, E., Mohamed, A.-r., Singh, R., Li, L., Zhou, D., 
                 H., Schölkopf, B., Mozer, M. C., Pal, C., and Bengio, Y.       and Kohli, P. Neuro-symbolic program synthesis. arXiv 
                 Learning neural causal models from unknown interven-           preprint arXiv:1611.01855, 2016. 
                 tions. arXiv preprint arXiv:1910.01075, 2019. 
              Koppel,  J.,  Premtoon,  V.,  and Solar-Lezama,  A.  One        Premtoon, V., Koppel, J., and Solar-Lezama, A. Semantic 
                 tool, many languages: Language-parametric transforma-          code search via equational reasoning. In Proceedings of 
                 tion with incremental parametric syntax.  PACMPL, 2            the 41st ACM SIGPLAN International Conference on Pro-
                 (OOPSLA):122:1–122:28, 2018. doi: 10.1145/3276492.             gramming Language Design and Implementation, PLDI 
                 URL https://doi.org/10.1145/3276492.                           2020, London, UK, June 15-20, 2020, pp. 1066–1082, 
                                                                                2020.  doi:  10.1145/3385412.3386001.  URL https: 
              Kulal, S., Pasupat, P., Chandra, K., Lee, M., Padon, O.,          //doi.org/10.1145/3385412.3386001. 
                 Aiken, A., and Liang, P. S.  Spoc:  Search-based pseu-       Pu, Y., Miranda, Z., Solar-Lezama, A., and Kaelbling, L. 
                 docode to code. In Advances in Neural Information Pro-         Selecting representative examples for program synthesis. 
                 cessing Systems, pp. 11906–11917, 2019.                        In International Conference on Machine Learning, pp. 
              Kurach,  K.,  Andrychowicz,  M.,  and  Sutskever,  I.             4161–4170. PMLR, 2018. 
                 Neural  random-access  machines.         arXiv  preprint     Reed, S. and De Freitas, N. Neural programmer-interpreters. 
                 arXiv:1511.06392, 2015.                                        arXiv preprint arXiv:1511.06279, 2015. 
              Lake,  B. M.,  Salakhutdinov,  R.,  and Tenenbaum,  J. B.       Ren, M., Triantafllou, E., Ravi, S., Snell, J., Swersky, 
                 Human-level concept learning through probabilistic pro-        K., Tenenbaum, J. B., Larochelle, H., and Zemel, R. S. 
                 gram induction. Science, 350(6266):1332–1338, 2015.            Meta-learning for semi-supervised few-shot classifcation. 
              Lavrijsen, W. T. and Dutta, A. High-performance python-           arXiv preprint arXiv:1803.00676, 2018. 
                 c++ bindings with pypy and cling. In 2016 6th Workshop       Reuther, A., Kepner, J., Byun, C., Samsi, S., Arcand, W., Be-
                 on Python for High-Performance and Scientifc Comput-           stor, D., Bergeron, B., Gadepally, V., Houle, M., Hubbell, 
                 ing (PyHPC), pp. 27–35. IEEE, 2016.                            M., et al. Interactive supercomputing on 40,000 cores for 
              Lewis, M., Liu, Y., Goyal, N., Ghazvininejad, M., Mo-             machine learning and data analysis. In 2018 IEEE High 
                 hamed, A., Levy, O., Stoyanov, V., and Zettlemoyer, L.         Performance extreme Computing Conference (HPEC), pp. 
                 Bart: Denoising sequence-to-sequence pre-training for          1–6. IEEE, 2018. 
                 natural language generation, translation, and comprehen-     Ruis, L., Andreas, J., Baroni, M., Bouchacourt, D., and 
                 sion. arXiv preprint arXiv:1910.13461, 2019.                   Lake, B. M.  A benchmark for systematic generaliza-
                                                                                tion in grounded language understanding. arXiv preprint 
              Li, Y., Gu, C., Dullien, T., Vinyals, O., and Kohli, P. Graph     arXiv:2003.05161, 2020. 
                 matching networks for learning the similarity of graph 
                 structured objects. In International Conference on Ma-       Rule, J.  The child as hacker:  building more human-like 
                 chine Learning, pp. 3835–3845. PMLR, 2019.                     models of learning. PhD thesis, MIT, 2020. 
﻿                                                  Large-scale few-shot program induction and synthesis 
               Scarselli, F., Gori, M., Tsoi, A. C., Hagenbuchner, M., and     Vassilev, V., Canal, P., Naumann, A., Moneta, L., and Russo, 
                 Monfardini, G. The graph neural network model. IEEE             P. Cling – the new interactive interpreter for ROOT 6. 
                 Transactions on Neural Networks, 20(1):61–80, 2009.           Vinyals, O., Blundell, C., Lillicrap, T., Kavukcuoglu, K., 
               Schmidhuber, J. Evolutionary principles in self-referential       and Wierstra, D. Matching networks for one shot learning. 
                 learning, or on learning how to learn: the meta-meta-           arXiv preprint arXiv:1606.04080, 2016. 
                 ... hook.  PhD thesis, Technische Universität München,        Xu, B., Qian, J., Zhang, X., Wu, Z., and Chen, L. A brief 
                 1987.                                                           survey of program slicing.  ACM SIGSOFT Software 
               Shafto, P., Goodman, N. D., and Griffths, T. L.  A ratio-         Engineering Notes, 30(2):1–36, 2005. 
                 nal account of pedagogical reasoning: Teaching by, and        Yasunaga, M. and Liang, P. Graph-based, self-supervised 
                 learning from, examples. Cognitive psychology, 71:55–           program repair from diagnostic feedback. arXiv preprint 
                 89, 2014.                                                       arXiv:2005.10636, 2020. 
               Shaw, D. E., Swartout, W. R., and Green, C. C. Inferring        Zavershynskyi, M., Skidanov, A., and Polosukhin, I. Naps: 
                 lisp programs from examples. In IJCAI, volume 75, pp.           Natural  program  synthesis  dataset.     arXiv  preprint 
                 260–267, 1975.                                                  arXiv:1807.03168, 2018. 
               Shin, R., Kant, N., Gupta, K., Bender, C., Trabucco, B., 
                 Singh, R., and Song, D.  Synthetic datasets for neural 
                 program synthesis.  arXiv preprint arXiv:1912.12345, 
                 2019. 
               Solar-Lezama, A., Tancau, L., Bodik, R., Seshia, S., and 
                 Saraswat, V. Combinatorial sketching for fnite programs. 
                 In Proceedings of the 12th international conference on 
                 Architectural support for programming languages and 
                 operating systems, pp. 404–415, 2006. 
               Tan, S. H., Yi, J., Mechtaev, S., Roychoudhury, A., et al. 
                 Codefaws: a programming competition benchmark for 
                 evaluating automated program repair tools.  In 2017 
                 IEEE/ACM 39th International Conference on Software 
                 Engineering Companion (ICSE-C), pp. 180–182. IEEE, 
                 2017. 
               Tate, R., Stepp, M., Tatlock, Z., and Lerner, S.  Equality 
                 saturation: a new approach to optimization. In Proceed-
                 ings of the 36th ACM SIGPLAN-SIGACT Symposium on 
                 Principles of Programming Languages, POPL 2009, Sa-
                 vannah, GA, USA, January 21-23, 2009, pp. 264–276, 
                 2009.  doi:  10.1145/1480881.1480915.  URL https: 
                 //doi.org/10.1145/1480881.1480915. 
               Thrun, S. and Pratt, L. Learning to learn. Springer Science 
                 & Business Media, 1998. 
               Triantafllou, E., Zhu, T., Dumoulin, V., Lamblin, P., Evci, 
                 U., Xu, K., Goroshin, R., Gelada, C., Swersky, K., Man-
                 zagol, P.-A., et al.  Meta-dataset: A dataset of datasets 
                 for learning to learn from few examples. arXiv preprint 
                 arXiv:1903.03096, 2019. 
               Tsantalis, N. and Chatzigeorgiou, A. Identifcation of extract 
                 method refactoring opportunities. In 2009 13th European 
                 Conference on Software Maintenance and Reengineering, 
                 pp. 119–128. IEEE, 2009. 
