                                               HiRoPE:LengthExtrapolationforCodeModelsUsingHierarchical
                                                                                                                                               Position
                                                                                                                                                 ∗                                                                             ∗
                                                                                           Kechi Zhang, Ge Li, Huangzhao Zhang, Zhi Jin
                                                       KeyLabofHighConfidenceSoftwareTechnology(PKU),MinistryofEducation
                                                                                        School of Computer Science, Peking University, China
                                                                          {zhangkechi,lige,zhang_hz,zhijin}@pku.edu.cn
                                                                                   Abstract                                                                                                Traditional Position Index
                                              Addressing the limitation of context length in                                                                                                           The token at position 100
                                              large language models for code-related tasks is                                                                                                                                           100th token
                                                                                                                                                                                             (…preceding tokens…) return a + b
                                              the primary focus of this paper. Existing LLMs                                                                                                                                       idx=100
                                              are constrained by their pre-trained context                                                                                                 Hierarchical Position Index
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     th
                                              lengths, leading to performance issues in han-                                                                                                           The token, in the 9 function,
                                              dling long complex code sequences. Inspired                                                                                                                                at position 100
                                                                                                                                                                                                                            def func1()…
                                              byhowhumanprogrammersnavigatecode,we                                                                                                                                         9th function
                                                                                                                                                                                                                            def func9()…
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         th
                                              introduce Hierarchical Rotary Position Embed-                                                                                                                                         10000 token
                                              ding (HiRoPE), a novel approach that enhances                                                                                                                                       return a + b
                                              the traditional rotary position embedding into                                                                                                                                       idx=(9,100)
                                              a hierarchical format based on the hierarchical                                                                    Figure 1: Illustration of the hierarchical position in
                                              structure of source code. HiRoPE offers easy                                                                       source code, such as function-level and token-level po-
                                              integration into existing LLMs without extra                                                                       sitions. We also show a simplified abstract syntax tree
                                              training costs. Our method is extensively eval-                                                                    of the code in the bottom left corner.
                                              uated with various LLMs, demonstrating stable
                                              performance in tasks such as language model-
                                              ing and long code completion. We also intro-
                                              duce a new long code understanding task with                                                                            Various methods have been developed to extend
                                              real-world code projects, in hopes of promoting                                                                    the context window of LLMs. Some approaches
                                              further development in this code-related field.                                                                    involve fine-tuning on extensive texts (Xiong et al.,
                                              Theoretically and experimentally, we find that                                                                     2023; Chen et al., 2023b,a; Peng et al., 2023),
                                              HiRoPEalsoaddresses the out-of-distribution                                                                       which can be resource-intensive and potentially
                                              issue in position encoding. Our HiRoPE signif-                                                                     lead to overfitting and loss of performance on
                                              icantly expands the context length capabilities                                                                    shorter sequences. There are also some training-
                                              of LLMs, enabling inference at lengths expo-
                                              nentially greater than the training length.                                                                        free methods (Xiao et al., 2023; Han et al., 2023;
                                      1 Introduction                                                                                                             Dingetal., 2023). However, these methods usually
                                                                                                                                                                 usewindowattentionrelyonlocalinformation,and
                                      Large language models (LLMs) such as LLaMA-2                                                                               ignore the long dependency in code. It is essential
                                     (Touvron et al., 2023b), and CodeLLaMA (Rozière                                                                             to incorporate certain structural characteristics of
                                      et al., 2023) have achieved significant performances                                                                       the code into position encoding to efficiently model
                                      in code-related tasks. These Transformer-based                                                                             these long-distance code dependencies.
                                      models excel in code comprehension and genera-                                                                                  Our work diverges from these methods by fo-
                                      tion but face a notable challenge: the limitation                                                                          cusing on the hierarchical information of source
                                      of maximum context length. LLMs are typically                                                                              code in position encoding, inspired by how human
                                      pre-trained with a context length ranging from 2k                                                                          programmers navigate code. Traditional positional
                                      to 16k tokens, which often proves insufficient for                                                                         encoding uses token counts for positioning, and
                                      complex, extended source code. Exceeding this                                                                              treats code as plain text. However, human pro-
                                      length limitation during inference may lead to per-                                                                        grammers often use hierarchical information in the
                                      formance degradation for these code models, par-                                                                           code, representing positions in the code efficiently
                                      ticularly in tasks like project-level code completion                                                                      through multi-level hierarchical positions. We pro-
                                      or long code generation.                                                                                                   poseahierarchical position approach that identifies
                                            *Corresponding authors.                                                                                              token positions within specific levels, such as func-
                                                                                                                                                      13615
                           Proceedings of the 62nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), pages 13615–13627
                                                                                          August 11-16, 2024 ©2024 Association for Computational Linguistics
﻿                   tions or statements. Figure 1 shows the comparison                ing language modeling and code completion.
                   of the traditional position and our hierarchical po-              We also introduce a new long code under-
                   sition. It is clear that the hierarchical positional              standing task with real-world code projects,
                   encoding, benefiting from the full utilization of                 in hopes of promoting further development in
                   structural information in the code, can more con-                 this code-related field.
                   veniently locate positional information within long             • We demonstrate that HiRoPE effectively ad-
                   code sequences. This method could more effec-                     dresses the out-of-distribution issue in posi-
                   tively model long dependencies in source code.                    tion encoding, enabling inference at lengths
                      Following such inspirations, we introduce a                    exponentially greater than the training length.
                   novel approach, Hierarchical Rotary Position Em-
                   bedding (HiRoPE), which enhances the popular                 2 Preliminary
                   rotary position embedding (RoPE) (Su et al., 2024)
                   into a hierarchical format. HiRoPE differentiates            We first introduce rotary position embedding in
                   itself by extracting hierarchical information from           Transformer in Section 2.1. While existing work
                   the source code and splitting the RoPE dimension             usually regards source code as plain text for model-
                   to represent different hierarchical levels. It simul-        ing, we will also introduce the ignored hierarchical
                   taneously models token-level relative location and           information in source code in Section 2.2.
                   higher-level relative location information. We also          2.1   Rotary Position Embedding in
                   add a window mechanism to ensure stability with                    Transformer
                   short texts, aligning with traditional positional en-
                   coding.                                                      Transformer models require explicit positional in-
                      HiRoPEisaplug-and-play solution, easily inte-             formationtobeinjected,typicallyintheformofpo-
                   grated into existing LLMs without additional train-          sitional encodings, to represent the order of inputs.
                   ing costs. Our extensive experiments with popu-              Recently, the rotary position embedding (RoPE)
                   lar LLMs on tasks like language modeling and to-             (Su et al., 2024) has become one of the most popu-
                   ken completion in long code contexts (CodeParrot,            lar and elegant position encoding strategies and is
                   2022) demonstrate its effectiveness. We compare              adopted by various LLMs (Touvron et al., 2023a,b;
                   HiRoPE with existing length extrapolation meth-              Rozière et al., 2023). The main point of the RoPE
                   odsusinglongcodebenchmarkssuchasLCC(Guo                      methodisusingabsolutepositionencodingtoshow
                   et al., 2023) and RepoBench (Liu et al., 2023a). We          relative position information. Formally, given a po-
                   also introduce a new long code understanding task            sition index m ∈ [0,L) and an embedding vector
                   namedcodesymbolunderstanding with real-world                 x := [x ,x ,...,x         ]⊤, where d is the dimen-
                                                                                         0   1        d−1
                   code libraries. Theoretically and experimentally,            sion of the attention head, RoPE defines a complex
                   wefind that HiRoPE effectively addresses the out-            function f(x,m) as follows:
                   of-distribution issue (Liu et al., 2023b) in position
                                                                                                         imθ              imθ
                                                                                  f(x,m) = [(x +ix )e       0,(x +ix )e      1,...,
                   encoding. Our HiRoPE significantly expands the                               0     1          2     3              (1)
                                                                                                                        imθd/2−1 ⊤
                                                                                                        (x    +ix     )e         ]
                   context length capabilities of LLMs, enabling in-                                      d−2      d−1
                   ference at lengths exponentially greater than the                          √
                   training length. We believe our work with HiRoPE             where i :=      −1is the imaginary unit and θj =
                                                                                       −2j/d
                   not only addresses a critical length limitation in           10000        .
                   LLMapplications but also opens new avenues for                  With RoPE, the self-attention score can be cal-
                   long-structured data modeling research.                      culated as:
                      In summary, we make the following main contri-
                   butions:                                                       a(m,n) = Re⟨f(q,m),f(k,n)⟩
                                                                                        d/2−1                                       
                      • Wepropose Hierarchical RoPE (HiRoPE), en-                          X                                i(m−n)θ
                                                                                  =Re         (q   +iq     )(k   −ik     )e        j
                        hancing the traditional rotary position embed-                           2j     2j+1   2j     2j+1
                        ding into a hierarchical format based on the                       j=0
                                                                                     d/2−1
                        hierarchical structure of source code, provid-            = X[(q k +q             k     )cos((m−n)θ )
                                                                                             2j 2j    2j+1 2j+1                j
                        ing improved extrapolation capabilities.                      j=0
                                                                                     +(q k       −q      k )sin((m−n)θ )]
                      • We conducted comprehensive experiments                           2j 2j+1    2j+1 2j                j
                        with LLMs on various long code tasks involv-              =: a(m−n)                                           (2)
                                                                          13616
﻿                   Here Re⟨...⟩ denotes the real part function for a             add a window mechanism, so that when dealing
                   complex number. q and k are the query and key                 with short texts, our proposed method is consistent
                   vector for a specific attention head. At each layer,          with the original positional encoding. An illustra-
                   RoPEisappliedonbothqueryandkeyembeddings                      tion of our HiRoPE is shown in Figure 2.
                   for computing attention scores. We can observe                3.1   Hierarchical format
                   that the calculated attention score is only depen-
                   dent on relative position m − n through trigono-              Unlike previous work that encodes the information
                   metric functions, which reflects the core of RoPE             of each position as a number index m ∈ [0,L), we
                   that uses the absolute position to represent the rel-         use a h-dimensional vector to represent the hierar-
                   ative distance. Existing studies show that when               chical position index from high-level to low-level,
                   dealing with long plain text, the RoPE will meet              where h is a hyperparameter that indicates how
                   O.O.D issues where the value of m − n during                  manylevels of information we consider in the en-
                   inference is unseen (Liu et al., 2023b), leading to           coding. We begin with a simple case that we set
                   poor performances.                                            h=2andeachtokenpositioncanberepresented
                                                                                 as (m ,m ). We use the higher and lower dimen-
                                                                                        1    2
                   2.2    Hierarchical Position in Source Code                   sions in RoPE respectively to represent these two
                   Most LLMs treat source code as plain text, pro-               hierarchical position indexes, so the Equation 1 can
                   cessing it as if it were ordinary natural language.           be rewritten as:
                   However, it is essential to take the structural in-           f′(x,m1,m2) =
                                                                                             im θ                         im θ
                   formation of code into mind. Source code can be               [(x +ix )e 1 0,...,(x         +ix      )e   1 ds/2−1,
                                                                                    0     1               d −2      d −1
                                                                                                           s         s
                   transformed into abstract syntax trees, and these                             im2θ                          im2θ      ⊤
                                                                                 (x   +ix      )e    ds/2,...,(x     +ix     )e    d/2−1]
                                                                                   d      d +1                   d−2     d−1
                   tree structures contain rich hierarchical position in-           s      s
                                                                                                                                       (3)
                   formation. For example, the code snippets usually             There are a total of d dimensions in RoPE, and we
                   can be split into several class or function units, and        use the lower d dimensions to represent the hierar-
                   each class/function contains various types of code                             s
                   blocks and statements. Figure 1 shows an illustra-            chical index of m1, and the remaining dimensions
                                                                                 to represent m . When we apply it to self-attention,
                   tion of the simplified abstract syntax tree for a code                        2
                   snippet in the bottom left corner. This higher-level          wecangetanewcalculation of the attention score:
                   positional information contains rich semantics of              hierarchicalAttn = Re⟨f(q,m ,m ),f(k,n ,n )⟩
                                                                                                                 1   2        1   2
                   source code, making it easy for human program-                    ds/2−1
                                                                                  = X [(q k +q              k    )cos((m −n )θ )
                   mers to locate and refer to different semantic parts.                      2j 2j    2j+1 2j+1          1    1   j
                   Therefore, in manyexistingprogramrepresentation                     j=0
                                                                                     +(q k       −q      k )sin((m −n )θ )]
                   tasks, this hierarchical information plays a very im-                 2j 2j+1     2j+1 2j         1    1  j
                                                                                         d/2−1
                   portant role (Allamanis et al., 2018; Zhang et al.,               + X [(q k +q               k     )cos((m −n )θ )
                   2023). However,fortoday’slargelanguagemodels,                                  2j 2j     2j+1 2j+1         2     2  j
                                                                                       j=d /2+1
                                                                                          s
                   this high-level hierarchical positional information               +(q k       −q      k )sin((m −n )θ )]
                                                                                         2j 2j+1     2j+1 2j         2    2  j
                   is almost ignored. In this paper, we try to incorpo-           =: a′(m −n ,m −n )
                   rate this hierarchical information into the position                    1    1   2     2
                                                                                                                                       (4)
                   encoding method.                                                                      ′
                                                                                 Theattention score a (...) we ultimately obtained
                   3 Hierarchical RoPE                                           through the inner product is quite elegant. It in-
                                                                                 cludes the relative position distance of various hi-
                   In this paper, we propose HiRoPE, a hierarchical              erarchical levels, and this form can be similarly
                   rotary position encoding for source code model-               extended to the representation of more hierarchi-
                   ing. Our proposed HiRoPE requires two modified                cal positional structures, as shown in Equation 5.
                   stages: ❶ Hierarchical Format: We first take                  Specifically, when h = 1, it remains the same as
                   the step to transfer the existing rotary position em-         the original RoPE.
                   bedding into a hierarchical format. We verify our
                   approach theoretically and find that the hierarchi-              hierarchicalAttnh
                                                                                    =Re⟨f(q,m ,...,m ),f(k,n ,...,n ))⟩
                   cal format can bring stable extrapolation ability for                            1         h          1        h
                   RoPE.❷WindowMechanism. Toensureperfor-                           =: a′(m −m ,...,m −n )
                                                                                              1      2          h     h
                   mance stability without further training, we also                                                                   (5)
                                                                           13617
﻿                                                                                       Relative Distance in Attention                             HiRoPE
                                            Absolute Distance                                           0                                            0
                                              in Code Tokens                                            1 0                                          1 0
                                                                                          Low dim       2 1 0                         Low Dim:       2 1 0
                                                                                        (Token-level)   3 2 1 0                    Same as original  3 2 1 0
                                                                                                        4 3 2 1 0                                    4 3 2 1 0
                                                                                                        5 4 3 2 1 0                                  5 4 3 2 1 0
                                                    hierarchial pos_idx:                                0                                            0
                                                 (function_idx,token_idx)                               0 0                                          1 0
                                             (0,0) (0,1) (0,2) (0,3) (0,4) (1,5) (1,6)   High dim       0 0 0                        High Dim:       2 1 0
                                                                                        (Func-level)    0 0 0 0                   Add  Window = 3    2 2 1 0
                                                                                                        1 1 1 1 0                                    3 3 2 1 0
                                                                                                        1 1 1 1 0 0                                  3 3 3 2 1 0
                           Figure 2: Overview of our HiRoPE. We transfer the existing position encoding method into a hierarchical format
                           (i.e.,, function-level and token-level) and apply it across different dimensions. We also add a window mechanism to
                           ensure performance stability (in this figure we set L                                     to 3).
                                                                                                         window
                               It indicates that the RoPE has the potential to be                                             Task                     Dataset             Avg. Length     Samples
                           transformed into a hierarchical form, and we can                                                                                 0-2048            1031.46         100
                                                                                                                           LongCode          CodeParrot     2048-4096         3667.76         100
                           use the hierarchical position index in the source                                          Language Modeling                     4096-8192         7074.57         100
                           code for this new form of RoPE, as shown in the                                                                                  8192-16384       14353.94         100
                                                                                                                           LongText                 ReRoPE-eval              21367.55         200
                           left part of Figure 2.                                                                     Language Modeling
                                                                                         −2j/d                           CodeSymbol           Real-world Code Project        12976.89         56
                               Theoriginal RoPE sets θj to 10000                                 , which                 Understanding
                           meansthat the lower the dimension, the higher its                                               LongCode                     LCC                  17855.73         300
                           frequency, and the more emphasis on modeling the                                               Completion                 RepoBench               21103.42         300
                           relative position information of short distances (Pal                                            Table 1: Statistics of the evaluation datasets
                           et al., 2023). Therefore, in our hierarchical format,
                           we use those low dimensions to represent token-
                           level information, and high dimensions to represent                                      ble in various scenarios with arbitrary input lengths.
                           higher-level hierarchical information, such as the                                       Anillustration of the final HiRoPE is shown in the
                           function level or statement level in source code.                                        right part of Figure 2.
                           3.2      WindowMechanism                                                                 4 ExperimentSetup
                           To ensure performance stability without further
                           training, we follow existing extrapolation methods                                       In this section, we aim to answer the following
                           (Xiao et al., 2023; Han et al., 2023) and add a win-                                     research questions through a series of experiments.
                           dowmechanism. Specifically, when dealing with                                            Detailsoftheevaluationdatasetstatisticsareshown
                           short code snippets, we believe that existing LLMs                                       in Table 1.
                           have already mastered the ability to model these                                             RQ1. How is the language modeling capa-
                           short semantic structures from vast pre-training                                         bility of HiRoPE on long code sequences? We
                           code datasets. Therefore, when calculating the at-                                       evaluate HiRoPE’s language modeling ability on
                           tention score, we directly use the original RoPE for                                     CodeParrot-valid dataset (CodeParrot, 2022) in
                           those parts that are shorter than a specific length                                      Section 5.1.
                           Lwindow. And for those long context parts that the                                           RQ2. How is the language modeling capa-
                           distance is larger than Lwindow, we transfer them to                                     bility of HiRoPE on long natural language se-
                           the new hierarchical format by adding Lwindow −1                                         quences? Thenatural language lacks the explicit
                           to each high-level distance. Our subsequent experi-                                      hierarchical structure information found in code,
                           mentshaveprovedthatevenwithoutanyadditional                                              so we have made some modifications: we set every
                           training, this window mechanism can bring strong                                        128 tokens as a segment, and encode it as higher-
                           stability, making the model’s performance applica-                                       level position information. We use the evaluation
                                                                                                            13618
﻿                                   LLaMA-2   ShearedLLaMA   TinyLLaMA   Vicuna     without training, including NTK (bloc97, 2023),
                     Para.            7B          1.3B         1.1B      7B        ReRoPE (Su, 2023) and Self-Extend (Jin et al.,
                     L               4096         4096         2048      2048
                       pretrain                                                    2024). ReRoPE sets a window when calculating
                     Vocab Size      32000       32000        32000     32000      the relative distance, and clips those distances out-
                     Hidden Size     4096         2048         2048      4096
                     Attention Head   32          16            32       32        side the window. Self-Extend uses group atten-
                     RoPEDim          128         128           64       128       tion with the floor operation to calculate relative
                                Table 2: Statistics of base LLMs                   distances. These methods have shown impressive
                                                                                   performance on long context language modeling.
                    dataset from ReRoPE-eval 1 (Su, 2023) in Section               Wealsomakecomparisonswiththeoriginal RoPE
                    5.2. It is a dataset curated from Common Crawl                 method, which is denoted as “origin” in the first
                    (Crawl, 2023), refined by length-based selection               rowofTable4,5and6.
                    criteria.                                                      4.3    Inference Settings
                       RQ3. Howdoes HiRoPE perform in under-
                    standingreal-world,long-codeprojects? Toeval-                  In our experiments, our HiRoPE uses a two-layer
                    uate the effect of the method in real long-code sce-           hierarchy, accounting for the position index at the
                    narios, we design a new evaluation task on real                token and function/class levels of the source code
                    code projects: Code Symbol Understanding in                    based on tree-sitter (Brunsfeld et al., 2024). For
                    Section 5.3. Given a long code file, the model                 long context in natural language, we make some
                    is required to output all the function names and               modifications and set every 128 tokens as a higher-
                    class names defined in it. We extract long code                level segment. We set the split dimension half of
                    files from popular open-sourced code repositories,             the total: ds = 0.5 ∗ dtotal, and choose a window
                    especially those newly updated code projects to                length: Lwindow = 512. We keep the hyperparam-
                    avoid data leakage. Details of these code projects             eters the same for those state-of-the-art baselines
                    are shown in Table 3.                                          for a fair comparison. We use greedy search decod-
                       RQ4. HowdoesHiRoPEperformonexisting                         ing for generation. We use 4 A6000 GPUs for all
                    benchmarks for long code completion?                   We      experiments.
                    further perform the evaluation using two long code
                    completion benchmarks: LCC (Guo et al., 2023)                  4.4    Details of Code Symbol Understanding
                    and RepoBench (Liu et al., 2023a) in Section 5.4.                     task
                       RQ5. Whatistheimpactofvarioussettings
                    in HiRoPE? Todemonstrate that each setting in                  In RQ3, we design a new task: Code Symbol Un-
                    the design of our HiRoPE works, we carry out                   derstanding. Given a long code context, the model
                    extensive ablation studies that include the dimen-             is required to output all the function names and
                    sions’ split settings, the window mechanism, and               class names defined in it. We extract long code
                    the high-level segment split strategy in Section 5.5.          files from popular open-sourced code repositories,
                    4.1   Base LLMs                                                especially those newly updated code projects to
                                                                                   avoid data leakage. We construct a static analysis
                    Themodelsusedinclude LLaMA-2(7B)(Touvron                       tool to get the abstract syntax tree of each code file,
                    et al., 2023b), Sheared-LLaMA (1.3B) (Xia et al.,              and then get all defined function and class names
                    2023), TinyLlama (1.1B) (Zhang et al., 2024), and              in it as the ground-truth output symbols. Details
                    Vicuna (7B) (Chiang et al., 2023). This model                  of these code projects are shown in Table 3. We
                    choice is driven by their widespread use and popu-             show the number of files we extracted from each
                    larity, as well as the constraints of our computing            project as well as the average length of these code
                    capabilities. Details are provided in Table 2.                 files. We also show the average number of symbols
                    4.2   Baselines                                                and their location statistics in the table.
                                                                                      In Figure 3 we show an illustration of our pro-
                    Considering training on long context sequences                 posed new task. We replace the input_code part
                    is resource-intensive and time-consuming, we fo-               with each code file, and use the task prompt to
                    cus on those popular length extrapolation methods              guide models to extract and output all defined func-
                       1https://github.com/bojone/rerope/                          tion and class names in input code. We also show
                    blob/main/samples_15k.jsonl                                    an example output in the figure.
                                                                              13619
﻿                                   Github Repo              File Nums   File Length  Avg. Symbols    Min. Symbol Loc   Max. SymbolLoc
                                   ddbourgin/numpy-ml           2          14055          15               927              10845
                                   gradio-app/gradio            1          12938          11               272              12265
                                   huggingface/accelerate       4         12814.5         11.5             379              12500
                                   huggingface/diffusers        4        13324.75         16.2             276               8347
                                   huggingface/optimum          1          13491          11               580              12868
                                   huggingface/peft             1          15457          11               514               8525
                                   huggingface/transformers     18        12919.4         12.7             239              14514
                                   langchain-ai/langchain/      2          14195          11.5             285              10790
                                   numpy/numpy                  6         11158.8         14               100              12026
                                   tensorflow/tensorflow        17        13191.7         13.4             285              14920
                                   Total                        56       12976.89        13.17             100              14920
                     Table 3: Statistics of Code Symbol Understanding task. We show the number of files we extracted from each project
                     as well as the average length of these code files. We also show the average number of symbols and their location
                     statistics in the table.
                               def add_func(a,b):           Input_code                 range for those long source codes. Specifically, for
                                    return a + b                                       ultra-long code sequences (length over 8192), Hi-
                                         …                                             RoPEachieves the best results in all metrics and
                               # Task: Extract all defined function                    under all settings. This fully demonstrates the ad-
                               names and class names from the                          vantagesofourHiRoPEinmodelinglongsequence
                               above code snippet.              Task                   codes. Our method also shows generalization abil-
                               extracted_entities =            prompt                  ities. The four models evaluated have differences
                                                 An example output:                    in model parameters, pre-training data, and pre-
                                                 [add_func, …,]                        training length, yet our method has shown very
                                                                                       good results on all these models.
                     Figure 3: Illustration of Code Symbol Understanding                   It is worth noting that our method does not im-
                     task. We use the task prompt to guide models to extract           pair the model’s performance on shorter code. We
                     and output all defined function and class names in input          noted that some popular length extension meth-
                     code.                                                             ods, such as NTK, can impair the performance on
                                                                                       short code. Thanks to our window mechanism, our
                     5 ResultsandAnalyses                                              method stays on par with the baseline model on
                                                                                       shorter datasets (length 0-2048) and even surpasses
                     5.1    LongCodeLanguageModeling                                   the baseline on some metrics. HiRoPE demon-
                     Language modeling is the most fundamental and                     strates consistently excellent language modeling
                     the least requirement for a LLM. We evaluate Hi-                  capabilities in various code length scenarios.
                     RoPE’slanguage modeling ability on CodeParrot-                    5.2    LongTextLanguageModeling
                     valid dataset. We divide the original dataset into
                     different length intervals. The experiment results                In addition to testing the ability of language mod-
                     are shown in Table 4. A smaller loss and a smaller                eling on long code, we also evaluate its effects on
                     ppl indicate a stronger language modeling capacity                long natural language texts. We set every 128 to-
                     of the corresponding model. Conversely, a larger                  kens as a high-level segment. We use the ReRoPE-
                     acc suggests a stronger capability of the respective              eval dataset, and results are shown in Table 5. In
                     modelincodecompletiononthegivendataset. The                       addition to calculating metrics on all tokens (refer
                     origin indicates that we directly use the original                to "all_..." in the table), we also record metrics on
                     setting of the model to evaluate.                                 the last 2048 tokens of each data (refer to "last_...").
                        Experiments show that original LLMs perform                        Wefind that our HiRoPE can also achieve sig-
                     badly on the long code language modeling task.                    nificant improvement. HiRoPE achieves the best
                     Even when the length slightly exceeds the pre-                    results on almost all metrics. Another interesting
                     training length, the ppl of all models exceed 45,                 observation is that, given sufficient context, the
                     demonstrating their essential lack of modeling and                model can utilize this contextual information to
                     understanding capabilities for longer codes. When                 perform better when generating later tokens. That
                     weapply length extrapolation methods, all meth-                   is to say, the metrics of "last_..." should be better
                     ods can reduce the loss and ppl into an acceptable                than those of "all_...". However, we observe that
                                                                                 13620
﻿                                                             Dataset Length:          0-2048                 2048-4096                  4096-8192                   8192-16384
                                            Para. Lpretrain                   loss ↓   ppl ↓   acc ↑   loss ↓   ppl ↓   acc ↑   loss ↓    ppl ↓     acc ↑   loss ↓     ppl ↓     acc ↑
                                                             origin           0.8579 2.3583 0.8065 0.9820 2.6698 0.7551          nan       nan       nan     nan       nan        nan
                                                             NTK              1.1107 3.0365 0.7472 1.0469 2.8488 0.7414 0.9858           2.6800    0.7729 1.0181      2.7678     0.7630
                           LLaMA-2           7B      4096    ReRoPE           0.8593 2.3615 0.8054 0.7278 2.0705 0.8121 0.6633           1.9411    0.8411 0.7187      2.0518     0.8243
                                                             Self-Extend      0.8588 2.3604 0.8055 0.7209 2.0562 0.8147 0.6519           1.9192    0.8441 0.6983      2.0103     0.8290
                                                             HiRoPE           0.8586 2.3598 0.8060 0.7185 2.0514 0.8153 0.6482           1.9121    0.8452 0.6821      1.9780     0.8332
                                                             origin           1.2874 3.6235 0.7341 1.3103 3.7074 0.7019 3.8381           46.4375   0.4866 5.6958     297.6160    0.3211
                                                             NTK              1.6242 5.0744 0.6607 1.5047 4.5029 0.6619 1.3708           3.9383    0.7015 1.3657      3.9183     0.6964
                           ShearedLLaMA 1.3B         4096    ReRoPE           1.2897 3.6316 0.7332 1.0497 2.8567 0.7560 0.9699           2.6376    0.7846 1.0044      2.7303     0.7716
                                                             Self-Extend      1.2892 3.6300 0.7337 1.0428 2.8371 0.7586 0.9568           2.6034    0.7874 0.9804      2.6656     0.7768
                                                             HiRoPE           1.2888 3.6285 0.7338 1.0382 2.8242 0.7600 0.9514           2.5894    0.7885 0.9660      2.6273     0.7811
                                                             origin           1.0788 2.9410 0.7594 4.1732 64.9235 0.4506 6.6603 780.8009 0.2630 7.9938 2962.5881                 0.1682
                                                             NTK              1.1837 3.2664 0.7405 1.0952 2.9899 0.7256 0.9719           2.6430    0.7733 1.0021      2.7240     0.7626
                           TinyLlama        1.1B     2048    ReRoPE           0.9703 2.6388 0.7877 0.8251 2.2821 0.7905 0.7685           2.1565    0.8210 0.8275      2.2877     0.8040
                                                             Self-Extend      0.9698 2.6375 0.7856 0.8123 2.2530 0.7931 0.7577           2.1333    0.8235 0.8119      2.2521     0.8073
                                                             HiRoPE           0.9743 2.6493 0.7881 0.8268 2.2861 0.7981 0.7683           2.1562    0.8208 0.8040      2.2345     0.8094
                                                             origin           1.1787 3.2502 0.7551 4.6046 99.9449 0.4473 7.7207 2254.4730 0.2597 9.9449 20846.3927 0.1601
                                                             NTK              1.3417 3.8255 0.7150 1.2587 3.5208 0.7068 1.1809           3.2573    0.7344 1.1912      3.2911     0.7285
                           Vicuna            7B      2048    ReRoPE           1.0716 2.9201 0.7800 0.8760 2.4012 0.7912 0.8138           2.2566    0.8182 0.8580      2.3585     0.8023
                                                             Self-Extend      1.0710 2.9183 0.7802 0.8735 2.3953 0.7891 0.7988           2.2228    0.8220 0.8351      2.3049     0.8066
                                                             HiRoPE           1.0707 2.9174 0.7799 0.8724 2.3926 0.7903 0.8002           2.2261    0.8213 0.8314      2.2965     0.8080
                         Table 4: Language Modeling Ability on CodeParrot-valid dataset. “nan” indicates that the model performs
                         significantly poor on the given setting.
                                                    last loss ↓ last ppl ↓ last acc ↑ all loss ↓ all ppl ↓ all acc ↑                                             LongCode
                                         origin      9.3083   >1000   0.0194   7.3486  >1000 0.1466                                   CodeSymbol                Completion
                                         NTK         2.1338   8.4468  0.5553   2.2745 9.7234    0.53                                  Understanding             (Edit Sim ↑)
                          TinyLlama      ReRoPE      1.8448   6.327   0.6008    1.903  6.7062 0.5867                                    (Recall ↑)        LCC             RepoBench
                                         Self-Extend 1.7904   5.9916  0.6089   1.8749 6.5201 0.5908                                                 0-4k 4k-8k >8k 0-4k 4k-8k >8k
                                         HiRoPE      1.7829   5.9474  0.6102   1.8717 6.4991 0.5913                           origin     0.0012     54.5   4.36  4.08  8.29  6.79  6.59
                                         origin      8.5027   >1000   0.0412   5.5237  250.5   0.274         LLaMA-2         ReRoPE      0.0837     65.83 67.43 63.22 52.82 47.85 45.38
                                         NTK         2.3596  10.5863  0.5159   2.4056 11.0853 0.5059                         HiRoPE      0.0911     66.61 69.93 65.38 52.20 53.30 51.24
                          ShearedLLaMAReRoPE         1.7952   6.0205   0.605   1.8514 6.3687 0.5932
                                         Self-Extend 1.7662   5.8486  0.6105   1.8348  6.264   0.5966                         origin     0.0067     27.17 3.33   2.52  4.39  2.94  2.35
                                         HiRoPE      1.7622   5.8252  0.6113   1.8332 6.2536 0.5963          ShearedLLaMA ReRoPE         0.0743     35.56 36.1 36.91 34.03 37.37 33.44
                                                                                                                             HiRoPE      0.0809     46.13 51.67 46.33 40.17 39.98 39.52
                         Table 5: Language Modeling Ability on ReRoPE-eval                                                    origin     0.0067     17.29 5.45   6.28  7.91  7.53  7.07
                                                                                                             TinyLLaMA       ReRoPE      0.1214     49.22 57.20 53.11 37.72 40.50 39.38
                         dataset. In addition to calculating metrics on all tokens                                           HiRoPE      0.1415     35.17 42.83 49.92 42.48 43.53 39.82
                         (refer to "all_..."), we also record metrics on the last                                             origin     0.0067     18.47 2.56   2.76  3.67  2.49  2.32
                                                                                                             Vicuna          ReRoPE      0.0636     57.95 59.73 58.52 42.78 43.65 45.23
                         2048 tokens of each data (refer to "last_..." ).                                                    HiRoPE      0.0721     63.42 62.01 64.42 37.10 42.30 45.93
                                                                                                            Table 6: Performance on Code Symbol Understanding
                         for the original model, the situation is contrary to                               and Long Code Completion.
                         this. We attribute this to the fact that the original
                         model’s ability to model long sequence languages                                   thetic evaluation (gkamradt, 2023), but our code
                         is so poor that it can’t utilize that distant contextual                           symbol understanding task is more realistic and
                         information at all. Our HiRoPE can significantly                                   code-related. Task examples are shown in Figure 3.
                         improve the model’s ability to handle long codes                                   Weuserecall as the evaluation metric.
                         and textual data, without requiring any training,                                      Our experiments in Table 6 have proven that
                         reflecting its practical value.                                                    this seemingly simple task is extremely difficult for
                         5.3      CodeSymbolUnderstanding                                                   LLMs. Wealsoevaluate this task using GPT-3.5-
                                                                                                            16k (GPT-3.5, 2023) and find that its result is only
                         To evaluate the effect of the method in real long-                                 0.72. All these LLMs are not ideal in this more
                         code scenarios, we have designed an evaluation                                     realistic code symbol understanding task. Our Hi-
                         task for real code projects: Code Symbol Under-                                    RoPEhasbeenimprovedfromtheperspectiveof
                         standing. Given a long code context, the model is                                  positional encoding, enabling the model to per-
                         required to output all the function names and class                                ceive structural hierarchy changes in the code, thus
                         names defined in it. These pre-defined functions                                   achieving relatively good results. Compared to the
                         and classes are reused frequently in actual code de-                               original models, our HiRoPE can achieve almost a
                         velopment. For code models, understanding which                                    hundredfold improvement on average across four
                         functionsandclassesaredefinedinthecodeproject                                      models. We release our dataset in hopes of pro-
                         is a basic capability requirement. This task is in-                                moting further development in this code-related
                         spired by the popular "Needle in a Haystack" syn-                                  field.
                                                                                                     13621
﻿                                                                               and [4k-8k]. For shorter code data, we observe
                                                                               a decreasing trend in ppl as the window size in-
                                                                               creases. This validates that the window mechanism
                                                                               can allow the model to retain its original computa-
                                                                               tional mechanisms and better handle short-distance
                                                                               dependencies. For longer code data, ppl behaves
                                                                               anomalously when the window size is very small.
                                                                               This also indicates that window mechanisms play a
                                                                               key role in modeling long-distance dependencies.
                                                                                  Wechangethehigh-level segment split strategy.
                   Figure 4: Ablation Studies including the settings of the    In addition to dividing the hierarchy at the func-
                   dimension split, the window mechanism, and the high-        level, we also try to split at the code statement
                   level segment split strategy.                               level as well as implementing a strategy of split-
                                                                               ting continuous n-tokens as a high-level segment
                   5.4   LongCodeCompletion                                    (n = 128, 512, 1024). Experiments show that divid-
                                                                               ing at the function level achieves the best results.
                   Wefurther perform the evaluation using two real-            Thesemantics within a function are relatively simi-
                   world long code completion benchmarks: LCC                  lar, while the semantics between functions usually
                   and RepoBench. Given a long code context, the               vary greatly. It is necessary to divide long code
                   model is required to generate the complete next             sequences into levels according to functions and
                   line of code. We follow the experiment settings             classes.
                   in Longbench-E (Bai et al., 2023) and use edit
                   similarity as metrics. Results are shown in Table 6.        6 Discussion
                      OurHiRoPEalsoachievesstable improvements                 6.1    Mitigating Out-of-Domain Issues in Long
                   on this long code-related task. The input code con-                Contexts
                   text is filled with various predefined functions and
                   classes. Our method can effectively sense these             Existing work (Liu et al., 2023b) shows that LLMs
                   contents, handle these complex dependencies, and            fail on input out of the pretraining context win-
                   successfully use those functions that are defined           dowbecause of the Out-Of-Distribution (O.O.D)
                   far away during generation. Under two dataset sce-          issues. We take the inspiration to explain it from
                   narios, our method consistently outperforms other           a cyclical perspective. In RoPE, each dimension
                   baseline settings. The results reflect the practicality     is composed of trigonometric functions, and its pe-
                                                                                                                 2π                  2j
                   and generalization ability of our method.                   riod can be denoted as T =            =2π∗10000d.
                                                                                                           j     θj
                   5.5   Ablation Study                                        Onlythose dimensions that have been completely
                                                                               trained within the pre-training length can be con-
                   In our experiments, ❶ we set the split dimension            sidered as a reliable part for extrapolation, others
                   half of the total ds = 0.5 ∗ dtotal and ❶ choose a          wouldencounter O.O.D issues when dealing with
                   window length ❷ Lwindow = 512. ❸ Our hierar-                problems of extrapolation. We can then get those
                   chical position includes both the token and func-           reliable dimensions by calculating T < L                .
                                                                                                                        j      pretrain
                   tion/class levels of the source code. We further            The calculated dim split is 0.70 and 0.63 for the
                   carry out extensive ablation studies including these        four models in our experiments (Table 7). We are
                   settings and results are shown in Figure 4.                 surprised to find that it is similar to the ratio we
                      Wechoosedifferent dimension splitting ratios to          obtained in the ablation study in Figure 4. Our
                   observe the performance of LLaMA-2 and TinyL-               HiRoPE uses those high dimensions to represent
                   LaMA in terms of ppl on CodeParrot [4k-8k].                 higher-level position index information, and prop-
                   Whenthesplit ratio is 1, the HiRoPE degenerates             erly applies them to smaller input numbers, thus
                   into the original model. Specifically, both models          mitigating O.O.D issues in long code contexts.
                   showsignificant fluctuations in ppl between ratios             Thetraditional RoPE uses a number m as the po-
                   of [0.6,0.7]. We will explore the reason in Section         sition index to represent position information. Due
                   6.1.                                                        to the O.O.D problem in high dimensions, its reli-
                      We change the window length to observe the               able range is {m ∈ [0,L             ]}. In our HiRoPE,
                                                                                                          pretrain
                   performance of LLaMA-2 on CodeParrot [0-2k]                 we use a two-layer hierarchy as (m ,m ) and
                                                                                                                           1    2
                                                                          13622
﻿                                                                            maydecreasequitedrastically. Recent studies have
                                                                            explored ways to expand the context length. Po-
                                                                            sition Interpolation (Chen et al., 2023b) linearly
                                                                            down-scales the input position indices to match the
                                                                            original context window size of LLMs with several
                                                                            training steps. Similar studies (Chen et al., 2023a;
                                                                            Peng et al., 2023; Chen et al., 2023c; Guo et al.,
                  Figure 5: Performance of Short-ShearedLLaMA on            2023) also require fine-tuning. However, these
                  CodeParrot dataset. The training length is set to 128.    methods need additional tuning in longer contexts
                  Theresults suggest our method has the potential to ex-    or face a disastrous collapse after the extrapolation
                  trapolate code models at an exponential length.           bound. There are also some approaches without
                                                                            training. Some studies use window attention to clip
                  the reliable range is {m     ∈ [0,L          ], m   ∈     the long sequences such as (Xiao et al., 2023; Han
                                             1         pretrain     2       et al., 2023; Ding et al., 2023)). However, these
                  [0,L         ]}. It proves that under ideal circum-
                       pretrain                                             methods rely on local information and may not ef-
                  stances, HiRoPE can effectively extrapolate to the        fectively expand the context window, struggling
                  length of Lh in an exponential ratio, where h is the
                  hierarchy layer. We attempt to explore the upper          with long dependencies in code. Recently, some
                  limit of our HiRoPE’s extrapolation performance           methods have explored modifying the relative dis-
                  in the experiment in the next Section 6.2.                tance to extend the extrapolation length (bloc97,
                                                                            2023; Su, 2023; Jin et al., 2024) and focus on the
                  6.2   UpperLimitofHiRoPE’sPerformance                     natural language text. We pursue the research line
                  Due to computational resource constraints, we             of training-free methods and propose considering
                  made the following modifications based on Sec-            the structural information of the code when model-
                  tion 5.1: ❶ Firstly, in order to obtain a base            ing the position. Our work is inspired by the hierar-
                  model of suitable length, we designed a training          chical embedding in our former work (Zhang et al.,
                  strategy to obtain a shorter context length LLM,          2023). We notice hierarchical positions are used in
                  namedShortLLM:Weusethepositioninterpola-                  some concurrent work (He et al., 2024; Lu et al.,
                  tion (Chen et al., 2023b) method reversely to re-         2024) in NLP and CV domains. We expand the
                  duce the input length of some mainstream models           traditional RoPE method into a hierarchical format
                  to L      =128atasmallertraining cost. Specifi-           and prove the effectiveness of our HiRoPE through
                       short                                                theoretical derivations and practical experiments.
                  cally, given a position index m in the original RoPE,        .
                  we use the new index α          ∗ m to replace it as
                                             short
                  shown in Table 8. We fine-tune short models for           8 Conclusion
                  1000 steps. ❷ We resample the CodeParrot-valid
                  dataset, further refining it into smaller distance        WeproposeHiRoPE,atraining-free solution to the
                  ranges, each range containing up to 50 test samples.      context length limitation in LLMs for long code
                  Theresults are shown in Figure 5 and 6.                   modeling. We integrate the hierarchical structure
                     Our trained ShortLLM successfully demon-               of source code into position encoding of LLMs.
                  strates the expected performance: the performance         Experiments demonstrate that HiRoPE achieves
                  drastically decreases after surpassing the training       stable improvements on diverse code-related tasks.
                  length Lshort = 128. We then apply our Hi-                Ourworknotonlyaddresses a critical limitation in
                  RoPEaswellasthebaselineReRoPE.OurHiRoPE                   LLMapplications but also opens new avenues for
                  demonstrates a more stable trend on long code se-         long structured data modeling research.
                                                               2
                  quences, even at the position close to L          . It
                                                               short        9 Acknowledgments
                  suggests our method has the potential to extrapo-
                  late code models at an exponential length.                This research is supported by the National Key
                  7 RelatedWork                                             R&DProgramunderGrantNo. 2023YFB4503801,
                                                                            the National Natural Science Foundation of China
                  Existing large language models are originally             under Grant No. 62072007, 62192733, 61832009,
                  trained with fixed context sizes. When dealing            62192730, and the Major Program (JD) of Hubei
                  with longer sequences, the model’s performance            Province (No.2023BAA024).
                                                                       13623
﻿                 Limitations                                              ous length extrapolation for large language models.
                                                                         CoRR,abs/2310.16450.
                 There are several limitations to our work that we
                 aim to address:                                       ShouyuanChen,ShermanWong,LiangjianChen,and
                   Firstly, constrained by computational resources,      Yuandong Tian. 2023b. Extending context window
                 wechoosemodelsbelow7Bforexperiments. The                 of large language models via positional interpolation.
                                                                         CoRR,abs/2306.15595.
                 fourmodelsevaluatedhavedifferencesinmodelpa-          Yuhan Chen, Ang Lv, Ting-En Lin, Changyu Chen,
                 rameters, pre-training data, and pre-training length,   Yuchuan Wu, Fei Huang, Yongbin Li, and Rui Yan.
                 yet our method has shown very good results on all        2023c. Fortify the shortest stave in attention: En-
                 these models. We will attempt to conduct experi-         hancing context awareness of large language models
                 ments on models with larger parameters and more          for effective tool use. CoRR, abs/2312.04455.
                 complex structures to promote the development of      Wei-Lin Chiang, Zhuohan Li, Zi Lin, Ying Sheng,
                 the LLMcommunity.                                        ZhanghaoWu,HaoZhang,LianminZheng,Siyuan
                   Next, our discussion on the upper limit of the         Zhuang, Yonghao Zhuang, Joseph E Gonzalez, et al.
                 HiRoPE’sperformance tends to lean towards theo-          2023. Vicuna: An open-source chatbot impressing
                 retical derivation. We have designed a set of Short-     gpt-4 with 90%* chatgpt quality. See https://vicuna.
                                                                          lmsys. org (accessed 14 April 2023).
                 LLMexperimentstoproveourconclusions. It sug-          CodeParrot. 2022. https://huggingface.co/codeparrot.
                 gests our method has the potential to extrapolate
                 code models at an exponential length, so for the      Common Crawl. 2023. Common crawl. https://
                 LLaMA-2modelwith L                =4096, we can          commoncrawl.org/.
                                          pretrain
                                                         2
                 theoretically extrapolate its length to L       ≈
                                                         pretrain      Jiayu Ding, Shuming Ma, Li Dong, Xingxing Zhang,
                 16,000,000. We are not clear whether some set-           Shaohan Huang, Wenhui Wang, Nanning Zheng, and
                 tings will implicitly affect the performance of the      Furu Wei. 2023. Longnet: Scaling transformers to 1,
                 model. We will continue to explore the robust-           000, 000, 000 tokens. CoRR, abs/2307.02486.
                 ness of this experimental idea and try to explore     gkamradt. 2023. Needle in a haystack - pressure testing
                 the maximumperformanceofourmethodonreal                  llms.    https://github.com/gkamradt/
                 LLMs.                                                    LLMTest_NeedleInAHaystack/tree/
                                                                          main.
                 References                                            GPT-3.5. 2023.    https://platform.openai.
                                                                          com/docs/models/gpt-3-5.
                 Miltiadis Allamanis, Marc Brockschmidt, and Mah-      Daya Guo, Canwen Xu, Nan Duan, Jian Yin, and Ju-
                   moud Khademi. 2018. Learning to represent pro-         lian J. McAuley. 2023. Longcoder: A long-range pre-
                   grams with graphs. In 6th International Conference     trained language model for code completion. In In-
                   on Learning Representations, ICLR 2018, Vancouver,     ternational Conference on Machine Learning, ICML
                   BC, Canada, April 30 - May 3, 2018, Conference        2023, 23-29 July 2023, Honolulu, Hawaii, USA,
                   Track Proceedings.                                     pages 12098–12107.
                 Yushi Bai, Xin Lv, Jiajie Zhang, Hongchang Lyu,       Chi Han, Qifan Wang, Wenhan Xiong, Yu Chen, Heng
                   Jiankai Tang, Zhidian Huang, Zhengxiao Du, Xiao       Ji, and Sinong Wang. 2023. Lm-infinite: Simple
                   Liu, Aohan Zeng, Lei Hou, Yuxiao Dong, Jie Tang,       on-the-fly length generalization for large language
                   and Juanzi Li. 2023. Longbench: A bilingual, mul-      models. CoRR, abs/2308.16137.
                   titask benchmark for long context understanding.
                   CoRR,abs/2308.14508.                                Zhenyu He, Guhao Feng, Shengjie Luo, Kai Yang,
                                                                          DiHe,Jingjing Xu, Zhi Zhang, Hongxia Yang, and
                 bloc97.  2023.       Ntk-aware   scaled  rope   al-      Liwei Wang. 2024. Two stones hit one bird: Bilevel
                   lows llama models to have extended (8k+)               positional encoding for better length extrapolation.
                   context   size  without   any   fine-tuning  and      CoRR,abs/2401.16421.
                   minimal    perplexity degradation.       https:
                   //www.reddit.com/r/LocalLLaMA/                      Hongye Jin, Xiaotian Han, Jingfeng Yang, Zhimeng
                   comments/14lz7j5/ntkaware_scaled_                     Jiang, Zirui Liu, Chia-Yuan Chang, Huiyuan Chen,
                   rope_allows_llama_models_to_have/.                     and Xia Hu. 2024.    LLM maybe longlm: Self-
                                                                          extend LLM context window without tuning. CoRR,
                 Max Brunsfeld, Andrew Hlynskyi, Amaan Qureshi,           abs/2401.01325.
                   Patrick Thomson, Josh Vera, and et al. 2024. tree-
                   sitter/tree-sitter: v0.21.0-pre-release-1.          Tianyang Liu, Canwen Xu, and Julian J. McAuley.
                                                                          2023a.   Repobench: Benchmarking repository-
                 Guanzheng Chen, Xin Li, Zaiqiao Meng, Shangsong          level code auto-completion systems.      CoRR,
                   Liang, and Lidong Bing. 2023a. CLEX: continu-          abs/2306.03091.
                                                                  13624
﻿                 Xiaoran Liu, Hang Yan, Shuo Zhang, Chenxin An,          Kechi Zhang, Zhuo Li, Zhi Jin, and Ge Li. 2023. Im-
                    Xipeng Qiu, and Dahua Lin. 2023b. Scaling laws of       plant global and local hierarchy information to se-
                    rope-based extrapolation. CoRR, abs/2310.05209.         quence based code representation models. In 31st
                                                                            IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program
                 ZeyuLu,ZidongWang,DiHuang,ChengyueWu,Xihui                 Comprehension, ICPC 2023, Melbourne, Australia,
                    Liu, Wanli Ouyang, and Lei Bai. 2024. Fit: Flexi-       May15-16,2023,pages157–168.
                    ble vision transformer for diffusion model. CoRR,
                    abs/2402.12376.                                      Peiyuan Zhang, Guangtao Zeng, Tianduo Wang, and
                                                                            Wei Lu. 2024. Tinyllama: An open-source small
                 Arka Pal, Deep Karkhanis, Manley Roberts, Samuel           language model. CoRR, abs/2401.02385.
                    Dooley, Arvind Sundararajan, and Siddartha Naidu.
                    2023. Giraffe: Adventures in expanding context
                    lengths in llms. CoRR, abs/2308.10882.
                 BowenPeng, Jeffrey Quesnelle, Honglu Fan, and En-
                    rico Shippole. 2023. Yarn: Efficient context win-
                    dow extension of large language models. CoRR,
                    abs/2309.00071.
                 Baptiste Rozière, Jonas Gehring, Fabian Gloeckle, Sten
                    Sootla, Itai Gat, Xiaoqing Ellen Tan, Yossi Adi,
                    Jingyu Liu, Tal Remez, Jérémy Rapin, et al. 2023.
                    Codellama: Openfoundationmodelsforcode. arXiv
                    preprint arXiv:2308.12950.
                 Jianlin Su. 2023. Rectified rotary position embeddings.
                    https://github.com/bojone/rerope.
                 Jianlin Su, Murtadha H. M. Ahmed, Yu Lu, Shengfeng
                    Pan, Wen Bo, and Yunfeng Liu. 2024. Roformer: En-
                    hanced transformer with rotary position embedding.
                    Neurocomputing, 568:127063.
                 HugoTouvron,Thibaut Lavril, Gautier Izacard, Xavier
                    Martinet, Marie-Anne Lachaux, Timothée Lacroix,
                    Baptiste Rozière, Naman Goyal, Eric Hambro, Faisal
                    Azhar, Aurélien Rodriguez, Armand Joulin, Edouard
                    Grave, and Guillaume Lample. 2023a. Llama: Open
                    and efficient foundation language models. CoRR,
                    abs/2302.13971.
                 Hugo Touvron, Louis Martin, Kevin Stone, Peter Al-
                    bert, Amjad Almahairi, and et al. 2023b. Llama 2:
                    Openfoundation and fine-tuned chat models. CoRR,
                    abs/2307.09288.
                 MengzhouXia,TianyuGao,ZhiyuanZeng,andDanqi
                    Chen. 2023. Sheared llama: Accelerating language
                    model pre-training via structured pruning. CoRR,
                    abs/2310.06694.
                 Guangxuan Xiao, Yuandong Tian, Beidi Chen, Song
                    Han, and Mike Lewis. 2023.       Efficient stream-
                    ing language models with attention sinks. CoRR,
                    abs/2309.17453.
                 WenhanXiong,JingyuLiu,IgorMolybog,HejiaZhang,
                    Prajjwal Bhargava, Rui Hou, Louis Martin, Rashi
                    Rungta, Karthik Abinav Sankararaman, Barlas Oguz,
                    MadianKhabsa,HanFang,YasharMehdad,Sharan
                    Narang, Kshitiz Malik, Angela Fan, Shruti Bhosale,
                    Sergey Edunov, Mike Lewis, Sinong Wang, and Hao
                    Ma.2023. Effective long-context scaling of founda-
                    tion models. CoRR, abs/2309.16039.
                                                                    13625
﻿                       A DetailsofShortLLMexperiments
                       A.1      Theoretical calculation for O.O.D issues
                       According to the analysis in Section 6.1, we can
                       calculate the reliable dimensions for each model
                       as:
                                                                L
                                         Split% = log             pretrain                (6)
                                                         10000      2π
                         The theoretical calculation results are shown in
                                           Lpretrain    RoPEDim         Split %   Split Dim
                         LLaMA-2              4096         128           0.70       90.05
                         ShearedLLaMA         4096         128           0.70       90.05
                         TinyLLaMA            2048         64            0.63       40.21
                         Vicuna               2048         128           0.63       80.42
                       Table 7: Theoretical calculation of the reliable extrapo-
                       lation dimension.
                       Table 7.
                       A.2      ShortLLMTraining
                       In order to obtain the ShortLLM of suitable length,
                       we use the position interpolation (Chen et al.,
                       2023b) method reversely. Given a position index                                                   Para.    L                 L         α
                       min the original RoPE, we use the new index                                                                  pretrain         short      short
                       α         ∗mtoreplace it as shown in Table 8. We                              LLaMA-2              7B         4096            128         32
                         short                                                                       ShearedLLaMA        1.3B        4096            128         32
                       sample the CodeParrot-train dataset and filter the                            TinyLLaMA           1.1B        2048            128         16
                       data length less than L                  .  We set the global                 Vicuna               7B         2048            128         16
                                                         short
                       batch size to 64 and fine-tune the models for 1000                          Table 8: Model Statistics for ShortLLM experiments.
                       steps.
                       A.3      ShortLLMPerformances
                       After training, we apply our HiRoPE to these Short-
                       LLMmodels. Figure 6 shows the experiment re-
                       sults of the ShortLLM. We can observe that for all
                       models, Our HiRoPE can maintain good stability
                       as the length of the input code increases. Even if
                       the baseline ReRoPE method gradually becomes
                       unstable under some experimental settings (such
                       as on Short-TinyLLaMA), our method can resist
                       these performance declines.
                                                                                            13626
﻿            Figure 6: Performance of ShortLLMs on CodeParrot dataset. The training length is set to 128.
                             13627
