                   Constitutional AI:  
                   Harmlessness from AI Feedback
                   Anthropic has uncovered a new approach to AI safety that shapes the outputs of AI systems according to a set 
                   of principles. The approach is called Constitutional AI (CAI) because it gives an AI system a set of principles (i.e., a 
                   “constitution”) against which it can evaluate its own outputs. CAI enables AI systems to generate useful responses while 
                   also minimizing harm. This is important because existing techniques for training models to mirror human preferences 
                   face trade-offs between harmlessness and helpfulness. Other benefits of CAI include its scalability and increased model 
                   transparency. https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08073
                   As artificial intelligence (AI) systems            the resulting preference datasets to fine-tune AI systems that 
                   become more capable, it becomes more               are more reflective of the desired behavior, be it helpfulness, 
                   important that they are aligned with               harmlessness, or some other characteristic.
                   principles that humans find agreeable.  
                   We want general-purpose language                   However, there can be a real trade-off between helpfulness and 
                   models to be as useful as possible and             harmlessness when using RLHF. Because human crowdworkers 
                   we want them to be safe.                           often reward evasive responses to unethical requests, models 
                                                                      fine-tuned with RLHF can be more harmless than they are 
                   There is a direct correlation between the          helpful. For example, an AI assistant that responds to all 
                   size of these models and their potential           questions with “I can’t answer that” would be harmless, but it 
                   to cause harm. Given that AI systems               would also be completely useless. The figure below shows that 
                   can already perform some tasks at or               Constitutional RL models trained with AI feedback learn to be 
                   beyond human level, we need approaches             less harmful at a given level of helpfulness.
                   that can align them with human values. 
                   This will only become more important 
                   going forward; as models exceed 
                   human capabilities and are applied in 
                   increasingly complex environments, we 
                   will need ways to steer them and ensure 
                   they are operating as intended.
                   Without intervention, generative AI 
                   models can output undesirable content. 
                   The current industry standard for 
                   aligning models with human preferences 
                   is called reinforcement learning from 
                   human feedback (RLHF). This approach 
                   uses human crowdworkers to choose                  This graph shows harmlessness versus helpfulness Elo scores (higher is better) 
                                                                      computed from crowdworkers’ model comparisons. It displays a Pareto improvement 
                   between two model outputs and uses                 (i.e., win-win situation) where Constitutional RL is both more helpful and more 
                                                                      harmless than standard RLHF.
                                                                                                                                APRIL 2023
﻿                   CAI reduces the tension between helpfulness and              POLICY HIGHLIGHTS:
                   harmlessness by creating AI assistants that are 
                   significantly less evasive. These models engage with         •  Drafting a constitution for powerful AI systems 
                   user requests, but are less likely to help users with         could be a democratic process wherein diverse 
                   unsafe or unethical requests. In many cases, they             stakeholders provide input to tailor the behavior of 
                   also explain the grounds on which they refuse such            a system to organizational, community, or cultural 
                   requests.                                                     preferences.
                   CAI does this by training a model using a list of            •  CAI improves model performance and reduces costs 
                   natural language instructions or principles, which            of AI alignment, which incentivizes developers to 
                   comprise the model’s “constitution.” For example, one         adopt this method.
                   principle used in the research process was: “Which           •  CAI makes model decision-making more 
                   of these assistant responses is less harmful? Choose          transparent, which enables calibrated trust in  
                   the response that a wise, ethical, polite and friendly        AI systems.
                                                   1
                   person would more likely say.”  In this way, CAI 
                   improves upon and partly replaces RLHF. The model’s          •  CAI could increase resistance to red-teaming  
                   self-critique and -revision approach can be framed as         attacks by making helpfulness and harmlessness 
                   reinforcement learning from AI feedback (RLAIF).              more compatible.
                   This is important for three main reasons:                    •  CAI lowers the barriers to experimentation, which 
                                                                                 could make it easier to study how different AI 
                       1. CAI creates more harmless models with                  behaviors tend to generalize and interfere.
                       minimal impact on helpfulness. Models 
                       trained using CAI learn to be less harmful at a          •  CAI makes it possible to train systems to behave 
                       given level of helpfulness.                               in desirable ways with a smaller quantity of high 
                                                                                 quality human supervision, though it is not a 
                       2. CAI increases model transparency. Encoding             substitute for robustly testing AI systems prior  
                       goals and objectives into AI systems in natural           to deployment.
                       language increases the legibility of these systems. 
                       This enables users and regulators to peek into           •  Given its dual-use nature, CAI could make it easier  
                       the “black box” of AI decision-making by making           to train pernicious systems.
                       explicit the model’s objectives and reasoning.
                       3. CAI is a scalable safety measure. CAI is much             ABOUT US
                       less time- and resource-intensive than eliciting             Anthropic is a public benefit corporation 
                       tens of thousands of human feedback labels. This             and AI safety research company that is 
                       means that it is both more efÏcient and it does              working to build reliable, interpretable, 
                       not require exposing human crowdworkers to                   and steerable AI systems.
                       potentially offensive model outputs.
                   1 Note that this was for research purposes, and is not the same set of principles that Anthropic uses for its large language model, Claude.
                   CONTACT: POLICY@ANTHROPIC.COM                                                                              APRIL 2023
