                                          COMMONSENSEQA:AQuestionAnsweringChallengeTargeting
                                                                                            CommonsenseKnowledge
                                                                 ∗∗,1,2                                              ∗,1                                            2                                              1,2
                                     AlonTalmor                                  Jonathan Herzig                                  Nicholas Lourie                              Jonathan Berant
                                                                            1School of Computer Science, Tel-Aviv University
                                                                                     2Allen Institute for Artiﬁcial Intelligence
                                       {alontalmor@mail,jonathan.herzig@cs,joberant@cs}.tau.ac.il,
                                                                                                nicholasl@allenai.org
                                                                   Abstract                                                        a) Sample ConceptNet for speciﬁc subgraphs
                                                                                                                                         pebble            AtLocation                                        waterfall
                                      Whenansweringaquestion,peopleoftendraw
                                      upon their rich world knowledge in addi-                                                           stream          AtLocation                        AtLocation
                                      tion to the particular context.                        Recent work                                                                      river         AtLocation        bridge
                                                                                                                                          bank          AtLocation                          AtLocation
                                      has focused primarily on answering questions
                                      given some relevant document or context,                                                                           AtLocation
                                      and required very little general background.                                                       canyon                                                                valley
                                      To investigate question answering with prior                                                    …
                                      knowledge, we present COMMONSENSEQA:                                                         b) Crowd source corresponding natural language questions 
                                                                                                                                       and two additional distractors
                                      a challenging new dataset for commonsense                                                   Where on a river can you hold a cup upright to catch water on a sunny day?
                                      questionanswering. Tocapturecommonsense                                                     ✔‍‍‍‍ waterfall,   ✘ bridge,   ✘ valley,   ✘pebble, ✘mountain
                                      beyond associations, we extract from CON-                                                   Where can I stand on a river to see water falling without getting wet? 
                                      CEPTNET (Speer et al., 2017) multiple target                                                                ✔
                                      concepts that have the same semantic relation                                               ✘waterfall,         bridge,   ✘ valley,    ✘stream, ✘bottom
                                      to a single source concept.                        Crowd-workers                            I’m crossing the river, my feet are wet but my body is dry, where am I? 
                                                                                                                                  ✘waterfall,   ✘ bridge,   ✔ valley, ✘ bank, ✘ island
                                      are asked to author multiple-choice questions
                                      that mention the source concept and discrim-                                                Figure 1: (a) A source concept (‘river’) and three tar-
                                      inate in turn between each of the target con-                                               get concepts (dashed) are sampled from CONCEPT-
                                      cepts. This encourages workers to create ques-                                              NET(b)Crowd-workersgeneratethreequestions, each
                                      tions with complex semantics that often re-                                                 having one of the target concepts for its answer (3),
                                      quirepriorknowledge. Wecreate12,247ques-                                                    while the other two targets are not (7). Then, for each
                                      tions through this procedure and demonstrate                                                question, workers choose an additional distractor from
                                      the difﬁculty of our task with a large number                                               CONCEPTNET (in italics), and author one themselves
                                      of strong baselines. Our best baseline is based                                             (in bold).
                                      on BERT-large (Devlin et al., 2018) and ob-
                                      tains 56% accuracy, well below human perfor-
                                      mance, which is 89%.
                                                                                                                                      WorkonQuestion Answering (QA) has mostly
                               1      Introduction                                                                                focusedonansweringfactoidquestions,wherethe
                               When humans answer questions, they capitalize                                                      answer can be found in a given context with lit-
                               on their common sense and background knowl-                                                        tle need for commonsense knowledge (Hermann
                               edge about spatial relations, causes and effects,                                                  et al., 2015; Rajpurkar et al., 2016; Nguyen et al.,
                               scientiﬁc facts and social conventions.                                       For in-              2016; Joshi et al., 2017). Small benchmarks such
                               stance, given the question “Where was Simon                                                        as the Winograd Scheme Challenge (Levesque,
                               when he heard the lawn mower?”, one can infer                                                      2011) and COPA (Roemmele et al., 2011), tar-
                               that the lawn mower is close to Simon, and that                                                    geted common sense more directly, but have been
                               it is probably outdoors and situated at street level.                                              difﬁcult to collect at scale.
                               This type of knowledge seems trivial for humans,                                                       Recently, efforts have been invested in devel-
                               but is still out of the reach of current natural lan-                                              oping large-scale datasets for commonsense rea-
                               guage understanding (NLU) systems.                                                                 soning. In SWAG (Zellers et al., 2018b), given
                                                                                                                                  a textual description of an event, a probable sub-
                                      ∗ Theauthors contributed equally                                                            sequent event needs to be inferred. However, it
                                                                                                                         4149
                                                                                      Proceedings of NAACL-HLT 2019, pages 4149–4158
                                                                                                                             c
                                                   Minneapolis, Minnesota, June 2 - June 7, 2019. 2019 Association for Computational Linguistics
﻿                 has been quickly realized that models trained on        sion (RC) models that utilize web snippets ex-
                 large amounts of unlabeled data (Devlin et al.,         tracted from Google search on top of the ques-
                 2018) capture well this type of information and         tion itself. We ﬁnd that ﬁne-tuning BERT-LARGE
                 performance on SWAG is already at human level.          (Devlin et al., 2018) on COMMONSENSEQA ob-
                 VCR (Zellers et al., 2018a) is another very re-         tains the best performance, reaching an accuracy
                 cent attempt that focuses on the visual aspects of      of 55.9%. This is substantially lower than human
                 common sense. Such new attempts highlight the           performance, which is 88.9%.
                 breadth of commonsense phenomena, and make it             Tosummarize, our contributions are:
                 evident that research on common sense has only            1. A new QA dataset centered around common
                 scratched the surface.    Thus, there is need for            sense, containing 12,247 examples.
                 datasets and models that will further our under-          2. A new method for generating commonsense
                 standing of what is captured by current NLU mod-             questions at scale from CONCEPTNET.
                 els, and what are the main lacunae.                       3. An empirical evaluation of state-of-the-art
                    In this work, we present COMMONSENSEQA,                   NLUmodelsonCOMMONSENSEQA,show-
                 a new dataset focusing on commonsense ques-                  ingthathumanssubstantiallyoutperformcur-
                 tion answering, based on knowledge encoded in                rent models.
                  CONCEPTNET(Speeretal., 2017). We propose a             The dataset can be downloaded from www.
                 method for generating commonsense questions at          tau-nlp.org/commonsenseqa. The code
                 scale by asking crowd workers to author questions       for all our baselines is available at github.
                 that describe the relation between concepts from        com/jonathanherzig/commonsenseqa.
                  CONCEPTNET (Figure 1). A crowd worker ob-
                 serves a source concept (‘River’ in Figure 1) and       2   Related Work
                 three target concepts (‘Waterfall’, ‘Bridge’, ‘Val-     Machine common sense, or the knowledge of and
                 ley’) that are all related by the same CONCEPT-         ability to reason about an open ended world, has
                  NET relation (AtLocation). The worker then             long been acknowledged as a critical component
                 authors three questions, one per target concept,        for natural language understanding. Early work
                 such that only that particular target concept is the    sought programs that could reason about an envi-
                 answer, while the other two distractor concepts are     ronment in natural language (McCarthy, 1959), or
                 not. This primes the workers to add commonsense         leverage a world-model for deeper language un-
                 knowledge to the question, that separates the tar-      derstanding (Winograd, 1972). Many common-
                 get concept from the distractors. Finally, for each     sense representations and inference procedures
                 question, the worker chooses one additional dis-        have been explored (McCarthy and Hayes, 1969;
                 tractor from CONCEPTNET, and authors another            Kowalski and Sergot, 1986) and large-scale com-
                 distractor manually. Thus, in total, ﬁve candidate      monsense knowledge-bases have been developed
                 answers accompany each question.                        (Lenat, 1995; Speer et al., 2017). However, evalu-
                    Because questions are generated freely by            ating the degree of common sense possessed by a
                 workers, they often require background knowl-           machine remains difﬁcult.
                 edge that is trivial to humans but is seldom explic-      One important benchmark,          the  Winograd
                 itly reported on the webduetoreportingbias(Gor-         Schema Challenge (Levesque, 2011), asks mod-
                 don and Van Durme, 2013). Thus, questions in            els to correctly solve paired instances of coref-
                  COMMONSENSEQAhaveadifferent nature com-                erence resolution. While the Winograd Schema
                 pared to prior QA benchmarks, where questions           Challenge remains a tough dataset, the difﬁculty
                 are authored given an input text.                       of generating examples has led to only a small
                    Using our method, we collected 12,247 com-           available collection of 150 examples. The Choice
                 monsense questions. We present an analysis that         ofPlausibleAlternatives(COPA)isasimilarlyim-
                 illustrates the uniqueness of the gathered ques-        portant but small dataset consisting of 500 devel-
                 tions compared to prior work, and the types of          opment and 500 test questions (Roemmele et al.,
                 commonsense skills that are required for tackling       2011). Each question asks which of two alterna-
                 it. We extensively evaluate models on COMMON-           tives best reﬂects a cause or effect relation to the
                  SENSEQA, experimenting with pre-trained mod-           premise. For both datasets, scalability is an issue
                 els, ﬁne-tuned models, and reading comprehen-           whenevaluating modern modeling approaches.
                                                                    4150
﻿                                           Withtherecentadoptionofcrowdsourcing,sev-                                                                                Crowdworkersauthor questions                              Crowdworkersadd distractors
                                     eral larger datasets have emerged, focusing on pre-                                                                        Dust in house? (attic, yard, street)                     Dust in house? (attic, yard, street, bed, desert)
                                                                                                                                                                Find glass outside? (bar, fork, car)                     Find glass outside? (bar, fork, car, sand, wine)
                                     dicting relations between situations or events in                                                                          Makes you happy? (laugh, sad, fall)                      Makes you happy? (laugh, sad, fall, blue, feel)
                                     natural language. JHU Ordinal Commonsense In-
                                     ference requests a label from 1-5 for the plau-                                                                            Extract subgraphs from ConceptNet                             Crowdworkersfilter questions by quality
                                     sibility that one situation entails another (Zhang                                                                          dust        attic      yard       street                 Dust in house? (attic, yard, …)         → 1.0
                                     et al., 2017). The Story Cloze Test (also referred to                                                                       glass       bar        fork        car                   Find glass outside? (bar, fork, ...)    → 0.2  X
                                                                                                                                                                                                                          Makes you happy? (laugh, sad, ...) → 0.8
                                     as ROC Stories) pits ground-truth endings to sto-                                                                          happy       laugh       sad         fall
                                     ries against implausible false ones (Mostafazadeh                                                                         Filter edges from ConceptNet with rules                       Collect relevant snippets via search engine
                                     et al., 2016). Interpolating these approaches, Sit-
                                     uations with Adversarial Generations (SWAG),                                                                                            X                                                     Dust in house? (attic, yard, …)
                                     asks models to choose the correct description of                                                                                                 X                                            Makes you happy? (laugh, sad, ...)
                                     what happens next after an initial event (Zellers                                                                       Figure 2:                 COMMONSENSEQA generation process.
                                     et al., 2018b). LM-based techniques achieve very                                                                        The input is CONCEPTNET knowledge base, and the
                                     high performance on the Story Cloze Test and                                                                            output is a set of multiple-choice questions with corre-
                                     SWAGbyﬁne-tuningapre-trainedLMonthetar-                                                                                 sponding relevant context (snippets).
                                     get task (Radford et al., 2018; Devlin et al., 2018).
                                           Investigations of commonsense datasets, and of
                                     natural language datasets more generally, have re-                                                                                  each with one source concept and three tar-
                                     vealed the difﬁculty in creating benchmarks that                                                                                    get concepts.
                                     measure the understanding of a program rather                                                                                2. We ask crowdsourcing workers to author
                                     than its ability to take advantage of distributional                                                                                three questions per subgraph (one per target
                                     biases, and to model the annotation process (Gu-                                                                                    concept),toaddtwoadditionaldistractorsper
                                     rurangan et al., 2018; Poliak et al., 2018). Annota-                                                                                question, and to verify questions’ quality.
                                     tion artifacts in the Story Cloze Test, for example,                                                                         3. We add textual context to each question by
                                     allow models to achieve high performance while                                                                                      querying a search engine and retrieving web
                                     only looking at the proposed endings and ignor-                                                                                     snippets.
                                     ing the stories (Schwartz et al., 2017; Cai et al.,
                                     2017). Thus, the development of benchmarks for                                                                          The entire data generation process is summarized
                                     commonsenseremainsadifﬁcult challenge.                                                                                  inFigure2. Wenowelaborateoneachofthesteps:
                                           Researchers have also investigated question an-                                                                   Extraction from CONCEPTNET CONCEPT-
                                     sweringthatutilizescommonsense. Scienceques-                                                                             NETisagraphknowledge-base G ⊆ C ×R×C,
                                     tions often require common sense, and have re-                                                                          wherethenodesC representnaturallanguagecon-
                                     cently received attention (Clark et al., 2018; Mi-                                                                      cepts, and edges R represent commonsense re-
                                     haylov et al., 2018; Ostermann et al., 2018); how-                                                                      lations.              Triplets (c ,r,c ) carry commonsense
                                     ever, they also need specialized scientiﬁc knowl-                                                                                                                      1           2
                                     edge. In contrast to these efforts, our work stud-                                                                      knowledge such as ‘(gambler, CapableOf, lose
                                     ies common sense without requiring additional                                                                           money)’.                    CONCEPTNET contains 32 million
                                     information.                      SQUABU created a small hand-                                                          triplets. To select a subset of triplets for crowd-
                                     curated test of common sense and science ques-                                                                          sourcing we take the following steps:
                                     tions (Davis, 2016), which are difﬁcult for current                                                                          1. We ﬁlter triplets with general relations (e.g.,
                                     techniques to solve. In this work, we create simi-                                                                                  RelatedTo) or relations that are already
                                     larly well-crafted questions but at a larger scale.                                                                                 well-explored in NLP (e.g., IsA). In total we
                                                                                                                                                                         use 22 relations.
                                     3        Dataset Generation                                                                                                  2. Weﬁlter triplets where one of the concepts is
                                                                                                                                                                         morethanfour words or not in English.
                                     Our goal is to develop a method for generating                                                                               3. We ﬁlter triplets where the edit distance be-
                                     questions that can be easily answered by humans                                                                                     tween c1 and c2 is too low.
                                     withoutcontext,andrequirecommonsenseknowl-                                                                              This results in a set of 236,208 triplets (q,r,a),
                                     edge. We generate multiple-choice questions in a                                                                        where we call the ﬁrst concept the question con-
                                     process that comprises the following steps.                                                                             cept and the second concept the answer concept.
                                          1. We extract subgraphs from CONCEPTNET,                                                                                 We aim to generate questions that contain the
                                                                                                                                                    4151
﻿                  question concept and where the answer is the an-             Measurement                            Value
                  swer concept. To create multiple-choice questions            # CONCEPTNETdistinct question nodes    2,254
                                                                               # CONCEPTNETdistinct answer nodes     12,094
                  we need to choose distractors for each question.             # CONCEPTNETdistinct nodes            12,107
                  Sampling distractors at random from CONCEPT-                 # CONCEPTNETdistinct relation lables    22
                  NETisabadsolution, as such distractors are easy              average question length (tokens)       13.41
                                                                               long questions (more than 20 tokens)  10.3%
                  to eliminate using simple surface clues.                     average answer length (tokens)          1.5
                     To remedy this, we propose to create ques-                # answers with more than 1 token       44%
                  tion sets:    for each question concept q and                # of distinct words in questions      14,754
                                                                               # of distinct words in answers         4,911
                  relation  r we group three different triplets
                  {(q,r,a1),(q,r,a2),(q,r,a3)} (see Figure 1).                 Table 1: Key statistics for COMMONSENSEQA
                  This generates three answer concepts that are se-
                  mantically similar and have a similar relation to        correct answer and four distractors.
                  the question concept q. This primes crowd work-
                  ers to formulate questions that require background       Verifying questions quality      Wetrain a disjoint
                  knowledge about the concepts in order to answer          groupofworkerstoverifythegeneratedquestions.
                  the question.                                            Veriﬁers annotate a question as unanswerable, or
                     The above procedure generates approximately           choose the right answer. Each question is veri-
                  130,000 triplets (43,000 question sets), for which       ﬁedby2workers,andonlyquestionsveriﬁedbyat
                  wecanpotentially generate questions.                     least one worker that answered correctly are used.
                  Crowdsourcing questions         We used Amazon           This processes ﬁlters out 15% of the questions.
                  Mechanical Turk (AMT) workers to generate and            Adding textual context        To examine whether
                  validate commonsense questions.                          web text is useful for answering commonsense
                     AMTworkers saw, for every question set, the           questions, we add textual information to each
                  question concept and three answer concepts. They         question in the following way: We issue a web
                  were asked to formulate three questions, where           query to Google search for every question and
                  all questions contain the question concept. Each         candidate answer, concatenating the answer to the
                  question should have as an answer one of the an-         question, e.g., ‘What does a parent tell their child
                  swer concepts, but not the other two. To discour-        to do after they’ve played with a lot of toys? +
                  age workers from providing simple surface clues          “clean room”’. We take the ﬁrst 100 result snip-
                  for the answer, they were instructed to avoid us-        pets for each of the ﬁve answer candidates, yield-
                  ing words that have a strong relation to the answer      ing a context of 500 snippets per question. Using
                  concept, for example, not to use the word ‘open’         this context, we can investigate the performance
                  whentheansweris‘door’.                                   of reading comprehension (RC) models on COM-
                     Formulating questions for our task is non-            MONSENSEQA.
                  trivial. Thus, we only accept annotators for which          Overall, we generated 12,247 ﬁnal examples,
                  at least 75% of the questions they formulate pass        from a total of 16,242 that were formulated. The
                  the veriﬁcation process described below.                 total cost per question is $0.33. Table 1 describes
                  Adding additional distractors         To make the        the key statistics of COMMONSENSEQA.
                  task more difﬁcult, we ask crowd-workers to add          4   Dataset Analysis
                  two additional incorrect answers to each formu-
                  lated question. One distractor is selected from a        CONCEPTNET concepts and relations             COM-
                  set of answer concepts with the same relation to         MONSENSEQA builds on CONCEPTNET, which
                  the question concept in CONCEPTNET (Figure 1,            contains concepts such as dog, house, or row
                  in red). The second distractor is formulated man-        boat, connected by relations such as Causes,
                  ually by the workers themselves (Figure 1, in pur-       CapableOf, or Antonym.             The top-5 ques-
                  ple). Workers were encouraged to formulate a dis-        tion concepts in COMMONSENSEQA are‘Person’
                  tractor that would seem plausible or related to the      (3.1%),‘People’(2.0%),‘Human’(0.7%),‘Water’
                  question but easy for humans to dismiss as incor-        (0.5%) and ‘Cat’ (0.5%). In addition, we present
                  rect. In total, each formulated question is accom-       the main relations along with the percentage of
                  panied with ﬁve candidate answers, including one         questions generated from them in Table 2. It’s
                                                                      4152
﻿                              Relation                  Formulatedquestion example                                                                                                                 %
                              AtLocation                WherewouldInotwantafox? A.henhouse,B.england,C.mountains,D....                                                                           47.3
                              Causes                    Whatisthe hopeful result of going to see a play? A. being entertained, B. meet, C. sit, D. ...                                           17.3
                              CapableOf                 Whywouldapersonputﬂowersinaroomwithdirtygymsocks? A.smellgood,B.manycolors,C.continuetogrow,D....                                         9.4
                              Antonym                   Someonewhohadaverybadﬂightmightbegivenatripinthistomakeupforit? A.ﬁrstclass,B.reputable, C. propitious , D. ...                           8.5
                              HasSubevent               Howdoesapersonbegintoattractanother person for reproducing? A. kiss, B. genetic mutation, C. have sex , D. ...                            3.6
                              HasPrerequisite IfIamtiltingadrinktowardmyface,whatshouldIdobeforetheliquidspillsover? A.openmouth,B.eatﬁrst,C.useglass,D....                                       3.3
                              CausesDesire              Whatdoparentsencouragekids to do when they experience boredom? A. read book, B. sleep, C. travel , D. ...                                 2.1
                              Desires                   Whatdoallhumanswanttoexperienceintheir own home? A. feel comfortable, B. work hard, C. fall in love , D. ...                              1.7
                              PartOf                    Whatwouldsomeoneweartoprotectthemselves from a cannon? A. body armor, B. tank, C. hat , D. ...                                            1.6
                              HasProperty               Whatisareasontopayyourtelevision bill? A. legal, B. obsolete, C. entertaining , D. ...                                                    1.2
                            Table 2: Top CONCEPTNET relations in COMMONSENSEQA,alongwiththeirfrequencyinthedataandanexam-
                            ple question. The ﬁrst answer (A) is the correct answer
                                                                                                                       Category           Deﬁnition                                                %
                                                                                                                       Spatial            Concept A appears near Concept B                         41
                                                                                                                       Cause & Effect     Concept A causes Concept B                               23
                                                                                                                       Hasparts           Concept A contains Concept B as one of its parts         23
                                                                                                                       Is member of       Concept A belongs to the larger class of Concept B       17
                                                                                                                       Purpose            Concept A is the purpose of Concept B                    18
                                                                                                                       Social             It is a social convention that Concept A                 15
                                                                                                                                          correlates with Concept B
                                                                                                                       Activity           Concept A is an activity performed in the context         8
                                                                                                                                          of Concept B
                                                                                                                       Deﬁnition          Concept A is a deﬁnition of Concept B                     6
                                                                                                                       Preconditions      Concept A must hold true in order for Concept B to        3
                                                                                                                                          take place
                                                                                                                     Table 3: Skills and their frequency in the sampled data.
                                                                                                                     Aseachexamplecanbeannotatedwithmultipleskills,
                            Figure 3: Examples of manually-annotated questions,                                      the total frequency does not sum to 100%.
                            with the required skills needed to arrive at the answers
                            (red circles). Skills are labeled edges, and concepts are
                            nodes.                                                                                   swer questions in COMMONSENSEQA, we ran-
                                                                                                                     domly sampled 100 examples from the develop-
                                                                                                                     ment set and performed the following analysis.
                            worth noting that since question formulators were                                            For each question, we explicitly annotated the
                            not shown the CONCEPTNET relation, they often                                            types of commonsense skills that a human uses
                            asked questions that probe other relationships be-                                       to answer the question. We allow multiple com-
                            tween the concepts. For example, the question                                            monsense skills per questions, with an average of
                            “What do audiences clap for?” was generated                                              1.75 skills per question. Figure 3 provides three
                            from the AtLocation relation, but focuses on                                             example annotations. Each annotation contains a
                            social conventions instead.                                                              node for the answer concept, and other nodes for
                                                                                                                     concepts that appear in the question or latent con-
                            Question formulation                        Question           formulators               cepts. Labeled edges describe the commonsense
                            were instructed to create questions with high                                            skill that relates the two nodes. We deﬁned com-
                            language variation. 122 formulators contributed                                          monsense skills based on the analysis of LoBue
                            to question generation.                      However, 10 workers                         and Yates (2011), with slight modiﬁcations to ac-
                            formulated more than 85% of the questions.                                               commodate the phenomena in our data. Table 3
                                Weanalyzedthedistribution of ﬁrst and second                                         presents the skill categories we used, their deﬁni-
                            words in the formulated questions along with ex-                                         tion and their frequency in the analyzed examples.
                            amplequestions. Figure4presentsthebreakdown.
                            Interestingly, only 44% of the ﬁrst words are WH-                                        5     Baseline Models
                            words. In about 5% of the questions, formulators                                         Our goal is to collect a dataset of commonsense
                            used ﬁrst names to create a context story, and in                                        questions that are easy for humans, but hard for
                            7%theyusedtheword“if”topresentahypothet-                                                 current NLU models. To evaluate this, we experi-
                            ical question. This suggests high variability in the                                     mentwithmultiple baselines. Table 4 summarizes
                            question language.                                                                       the various baseline types and characterizes them
                            Commonsense Skills                       To analyze the types of                         based on (a) whether training is done on COM-
                            commonsense knowledge needed to correctly an-                                            MONSENSEQA or the model is fully pre-trained,
                                                                                                             4153
﻿                                                                                                    heI
                                                                                                      f
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      t
                                                                                                    d h
                                                                                                    o e
                                                                                                    i r
                                                                                                    nge
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                    ? a
                                                                                                      r
                                                                                                      e
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      p
                                                                                                      e
                                                                                                      o
                                                                                                      p
                                                                                                      l
                                                                                                      e
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      w
                                                                                                      a
                                                                                                      t
                                                                                                      c
                                                                                                      h
                                                                                                      i
                                                                                                      n
                                                                                                      g
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      a
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      p
                                                                                                      r
                                                                                                      i
                                                                                                      e
                                                                                                      st
                                                                                                      ,
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      w
                                                                                                      h
                                                                                                      a
                                                                                                      t
                                                                                                       
                                                                                                      i
                                                                                                      s 
                                                                                The		13%
                         Figure 4: Distribution of the ﬁrst and second words in questions. The inner part displays words and their frequency
                         and the outer part provides example questions.
                                              Model           Training   Context                          rephrase“Whatisusuallynexttoadoor?”andthe
                                              VECSIM             7          7                             candidate answer “wall” to “Wall is usually next
                                              LM1B               7          7
                                              QABILINEAR         3          7                             to a door”. For questions that do not start with
                                              QACOMPARE          3          7
                                              ESIM               3          7                             the above preﬁxes, we concatenate the answer as
                                              GPT                3          7                             in LM1B-CONCAT. In both variations we return
                                              BERT               3          7
                                              BIDAF++            3         3                              the answer with highest LM probability.
                         Table 4: Baseline models along with their character-                             c QABILINEARThismodel,propsedbyYuetal.
                         istics. Training states whether the model was trained                            (2014) for QA, scores an answer a with a bilinear
                                                                                                                                                             i
                         on COMMONSENSEQA, or was only trained a differ-                                                     >
                                                                                                          model: qWa , where the question q and answers
                         entdataset. Context states whetherthemodelusesextra                                                 i
                                                                                                          a are the average pre-trained word embeddings
                         context as input.                                                                  i
                                                                                                          and W is a learned parameter matrix. A softmax
                                                                                                          layer over the candidate answers is used to train
                         and (b) whether context (web snippets) is used.                                  the model with cross-entropy loss.
                         Wenowelaborateonthedifferent baselines.                                          d QACOMPAREThismodelissimilartoanNLI
                         a VECSIMAmodelthatchoosestheanswerwith                                           model from Liu et al. (2016). The model repre-
                         highestcosinesimilaritytothequestion,wherethe                                    sents the interaction between the question q and a
                                                                                                          candidate answer a as: h = relu([q;a ;qa ;q−
                         question and answers are represented by an aver-                                                             i                            i         i
                                                                                                          a ]W +b ), where ’;’ denotes concatenation and
                         age of pre-trained word embeddings.                                                i     1      1
                         b LM1B Inspired by Trinh and Le (2018), we                                       is element-wise product. Then, the model pre-
                         employ a large language model (LM) from Joze-                                    dicts an answer score using a feed forward layer:
                                                                                                          hW +b . Average pre-trained embeddings and
                         fowicz et al. (2016), which was pre-trained on                                         2       2
                         the One Billion Words Benchmark (Chelba et al.,                                  softmax are used to train the model.
                         2013). We use this model in two variations. In                                   e ESIM We use ESIM, a strong NLI model
                         the ﬁrst (LM1B-CONCAT), we simply concate-                                       (Chen et al., 2016).                Similar to Zellers et al.
                         nate each answer to the question. In the second                                  (2018b), we change the output layer size to the
                         (LM1B-REP),weﬁrstclusterquestionsaccording                                       number of candidate answers, and apply softmax
                         to their ﬁrst two words. Then, we recognize ﬁve                                  to train with cross-entropy loss.
                         high-frequency preﬁxes that cover 35% of the de-                                 f BIDAF++ A state-of-the-art RC model, that
                         velopmentset(e.g.,“whatis”). Werephraseques-                                     usestheretrievedGooglewebsnippets(Section3)
                         tions that ﬁt into one of these preﬁxes as a declar-                             as context. We augment BIDAF (Seo et al., 2016)
                         ative sentence that contains the answer. E.g., we                                with a self-attention layer and ELMo representa-
                                                                                                   4154
﻿                   tions (Peters et al., 2018; Huang et al., 2018). To          networks that memorize might fail in such a sce-
                   adapttothemultiple-choicesetting, wechoosethe                nario. Since the random split is harder, we con-
                   answer with highest model probability.                       sider it the primary split of COMMONSENSEQA.
                   g GENERATIVE            PRE-TRAINED            TRANS-           Weevaluate all models on the test set using ac-
                   FORMER (GPT) Radford et al. (2018) proposed                  curacy (proportion of examples for which predic-
                   a method for adapting pre-trained LMs to perform             tion is correct), and tune hyper-parameters for all
                   a wide range of tasks. We applied their model to             trained models on the development set. To under-
                   COMMONSENSEQA by encoding each question                      stand the difﬁculty of the task, we add a SANITY
                   and its candidate answers as a series of delimiter-          mode, where we replace the hard distractors (that
                   separated sequences. For example, the question               share a relation with the question concept and one
                   “If you needed a lamp to do your work, where                 formulated by a worker) with random CONCEPT-
                   would you put it?”, and the candidate answer                 NET distractors. We expect a reasonable baseline
                   “bedroom” would become “[start] If ... ?                     to perform much better in this mode.
                   [sep] bedroom [end]”.              The hidden repre-            For pre-trained word embeddings we consider
                   sentations over each [end] token are converted               300dGloVeembeddings(Penningtonetal.,2014)
                   to logits by a linear transformation and passed              and 300d Numberbatch CONCEPTNET node em-
                   through a softmax to produce ﬁnal probabilities              beddings (Speer et al., 2017), which are kept ﬁxed
                   for the answers. We used the same pre-trained LM             at training time.    We also combine ESIM with
                   and hyper-parameters for ﬁne-tuning as Radford               1024d ELMo contextual representations, which
                   et al. (2018) on ROC Stories, except with a batch            are also ﬁxed during training.
                   size of 10.                                                  HumanEvaluation Totesthumanaccuracy,we
                   h BERTSimilarly to the GPT, BERT ﬁne-tunes                   created a separate task for which we did not use a
                   a language model and currently holds state-of-the-           qualiﬁcation test, nor used AMT master workers.
                   art across a broad range of tasks (Devlin et al.,            We sampled 100 random questions and for each
                   2018).     BERT uses a masked language mod-                  question gathered answers from ﬁve workers that
                   eling objective, which predicts missing words                werenotinvolvedinquestiongeneration. Humans
                   masked from unlabeled text. To apply BERT to                 obtain 88.9% accuracy, taking a majority vote for
                   COMMONSENSEQA, we linearize each question-                   each question.
                   answer pair into a delimiter-separated sequence
                   (i.e., “[CLS] If ... ? [SEP] bedroom [SEP]”)                 Results     Table 5 presents test set results for all
                   then ﬁne-tune the pre-trained weights from un-               models and setups.
                                            1
                   cased BERT-LARGE. Similarly to the GPT, the                     The best baselines are BERT-LARGE and GPT
                   hiddenrepresentationsovereach[CLS]tokenare                   with an accuracy of 55.9% and 45.5%, respec-
                   run through a softmax layer to create the predic-            tively, on the random split (63.6% and 55.5%, re-
                   tions. We used the same hyper-parameters as De-              spectively, on the question concept split). This is
                   vlin et al. (2018) for SWAG.                                 well below human accuracy, demonstrating that
                   6    Experiments                                             the benchmark is much easier for humans. Nev-
                                                                                ertheless, this result is much higher than random
                   Experimental Setup          We split the data into a         (20%), showing the ability of language models to
                   training/development/test set with an 80/10/10               store large amounts of information related to com-
                   split.  We perform two types of splits: (a) ran-             monsense knowledge.
                   dom split – where questions are split uniformly                 The top part of Table 5 describes untrained
                   at random, and (b) question concept split – where            models. We observe that performance is higher
                   each of the three sets have disjoint question con-           than random, but still quite low. The middle part
                   cepts. We empirically ﬁnd (see below) that a ran-            describes models that were trained on COMMON-
                   dom split is harder for models that learn from               SENSEQA,whereBERT-LARGEobtainsbestper-
                   COMMONSENSEQA, because the same question                     formance, as mentioned above.           ESIM models
                   concept appears in the training set and develop-             follow BERT-LARGE and GPT, and obtain much
                   ment/test set with different answer concepts, and            lower performance. We note that ELMo represen-
                      1The original weights and code released by Google may     tations did not improve performance compared to
                   be found here: https://github.com/google-research/bert       GloVeembeddings,possiblybecausewewereun-
                                                                           4155
﻿                                                                                                  Randomsplit          Question concept split
                                                        Model                                 Accuracy     SANITY Accuracy           SANITY
                                                         VECSIM+NUMBERBATCH                      29.1        54.0         30.3         54.9
                                                         LM1B-REP                                26.1        39.6         26.0         39.1
                                                         LM1B-CONCAT                             25.3        37.4         25.3         35.2
                                                         VECSIM+GLOVE                            22.3        26.8         20.8         27.1
                                                         BERT-LARGE                              55.9        92.3         63.6         93.2
                                                         GPT                                     45.5        87.2         55.5         88.9
                                                         ESIM+ELMO                               34.1        76.9         37.9         77.8
                                                         ESIM+GLOVE                              32.8        79.1         40.4         78.2
                                                         QABILINEAR+GLOVE                        31.5        74.8         34.2         71.8
                                                         ESIM+NUMBERBATCH                        30.1        74.6         31.2         75.1
                                                         QABILINEAR+NUMBERBATCH                  28.8        73.3         32.0         71.6
                                                         QACOMPARE+GLOVE                         25.7        69.2         34.1         71.3
                                                         QACOMPARE+NUMBERBATCH                   20.4        60.6         25.2         66.8
                                                         BIDAF++                                 32.0        71.0         38.4         72.0
                                                         HUMAN                                   88.9
                                                                        Table 5: Test set accuracy for all models.
                          Category       Formulatedquestion example                                                Correct answer     Distractor            Accuracy     %
                          Surface        If someone laughs after surprising them they have a good sense of what?   humor              laughter              77.7         35%
                          clues          Howmightaautomobilegetoffafreeway?                                        exit ramp          driveway
                          Negation /     Wherewouldyoustoreapillowcasethat is not in use?                          drawer             bedroom               42.8         7%
                          Antonym        Wheremightthestapler be if I cannot ﬁnd it?                               desk drawer        desktop
                          Factoid        Howmanyhoursareinaday?                                                    twenty four        week                  38.4         13%
                          knowledge      Whatgeographic area is a lizard likely to be?                             west texas         ball stopped
                          Bad            Whereis a well used toy car likely to be found?                           child’s room       ownhome               35.4         31%
                          granularity    Wheremayyoubeifyou’rebuyingporkchopsatacornershop?                        iowa               town
                          Conjunction    Whatcanyouusetostoreabookwhiletraveling?                                  suitcase           library of congress   23.8         23%
                                         Onahotdaywhatcanyoudotoenjoysomethingcoolandsweet?                        eat ice cream      fresh cake
                        Table 6: BERT-LARGE baseline analysis. For each category we provide two examples, the correct answer, one
                        distractor, model accuracy and frequency in the dataset. The predicted answer is in bold.
                        able to improve performance by back-propagating                               erage accuracy of the model for each category.
                        into the representations themselves (as we do in                                  Wefound that the model does well (77.7% ac-
                        BERT-LARGE and GPT). The bottom part shows                                    curacy) on examples where surface clues hint to
                        results for BIDAF++ that uses web snippets as                                 the correct answer. Examples that involve nega-
                        context. We observe that using snippets does not                              tion or understanding antonyms have lower accu-
                        lead to high performance, hinting that they do not                            racy (42.8%), similarly to examples that require
                        carry a lot of useful information.                                            factoid knowledge (38.4%). Accuracy is partic-
                            Performance on the random split is ﬁve points                             ularly low in questions where the correct answer
                        lower than the question concept split on average                              has ﬁner granularity compared to one of the dis-
                        across all trained models.                We hypothesize that                 tractors (35.4%), and in cases where the correct
                        this is because having questions in the develop-                              answer needs to meet a conjunction of conditions,
                        ment/test set that share a question concept with the                          andthedistractormeetsonlyoneofthem(23.8%).
                        training set, but have a different answer, creates
                        difﬁculty for networks that memorize the relation                             Learning Curves                To extrapolate how current
                        between a question concept and an answer.                                     models might perform with more data, we evalu-
                            Lastly, all SANITY models that were trained                               ated BERT-large on the development set, training
                        on COMMONSENSEQAachieveveryhighperfor-                                        with varying amounts of data. The resulting learn-
                        mance(92%for BERT-LARGE),showingthat se-                                      ingcurvesareplottedinﬁgure5. Foreachtraining
                        lecting difﬁcult distractors is crucial.                                      set size, hyper-parameters were identical to sec-
                                                                                                      tion 5, except the number of epochs was varied to
                        Baseline analysis              To understand the perfor-                      keep the number of mini-batches during training
                        mance of BERT-LARGE, we analyzed 100 ex-                                      constant. To deal with learning instabilities, each
                        amples from the development set (Table 6). We                                 data point is the best of 3 runs. We observe that
                        labeled examples with categories (possibly more                               the accuracy of BERT-LARGE is expected to be
                        than one per example) and then computed the av-                               roughly 75% assuming 100k examples, still sub-
                                                                                                4156
﻿                                                                            benchmark for measuring progress in statistical lan-
                                                                            guage modeling. arXiv preprint arXiv:1312.3005.
                                                                         Qian Chen, Xiaodan Zhu, Zhenhua Ling, Si Wei,
                                                                            Hui Jiang, and Diana Inkpen. 2016.      Enhanced
                                                                            lstm for natural language inference. arXiv preprint
                                                                            arXiv:1609.06038.
                                                                         Peter Clark, Isaac Cowhey, Oren Etzioni, Tushar Khot,
                                                                            Ashish Sabharwal, Carissa Schoenick, and Oyvind
                                                                            Tafjord. 2018. Think you have solved question an-
                                                                            swering? try arc, the ai2 reasoning challenge.
                                                                         Ernest Davis. 2016. How to write science questions
                  Figure 5: Development accuracy for BERT-LARGE             that are easy for people and hard for computers. AI
                                                                            magazine, 37(1):13–22.
                  trained with varying amounts of data.
                                                                         J. Devlin, M. Chang, K. Lee, and K. Toutanova. 2018.
                                                                            Bert: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers
                                                                            for language understanding. arXiv.
                  stantially lower than human performance.
                                                                         JonathanGordonandBenjaminVanDurme.2013. Re-
                  7   Conclusion                                            porting bias and knowledgeacquisition. In Proceed-
                                                                            ingsofthe2013WorkshoponAutomatedKnowledge
                  We present COMMONSENSEQA, a new QA                        Base Construction, AKBC ’13, pages 25–30, New
                  dataset that contains 12,247 examples and aims to         York, NY, USA. ACM.
                  test commonsense knowledge. We describe a pro-         Suchin Gururangan, Swabha Swayamdipta, Omer
                  cess for generating difﬁcult questions at scale us-       Levy, Roy Schwartz, Samuel R Bowman, and
                  ing CONCEPTNET, perform a detailed analysis of            Noah A Smith. 2018.       Annotation artifacts in
                  the dataset, which elucidates the unique properties       natural language inference data.   arXiv preprint
                  ofourdataset,andextensivelyevaluateonastrong              arXiv:1803.02324.
                  suite of baselines. We ﬁnd that the best model is      Karl Moritz Hermann, Tomas Kocisky, Edward
                  a pre-trained LM tuned for our task and obtains           Grefenstette, Lasse Espeholt, Will Kay, Mustafa Su-
                  55.9% accuracy, dozens of points lower than hu-           leyman, and Phil Blunsom. 2015.     Teaching ma-
                                                                            chinestoreadandcomprehend. InAdvancesinNeu-
                  man accuracy. We hope that this dataset facili-           ral Information Processing Systems, pages 1693–
                  tates future work in incorporating commonsense            1701.
                  knowledge into NLU systems.                            Hsin-Yuan Huang, Eunsol Choi, and Wen-tau Yih.
                  Acknowledgments                                           2018. Flowqa: Grasping ﬂow in history for con-
                                                                            versational machine comprehension. arXiv preprint
                  Wethank the anonymous reviewers for their con-            arXiv:1810.06683.
                  structive feedback. This work was completed in         M.Joshi, E. Choi, D. Weld, and L. Zettlemoyer. 2017.
                  partial fulﬁllment for the PhD degree of Jonathan         TriviaQA: A large scale distantly supervised chal-
                  Herzig, which was also supported by a Google              lenge dataset for reading comprehension. In Associ-
                  PhD fellowship. This research was partially sup-          ation for Computational Linguistics (ACL).
                  ported by The Israel Science Foundation grant          Rafal Jozefowicz, Oriol Vinyals, Mike Schuster, Noam
                  942/16, The Blavatnik Computer Science Re-                Shazeer, and Yonghui Wu. 2016.          Exploring
                  search Fund and The Yandex Initiative for Ma-             the limits of language modeling.   arXiv preprint
                  chine Learning.                                           arXiv:1602.02410.
                                                                         RKowalski and M Sergot. 1986. A logic-based calcu-
                                                                            lus of events. New Gen. Comput., 4(1):67–95.
                  References                                             Douglas B. Lenat. 1995. Cyc: A large-scale invest-
                  Zheng Cai, Lifu Tu, and Kevin Gimpel. 2017. Pay at-       ment in knowledge infrastructure. Commun. ACM,
                    tention to the ending: Strong neural baselines for the  38:32–38.
                    roc story cloze task. In ACL.
                                                                         Hector J. Levesque. 2011. The winograd schema chal-
                  C. Chelba, T. Mikolov, M. Schuster, Q. Ge, T. Brants,     lenge. In AAAI Spring Symposium: Logical Formal-
                    P. Koehn, and T. Robinson. 2013. One billion word       izations of Commonsense Reasoning.
                                                                     4157
﻿                    Yang Liu, Chengjie Sun, Lei Lin, and Xiaolong Wang.            P. Rajpurkar, J. Zhang, K. Lopyrev, and P. Liang. 2016.
                       2016.   Learning natural language inference using              Squad: 100,000+questionsformachinecomprehen-
                       bidirectional lstm model and inner-attention. arXiv            sion of text. In Empirical Methods in Natural Lan-
                       preprint arXiv:1605.09090.                                     guage Processing (EMNLP).
                    Peter LoBue and Alexander Yates. 2011.           Types of      M.Roemmele,C.Bejan,andA.Gordon.2011. Choice
                       common-sense knowledge needed for recognizing                  of plausible alternatives: An evaluation of common-
                       textual entailment. In Proceedings of the 49th An-             sense causal reasoning. In AAAI Spring Symposium
                       nual Meeting of the Association for Computational              on Logical Formalizations of Commonsense Rea-
                       Linguistics: Human Language Technologies: short                soning.
                       papers-Volume 2, pages 329–334. Association for             Roy Schwartz, Maarten Sap, Ioannis Konstas, Leila
                       Computational Linguistics.                                     Zilles, Yejin Choi, and Noah A. Smith. 2017. The
                    J. McCarthy. 1959. Programs with common sense. In                 effect of different writing tasks on linguistic style:
                       Proceedings of the Teddington Conference on the                Acasestudyoftherocstory cloze task. In CoNLL.
                       Mechanization of Thought Processes.                         M. Seo, A. Kembhavi, A. Farhadi, and H. Hajishirzi.
                    John McCarthy and Patrick J. Hayes. 1969.           Some          2016. Bidirectional attention ﬂow for machine com-
                       philosophical problems from the standpoint of ar-              prehension. arXiv.
                       tiﬁcial intelligence.  In B. Meltzer and D. Michie,         Robert Speer, Joshua Chin, and Catherine Havasi.
                       editors, Machine Intelligence 4, pages 463–502. Ed-            2017. Conceptnet 5.5: An open multilingual graph
                       inburgh University Press. Reprinted in McC90.                  of general knowledge. In AAAI, pages 4444–4451.
                    Todor Mihaylov, Peter Clark, Tushar Khot, and Ashish           O. Tange. 2011.         Gnu parallel - the command-
                       Sabharwal. 2018. Can a suit of armor conduct elec-             line power tool.    ;login: The USENIX Magazine,
                       tricity? a new dataset for open book question an-              36(1):42–47.
                       swering.
                    N. Mostafazadeh, N. Chambers, X. He, D. Parikh,                Trieu H Trinh and Quoc V Le. 2018.              A simple
                       D. Batra, L. Vanderwende, P. Kohli, and J. Allen.              method for commonsense reasoning. arXiv preprint
                       2016.   A corpus and cloze evaluation for deeper               arXiv:1806.02847.
                       understanding of commonsense stories.         In North      T. Winograd. 1972. Understanding Natural Language.
                       American Association for Computational Linguis-                AcademicPress.
                       tics (NAACL).
                                                                                   Lei Yu, Karl Moritz Hermann, Phil Blunsom, and
                    T. Nguyen, M. Rosenberg, X. Song, J. Gao, S. Tiwary,              Stephen Pulman. 2014. Deep learning for answer
                       R. Majumder, and L. Deng. 2016. MS MARCO:                      sentence selection. arXiv preprint arXiv:1412.1632.
                       Ahumangeneratedmachinereadingcomprehension
                       dataset.  In Workshop on Cognitive Computing at             Rowan Zellers, Yonatan Bisk, Ali Farhadi, and Yejin
                       NIPS.                                                          Choi. 2018a.       From recognition to cognition:
                                                                                      Visual commonsense reasoning.           arXiv preprint
                    SimonOstermann,AshutoshModi,MichaelRoth,Ste-                      arXiv:1811.10830.
                       fan Thater, and Manfred Pinkal. 2018. Mcscript: A
                       novel dataset for assessing machine comprehension           RowanZellers,YonatanBisk,RoySchwartz,andYejin
                       using script knowledge. CoRR, abs/1803.05223.                  Choi. 2018b.      Swag: A large-scale adversarial
                                                                                      dataset for grounded commonsenseinference. arXiv
                    J. Pennington, R. Socher, and C. D. Manning. 2014.                preprint arXiv:1808.05326.
                       Glove: Global vectors for word representation. In           Sheng Zhang, Rachel Rudinger, Kevin Duh, and Ben-
                       Empirical MethodsinNaturalLanguageProcessing                   jamin Van Durme. 2017. Ordinal common-sense in-
                       (EMNLP).                                                       ference. TACL, 5:379–395.
                    Matthew E. Peters, Mark Neumann, Mohit Iyyer, Matt
                       Gardner, Christopher Clark, Kenton Lee, and Luke
                       Zettlemoyer. 2018. Deep contextualized word rep-
                       resentations. In Proc. of NAACL.
                    Adam Poliak, Jason Naradowsky, Aparajita Haldar,
                       Rachel Rudinger, and Benjamin Van Durme. 2018.
                       Hypothesis only baselines in natural language infer-
                       ence. In Proc. of *SEM.
                    A. Radford, K. Narasimhan, T. Salimans, and
                       I. Sutskever. 2018. Improving language understand-
                       ing by generative pre-training.     Technical Report,
                       OpenAI.
                                                                              4158
