                                                 Alan D. Baddeley and Graham Hitch                                                                                                                     Working Memory                                                77
                    76
                    system consists of a limited capacity "work space" which can be di-                                                                      of this component               i~ exceeded,        then some of the general-purpose
                    vided between storage and control processing demands. The next                                                                           work space must be devoted to storage, with the result that less space
                    three sections comprise a tentative attempt to elaborate our view of                                                                     is available       for processing. We shall discuss this possibility in more
                    the working memory system by considering                                three    basic questions:                                        detail in the next section.
                    how work space is allocated, how the central processing system and                                                                           The final point concerns the factors which control the trade-off
                    the more peripheral             phonemic rehearsal system interact in the mem-                                                           between the amount of work space allocated to two competing tasks.
                    ory span task, and, finally, whether different                           modalities        each have                                     Results show that instructional emphasis is at least one determinant.
                    theiT own separate working memory system.                                                                                                In Experiment II, for example, Ss for whom the memory task was
                                                                                                                                                             emphasLzed showed a very much greater effect of a six-digit preload
                    A.     ALLOCATION OF WORK SPACE                                                                                                          on reasoning time than was shown by a second group who were in-
                                                                                                                                                             structed that both tasks were equally important.                            Evidence for a simi-
                       Our data suggest that a trade-off exists between                                the amount of                                         lar effect in free recall              learning       has been presented               by Murdock
                    storage required and the rate at which other processes can be earned                                                                     (1965). He showed that a concurrent card-sorting task interfered                                    with
                    out.    In Experiment             III,   for example,          Ss solved verbal reasoning                                                the long-term component of free recall and that the trade-off between
                    problems while either reciting a digit sequence, repeating the word                                                                      performance          on the two tasks was determined                           by the particular
                    the, or saying nothing.              It is assumed that reciting a digit sequence                                                        payoff specified in the instructions.
                    requires      more short-term            storage than either of the other two con-
                    ditions.     Reasoning times, which presumably reflect the rate at which                                                                 B.     THE ROLE OF 'I\'ORKING MEMORY IN THE MEl'vIORY SPAN
                    logical operations            are carried        out, were substantially               increased        in
                    this condition.         Furthermore, problems containing passive and nega-                                                                   We have suggested that the working memory system may contain
                    tive sentences were slowed down more than problems posed as active                                                                       both flexible work space and also a component that is dedicated to
                    and affirmative sentences. Since grammatically                               cotnplex       sentences                                    storage.     This view is illustrated                by the following suggested inter-
                    presumably require a greater number of processing operations than                                                                        pretation       of the role of working memory in the memory span task.
                    simple sentences, this result is consistent with the assumed trade-off                                                                   It is suggested that the memory span depends on both a phonemic
                    between storage-load and processing-rate.                                                                                                response buffer which is able to store a limited amount of speechlike
                       The effect of additional               memory load on free recall may be used                                                         material      in the appropriate            serial order and the flexible component
                    to make a similar point. Experiments on presentation rate and free                                                                       of working memory. The phonemic component is relatively passive
                    recall    suggest that "transfer"                to LTS proceeds at a limited rate.                                                      and makes few demands on the central processing space, provided
                    Since increasing memory load reduced transfer to LTS, it is arguable                                                                     its capacity is not exceeded. The more Hexible and executive com-
                    that this may result from a decrease in the rate at which the control                                                                    ponent of the system is responsible                       for setting        up the appropriate
                    processes necessary for transfer could be executed.                                                                                      phonemic         "rehearsal"         routines,      i.e.,   of loading         up the phonemic
                        However, although our evidence suggests some degree of trade-off                                                                     buffer and of retrieving information                     from the buffer when necessary.
                    between storage-load and processing-rate,                         it would probably be un-                                               Provided the memory load does not exceed the capacity of the pho-
                    wise to regard working memory as an entirely flexible system of                                                                          nemic buffer, little demand                    is placed upon the central executive,
                    which any part may be allocated                         either     to storage        or processing.                                      other than the routine recycling of the presumably                                    familiar       sub-
                    There are two reasons for this. In the first place, there may ulti-                                                                      routines      necessary for rehearsing                digits.    When the capacity of the
                    mately be no clear theoretical grounds for distinguishing                                  processing                                    phonemic buffer is exceeded. then the executive component of work·
                    and storage: they may always go together. Secondly, at the empirical                                                                     ing memory must devote more of its time to the problem of storage.
                    level, a number of results show that it is difficult to produce appre-                                                                   This probably involves both recoding in such a way as to reduce
                    ciable interference            with additio~l memory loads below the size of                                                             the length or complexity                  of the phonemic subroutine                     involved       in
                    the span. This may mean that a part of the system that may be used                                                                       rehearsal       and also devoting more attention                       to the problem of re-
                    for storage is not available for general processing. When the capacity                                                                   trieval.    It is, for example,           probably at this stage that retrieval                    rules
