                                  Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
                            Adrià PuigdomènechBadia*1 Bilal Piot*1 Steven Kapturowski*1 Pablo Sprechmann*1
                                                   Alex Vitvitskyi1 Daniel Guo1 Charles Blundell1
                                        Abstract
                    Atari games have been a long-standing bench-
                    markinthereinforcementlearning(RL)commu-
                    nity for the past decade. This benchmark was
                    proposed to test general competency of RL al-
                    gorithms. Previous work has achieved good av-
                    erage performance by doing outstandingly well
                    on many games of the set, but very poorly in
                    several of the most challenging games. We pro-
                    pose Agent57, the ﬁrst deep RL agent that out-
                    performs the standard human benchmark on all
                    57Atari games. To achieve this result, we train a
                    neural network which parameterizes a family of
                    policies ranging from very exploratory to purely             Figure 1. Number of games where algorithms are better than the
                    exploitative. We propose an adaptive mechanism               human benchmark throughout training for Agent57 and state-of-
                    to choose which policy to prioritize throughout              the-art baselines on the 57 Atari games.
                    the training process. Additionally, we utilize a
                    novelparameterizationofthearchitecturethatal-                Deep Q-Networks (DQN ; Mnih et al., 2015) was the ﬁrst
                    lows for more consistent and stable learning.                algorithm to achieve human-level control in a large num-
                                                                                 ber of the Atari 2600 games, measured by human nor-
                                                                                 malized scores (HNS). Subsequently, using HNS to assess
               1. Introduction                                                   performance on Atari games has become one of the most
               TheArcadeLearningEnvironment(ALE; Bellemareetal.,                 widely used benchmarks in deep reinforcement learning
               2013) was proposed as a platform for empirically assess-          (RL), despite the human baseline scores potentially under-
               ing agents designed for general competency across a wide          estimating human performance relative to what is possi-
               range of games. ALE offers an interface to a diverse set          ble (Toromanoff et al., 2019). Nonetheless, human bench-
               of Atari 2600 game environments designed to be engaging           mark performance remains an oracle for “reasonable per-
               and challenging for human players. As Bellemare et al.            formance” across the 57 Atari games. Despite all efforts,
               (2013) put it, the Atari 2600 games are well suited for eval-     nosingleRLalgorithmhasbeenabletoachieveover100%
               uating general competency in AI agents for three main rea-        HNS on all 57 Atari games with one set of hyperparam-
               sons: (i) varied enough to claim generality, (ii) each inter-     eters. Indeed, state of the art algorithms in model-based
               esting enough to be representative of settings that might be      RL,MuZero(Schrittwieser et al., 2019), and in model-free
               faced in practice, and (iii) each created by an independent       RL, R2D2 (Kapturowski et al., 2018) surpass 100% HNS
               party to be free of experimenter’s bias.                          on 51 and 52 games, respectively. While these algorithms
                                                                                 achieve well above average human-level performance on
               Agents are expected to perform well in as many games as           a large fraction of the games (e.g. achieving more than
               possible making minimal assumptions about the domain              1000% HNS), in the games they fail to do so, they often
               at hand and without the use of game-speciﬁc information.          fail to learn completely. These games showcase particu-
                                                                                 larly importantissuesthatageneralRLalgorithmshouldbe
                 *Equal contribution 1DeepMind. Correspondence to: Adrià         able to tackle. Firstly, long-term credit assignment: which
               Puigdomènech Badia <adriap@google.com>.                           decisions are most deserving of credit for the positive (or
               Proceedings of the 37th International Conference on Machine       negative) outcomes that follow? This problem is particu-
               Learning, Online, PMLR 119, 2020. Copyright 2020 by the au-       larly hard when rewards are delayed and credit needs to
               thor(s).                                                          be assigned over long sequences of actions, such as in the
﻿                                                  Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
               gamesofSkiing or Solaris. The game of Skiing is a canon-        R2D2achievestheoptimalscorewhileNGUperformssim-
               ical example due to its peculiar reward structure. The goal     ilar to a random policy. One shortcoming of NGU is that it
               of the game is to run downhill through all gates as fast as     collects the same amount of experience following each of
               possible. A penalty of ﬁve seconds is given for each missed     its policies, regardless of their contribution to the learning
               gate. The reward, given only at the end, is proportional to     progress. Some games require a signiﬁcantly different de-
               the time elapsed. Therefore long-term credit assignment         gree of exploration to others. Intuitively, one would want
               is needed to understand why an action taken early in the        to allocate the shared resources (both network capacity and
               game (e.g. missing a gate) has a negative impact in the         data collection) such that end performance is maximized.
               obtained reward. Secondly, exploration: efﬁcient explo-         WeproposeallowingNGUtoadaptitsexplorationstrategy
               ration can be critical to effective learning in RL. Games       over the course of an agent’s lifetime, enabling specializa-
               like Private Eye, Montezuma’s Revenge, Pitfall! or Venture      tion to the particular game it is learning. This is the ﬁrst
               are widely considered hard exploration games (Bellemare         signiﬁcant improvement we make to NGU to allow it to be
               et al., 2016; Ostrovski et al., 2017) as hundreds of actions    a more general agent.
               mayberequiredbeforeaﬁrstpositiverewardisseen. Inor-             Recent work on long-term credit assignment can be cate-
               der to succeed, the agents need to keep exploring the envi-     gorizedintoroughlytwotypes: ensuringthatgradientscor-
               ronment despite the apparent impossibility of ﬁnding pos-       rectly assign credit (Ke et al., 2017; Weber et al., 2019; For-
               itive rewards. These problems are particularly challenging      tunatoetal.,2019)andusingvaluesortargetstoensurecor-
               in large high dimensional state spaces where function ap-       rect credit is assigned (Arjona-Medina et al., 2019; Hung
               proximation is required.                                        et al., 2019; Liu et al., 2019; Harutyunyan et al., 2019; Fer-
               Exploration algorithms in deep RL generally fall into three     ret et al., 2020). NGU is also unable to cope with long-term
               categories:  randomized value functions (Osband et al.,         credit assignment problems such as Skiing or Solaris where
               2016; Fortunato et al., 2017; Salimans et al., 2017; Plap-      it fails to reach 100% HNS. Advances in credit assignment
               pert et al., 2017; Osband et al., 2018), unsupervised policy    in RL often involve a mixture of both approaches, as val-
               learning (Gregor et al., 2016; Achiam et al., 2018; Eysen-      ues and rewards form the loss whilst the ﬂow of gradients
               bach et al., 2018) and intrinsic motivation (Schmidhuber,       through a model directs learning.
               1991; Oudeyer et al., 2007; Barto, 2013; Bellemare et al.,      In this work, we propose tackling the long-term credit as-
               2016; Ostrovski et al., 2017; Fu et al., 2017; Tang et al.,     signment problem by improving the overall training sta-
               2017; Burda et al., 2018; Choi et al., 2018; Savinov et al.,    bility, dynamically adjusting the discount factor, and in-
               2018; Puigdomènech Badia et al., 2020). Other work com-         creasing the backprop through time window. These are
               bines handcrafted features, domain-speciﬁc knowledge or         relatively simple changes compared to the approaches pro-
               privileged pre-training to side-step the exploration prob-      posed in previous work, but we ﬁnd them to be effective.
               lem, sometimes only evaluating on a few Atari games (Ay-        Muchrecentworkhasexploredthisproblemofhowtody-
               tar et al., 2018; Ecoffet et al., 2019). Despite the encourag-  namically adjust hyperparameters of a deep RL agent, e.g.,
               ing results, no algorithm has been able to signiﬁcantly im-     approaches based upon evolution (Jaderberg et al., 2017),
               prove performance on challenging games without deterio-         gradients (Xu et al., 2018) or multi-armed bandits (Schaul
               rating performanceontheremaininggameswithoutrelying             et al., 2019). Inspired by Schaul et al. (2019), we propose
               on human demonstrations (Pohlen et al., 2018). Notably,         using a simple non-stationary multi-armed bandit (Garivier
               amongst all this work, intrinsic motivation, and in partic-     &Moulines, 2008) to directly control the exploration rate
               ular, Never Give Up (NGU; Puigdomènech Badia et al.,            and discount factor to maximize the episode return, and
               2020) has shown signiﬁcant recent promise in improving          then provide this information to the value network of the
               performance on hard exploration games. NGU achieves             agent as an input. Unlike Schaul et al. (2019), 1) it controls
               this by augmenting the reward signal with an internally         the exploration rate and discount factor (helping with long-
               generated intrinsic reward that is sensitive to novelty at two  termcredit assignment), and 2) the bandit controls a family
               levels: short-term novelty within an episode and long-term      of state-action value functions that back up the effects of
               novelty across episodes. It then learns a family of policies    exploration and longer discounts, rather than linearly tilt-
               for exploring and exploiting (sharing the same parameters),     ing a common value function by a ﬁxed functional form.
               with the end goal of obtaining the highest score under the
               exploitative policy. However, NGU is not the most gen-          In summary, our contributions are as follows:
               eral agent: much like R2D2 and MuZero are able to per-
               form strongly on all but few games, so too NGU suffers           1. A new parameterization of the state-action value func-
               in that it performs strongly on a smaller, different set of        tion that decomposes the contributions of the intrinsic
               games to agents such as MuZero and R2D2 (despite be-               and extrinsic rewards. As a result, we signiﬁcantly in-
               ing based on R2D2). For example, in the game Surround              creasethetrainingstabilityoveralargerangeofintrinsic
                                                                                  reward scales.
﻿                                                  Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
               2. A meta-controller: an adaptive mechanism to select            has its own associated discount factor γ (for background
                                                                                                                          j
                  whichofthepolicies (parameterized by exploration rate         and notations on Markov Decision Processes (MDP) see
                  and discount factors) to prioritize throughout the train-     App. A). Since the intrinsic reward is typically much more
                                                                                                                            N−1
                  ing process. This allows the agent to control the ex-         dense than the extrinsic reward, {(β ,γ )}       are chosen
                                                                                                                     j   j  j=0
                  ploration/exploitation trade-off by dedicating more re-       soastoallowforlongtermhorizons(highvaluesofγ )for
                                                                                                                                       j
                  sources to one or the other.                                  exploitative policies (small values of βj) and small term
                                                                                horizons (low values of γ ) for exploratory policies (high
               3. Finally, we demonstrate for the ﬁrst time performance                                    j
                  that is above the human baseline across all Atari 57          values of βj).
                  games. As part of these experiments, we also ﬁnd that         To learn the state-action value function Q∗ , NGU trains
                                                                                                                            rj
                  simply re-tuning the backprop through time window to          a recurrent neural network Q(x,a,j;θ), where j is a one-
                  be twice the previously published window for R2D2             hot vector indexing one of N implied MDPs (in particular
                  led to superior long-term credit assignment (e.g., in So-     (β ,γ )), x is the current observation, a is an action, and θ
                                                                                  j   j
                  laris) while still maintaining or improving overall per-      are the parameters of the network (including the recurrent
                  formance on the remaining games.                              state). In practice, NGU can be unstable and fail to learn
                                                                                                                   ∗
                                                                                anappropriateapproximationofQ         for all the state-action
                                                                                                                   rj
               These improvements to NGU collectively transform it into         value functions in the family, even in simple environments.
               the most general Atari 57 agent, enabling it to outperform       This is especially the case when the scale and sparseness
               the human baseline uniformly over all Atari 57 games.            of re and ri are both different, or when one reward is more
                                                                                    t      t
               Thus, we call this agent: Agent57.                               noisythantheother. Weconjecturethatlearningacommon
                                                                                state-action value function for a mix of rewards is difﬁcult
               2. Background: Never Give Up (NGU)                               whentherewardsareverydifferentinnature. Therefore, in
                                                                                Sec. 3.1, we propose an architectural modiﬁcation to tackle
               OurworkbuildsontopoftheNGUagent,whichcombines                    this issue.
               two ideas: ﬁrst, the curiosity-driven exploration, and sec-      Our agent is a deep distributed RL agent, in the lineage
               ond, distributed deep RL agents, in particular R2D2.             of R2D2 and NGU. As such, it decouples the data col-
               NGUcomputes an intrinsic reward in order to encourage            lection and the learning processes by having many actors
               exploration.   This reward is deﬁned by combining per-           feed data to a central prioritized replay buffer. A learner
               episode and life-long novelty.    The per-episode novelty,       can then sample training data from this buffer, as shown
               repisodic, rapidly vanishes over the course of an episode, and   in Fig. 2 (for implementation details and hyperparameters
                t                                                               refer to App. E). More precisely, the replay buffer con-
               it is computed by comparing observations to the contents
               of an episodic memory. The life-long novelty, αt, slowly
               vanishes throughout training, and it is computed by using a
               parametric model (in NGU and in this work Random Net-
               work Distillation (Burda et al., 2018) is used to this end).
               With this, the intrinsic reward ri is deﬁned as follows:
                                               t
                         ri = repisodic · min{max{α ,1},L},
                           t    t                     t
               where L = 5 is a chosen maximum reward scaling. This
               leverages the long-term novelty provided by αt, while
               repisodic continues to encourage the agent to explore within
                t
               an episode. For a detailed description of the computation
               of repisodic and α , see (Puigdomènech Badia et al., 2020)
                   t            t
               or App. I. At time t, NGU adds N different scales of the
               same intrinsic reward βjri (βj ∈ R+, j ∈ 0,...N − 1)
                                          t
               to the extrinsic reward provided by the environment, re, to      Figure 2. A schematic depiction of a distributed deep RL agent.
                                                                       t
               form N potential total rewards r      = re + β ri. Conse-
                                                 j,t     t     j t
               quently, NGU aims to learn the N different associated op-        tains sequences of transitions that are removed regularly
                                                    ∗
               timal state-action value functions Q   associated with each      in a FIFO-manner. These sequences come from actor pro-
                                                    rj
               reward function rj,t. The exploration rates βj are param-        cesses that interact with independent copies of the envi-
               eters that control the degree of exploration. Higher val-        ronment, and they are prioritized based on temporal dif-
               ues will encourage exploratory policies and smaller values       ferences errors (Kapturowski et al., 2018). The priorities
               will encourage exploitative policies. Additionally, for pur-     are initialized by the actors and updated by the learner with
                                                                         ∗
               poses of learning long-term credit assignment, each Q            the updated state-action value function Q(x,a,j;θ). Ac-
                                                                         rj
﻿                                                Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
              cording to those priorities, the learner samples sequences     ance associated with their corresponding reward, and we
              of transitions from the replay buffer to construct an RL       also allow for the associated optimizer state to be separated
              loss.  Then, it updates the parameters of the neural net-      for intrinsic and extrinsic state-action value functions.
              work Q(x,a,j;θ) by minimizing the RL loss to approxi-          Moreover, when a transformed Bellman operator (Pohlen
              mate the optimal state-action value function. Finally, each    et al., 2018) with function h is used (see App. A), we can
              actor shares the same network architecture as the learner      split the state-action value function in the following way:
              but with different weights. We refer as θ to the parameters
                                                      l
              of the l−th actor. The learner weights θ are sent to the ac-       Q(x,a,j;θ) =
              tor frequently, which allows it to update its own weights θ .                                                     
                                                                       l              −1             e         −1             i
              Each actor uses different values  , which are employed to         h h (Q(x,a,j;θ ))+βjh (Q(x,a,j;θ )) .
                                                l
              follow an  -greedy policy based on the current estimate of
                         l                                                   In App. B, we also show that the optimization of sepa-
              the state-action value function Q(x,a,j;θl). In particular,    rated transformed state-action value functions is equivalent
              at the beginning of each episode and in each actor, NGU        to the optimization of the original single transformed state-
              uniformly selects a pair (β ,γ ). We hypothesize that this
                                         j  j                                action value function. In practice, choosing a simple or
              processissub-optimalandproposetoimproveitinSec.3.2             transformed split does not seem to play an important role
              by introducing a meta-controller for each actor that adapts    in terms of performance (empirical evidence and an intu-
              the data collection process.                                   ition behind this result can be found in App. H.3). In our
                                                                             experiments, we choose an architecture with a simple split
              3. Improvements to NGU                                         which corresponds to h being the identity, but still use the
                                                                             transformed Retrace loss functions.
              3.1. State-Action Value Function Parameterization
              The proposed architectural improvement consists in split-      3.2. Adaptive Exploration over a Family of Policies
              ting the state-action value function in the following way:     The core idea of NGU is to jointly train a family of poli-
                   Q(x,a,j;θ) = Q(x,a,j;θe)+β Q(x,a,j;θi),                   cies with different degrees of exploratory behaviour using a
                                                     j                       single network architecture. In this way, training these ex-
              whereQ(x,a,j;θe)andQ(x,a,j;θi)aretheextrinsicand               ploratory policies plays the role of a set of auxiliary tasks
              intrinsic components of Q(x,a,j;θ) respectively. The sets      that can help train the shared architecture even in the ab-
              of weights θe and θi separately parameterize two neural        sence of extrinsic rewards. A major limitation of this ap-
              networks with identical architecture and θ = θi ∪ θe. Both     proach is that all policies are trained equally, regardless
              Q(x,a,j;θe) and Q(x,a,j;θi) are optimized separately           of their contribution to the learning progress. We propose
              with rewards re and ri respectively, but with the same tar-    to incorporate a meta-controller that can adaptively select
              get policy π(x) = argmaxa∈AQ(x,a,j;θ). More pre-               which policies to use both at training and evaluation time.
              cisely, to train the weights θe and θi, we use the same se-    This carries two important consequences. Firstly, by se-
              quenceoftransitionssampledfromthereplay,butwithtwo             lecting which policies to prioritize during training, we can
              different transformed Retrace loss functions (Munos et al.,    allocate more of the capacity of the network to better rep-
              2016). For Q(x,a,j;θe) we compute an extrinsic trans-          resent the state-action value function of the policies that
              formed Retrace loss on the sequence transitions with re-       are most relevant for the task at hand. Note that this is
              wards re and target policy π, whereas for Q(x,a,j;θi) we       likely to change throughout the training process, naturally
              compute an intrinsic transformed Retrace loss on the same      building a curriculum to facilitate training. As mentioned
              sequence of transitions but with rewards ri and target pol-    in Sec. 2, policies are represented by pairs of exploration
              icyπ. AreminderofhowtocomputeatransformedRetrace               rate and discount factor, (β ,γ ), which determine the dis-
                                                                                                        j  j
              loss on a sequence of transitions with rewards r and target    counted cumulative rewards to maximize. It is natural to
              policy π is provided in App. C.                                expect policies with higher βj and lower γj to make more
              In addition, in App. B, we show that this optimization of      progress early in training, while the opposite would be ex-
              separate state-action values is equivalent to the optimiza-    pected as training progresses. Secondly, this mechanism
              tion of the original single state-action value function with   also provides a natural way of choosing the best policy in
              reward re + β ri (under a simple gradient descent opti-        the family to use at evaluation time. Considering a wide
                             j                                               range of values of γ with β ≈ 0, provides a way of auto-
              mizer). Even though the theoretical objective being opti-                          j       j
              mizedisthesame,theparameterizationisdifferent: weuse           matically adjusting the discount factor on a per-task basis.
              two different neural networks to approximate each one of       This signiﬁcantly increases the generality of the approach.
              these state-action values (a schematic and detailed ﬁgures     Wepropose to implement the meta-controller using a non-
              of the architectures used can be found in App. F). By doing    stationary multi-arm bandit algorithm running indepen-
              this, we allow each network to adapt to the scale and vari-    dently on each actor. The reason for this choice, as op-
﻿                                                   Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
                                                                                 4. Experiments
                                                                                 Webeginthissectionbydescribingourexperimentalsetup.
                                                                                 Following NGU, Agent57 uses a family of coefﬁcients
                                                                                 {(β ,γ )}N−1 of size N = 32. The choice of discounts
                                                                                     j  j   j=0
                                                                                      N−1
                                                                                 {γ }      differs from that of NGU to allow for higher val-
                                                                                    j j=0
                                                                                 ues, ranging from 0.99 to 0.9999 (see App. G.1 for de-
                                                                                 tails). The meta-controller uses a window size of τ = 160
                                                                                 episodes and  = 0.5 for the actors and a window size of
               Figure 3. Capped human normalized score where we observe at       τ = 3600 episodes and  = 0.01. All the other hyper-
               whichpoint the agent surpasses the human benchmark on the last    parameters are identical to those of NGU, including the
               6 games.                                                          standard preprocessing of Atari frames. For a complete
                                                                                 description of the hyperparameters and preprocessing we
                                                                                 use, please see App. G.3. For all agents we run (that is,
               posedtoaglobalmeta-controller, is that each actor follows         all agents except MuZero where we report numbers pre-
               a different  -greedy policy which may alter the choice of        sented in Schrittwieser et al. (2019)), we employ a separate
                            l                                                    evaluator process to continuously record scores. We record
               the optimal arm. Each arm j from the N-arm bandit is              the undiscountedepisodereturnsaveragedover3seedsand
               linked to a policy in the family and corresponds to a pair        using a windowed mean over 50 episodes. For our best al-
               (β ,γ ). At the beginning of each episode, say, the k-
                 j   j                                                           gorithm, Agent57, we report the results averaged over 6
               th episode, the meta-controller chooses an arm Jk setting         seeds on all games to strengthen the signiﬁcance of the re-
               which policy will be executed. Note here that the arm J
                                                                           k     sults. On that average, we report the maximum over train-
               is a random variable. Then the l-th actor acts  -greedily
                                                                  l              ing as their ﬁnal score, as done in Fortunato et al. (2017);
               with respect to the corresponding state-action value func-        Puigdomènech Badia et al. (2020). Further details on our
               tion, Q(x,a,J ;θ ), for the whole episode. The undis-
                               k  l                                              evaluation setup are described in App. E.
               counted extrinsic episode returns, noted Re(Jk), are used
                                                            k                    In addition to using human normalized scores HNS =
               as a reward signal to train the multi-arm bandit algorithm
                                                                                  Agent  −Randomscore
               of the meta-controller.                                                score         , we report the capped human normal-
                                                                                 Human   −Random
                                                                                       score     score
               The reward signal Re(J ) is non-stationary, as the agent          ized scores, CHNS = max{min{HNS,1},0}. This mea-
                                     k   k                                       sure is a better descriptor for evaluating general perfor-
               changes throughout training. Thus, a classical bandit algo-       mance, as it puts an emphasis in the games that are below
               rithm such as Upper Conﬁdence Bound (UCB; Garivier &              the average human performance benchmark. Furthermore,
               Moulines, 2008) will not be able to adapt to the changes          and avoiding any issues that aggregated metrics may have,
               of the reward through time. Therefore, we employ a sim-           we also provide all the scores that all the ablations obtain
               pliﬁed sliding-window UCB with UCB-greedy exploration.           in all games we evaluate in App. H.1.
               Withprobability 1−UCB, this algorithm runs a slight mod-
               iﬁcation of classic UCB on a sliding window of size τ and         Westructure the rest of this section in the following way:
               selects a random arm with probability UCB (details of the        ﬁrstly, we show an overview of the results that Agent57
               algorithms are provided in App. D).                               achieves. Then we proceed to perform ablations on each
               Note that the beneﬁt of adjusting the discount factor             one of the improvements we propose for our model.
               through training and at evaluation could be applied even          4.1. Summary of the Results
               in the absence of intrinsic rewards. To show this, we pro-
               pose augmenting a variant of R2D2 with a meta-controller.         Tab. 1 shows a summary of the results we obtain on all 57
               In order to isolate the contribution of this change, we eval-     Atari games when compared to baselines. MuZero obtains
               uate a variant of R2D2 which uses the same RL loss as             the highest uncapped mean and median human normalized
               Agent57. Namely, a transformed Retrace loss as opposed            scores, but also the lowest capped scores. This is due to the
               to a transformed n-step loss as in the original paper. We re-     fact that MuZeroperformsremarkablywellinsomegames,
               fer to this variant as R2D2 (Retrace) throughout the paper.       such as Beam Rider, where it shows an uncapped score of
               Thereasonfor choosing this different loss is that it worked       27469%,butatthesametimecatastrophicallyfailstolearn
               better than the n-step loss for NGU, as described in Puig-        in games such as Venture, achieving a score that is on par
               domènech Badia et al. (2020). In all other aspects, R2D2          with a random policy. We see that the meta-controller im-
               (Retrace)isexactlythesamealgorithmasR2D2. Weincor-                provement successfully transfers to R2D2: the proposed
               porate the joint training of several policies parameterized       variant R2D2 (bandit) shows a mean, median, and CHNS
                       N−1
               by {γ }       to R2D2 (Retrace). We refer to this algorithm
                     j j=0                                                       that are much higher than R2D2 with the same Retrace
               as R2D2 (bandit).
﻿                                                                             Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
                       Table 1. Number of games above human, mean capped, mean and median human normalized scores for the 57 Atari games.
                                                                Statistics               Agent57        R2D2(bandit)          NGU          R2D2(Retrace)          R2D2         MuZero
                                                             Cappedmean                   100.00             96.93            95.07             94.20              94.33        89.92
                                                     Numberofgames>human                     57               54                51                52                52            51
                                                                  Mean                    4766.25          5461.66           3421.80           3518.36           4622.09       4998.51
                                                                 Median                   1933.49          2357.92           1359.78           1457.63           1935.86       2041.12
                                                            40th Percentile               1091.07          1298.80           610.44             817.77           1176.05       1172.90
                                                            30th Percentile               614.65            648.17           267.10             420.67            529.23        503.05
                                                            20th Percentile               324.78            303.61           226.43             267.25            215.31        171.39
                                                            10th Percentile               184.35            116.82           107.78             116.03            115.33        75.74
                                                             5th Percentile               116.67             93.25            64.10             48.32              50.27         0.03
                       loss. Finally, Agent57 achieves a median and mean that is
                       greater than NGU and R2D2, but also its CHNS is 100%.
                       This shows the generality of Agent57: not only it obtains
                       a strong mean and median, but also it is able to obtain
                       strong performance on the tail of games in which MuZero
                       and R2D2 catastrophically fail. This is more clearly ob-
                       served when looking at different percentiles: up to the
                       20thpercentile, Agent57 showsmuchgreaterperformance,
                       only slightly surpassed by R2D2 (bandit) when we exam-
                       ine higher percentiles. In Fig. 3 we report the performance
                       of Agent57 in isolation on the 57 games. We show the last
                       6 games (in terms of number of frames collected by the
                       agents) in which the algorithm surpasses the human perfor-
                       mance benchmark. As shown, the benchmark over games                                                 Figure 4. Performance progression on the 10-game challenging
                       is beaten in a long-tailed fashion, where Agent57 uses the                                          set obtained from incorporating each one of the improvements.
                       ﬁrst 5 billion frames to surpass the human benchmark on
                       51games. Afterthat, we ﬁnd hard exploration games, such
                       as Montezuma’s Revenge, Pitfall!, and Private Eye. Lastly,                                          equivalent to Agent57. We observe that each one of the
                       Agent57 surpasses the human benchmark on Skiing after                                               improvementsresults in an increment in ﬁnal performance.
                       78 billion frames. To be able to achieve such performance                                           Further, we see that each one of the improvements that is
                       on Skiing, Agent57 uses a high discount (as we show in                                              part of Agent57 is necessary in order to obtain the consis-
                       Sec. 4.4). This naturally leads to high variance in the re-                                         tent ﬁnal performance of 100% CHNS.
                       turns, which leads to needing more data in order to learn
                       to play the game. One thing to note is that, in the game                                            4.2. State-Action Value Function Parameterization
                       of Skiing, the human baseline is very competitive, with a
                       score of −4336.9, where −17098.1 is random and −3272                                                We begin by evaluating the inﬂuence of the state-action
                       is the optimal score one can achieve.                                                               value function parametrization on a minimalistic gridworld
                       In general, as performance in Atari keeps improving, it                                             environment, called “random coin”. It consists of an empty
                       seems natural to concentrate on the tail of the distribution,                                       room of size 15 × 15 where a coin and an agent are
                       i.e., pay attention to those games for which progress in the                                        randomly placed at the start of each episode. The agent
                       literature has been historically much slower than average.                                          can take four possible actions (up, down, left right) and
                       Wenowpresentresultsforasubsetof10gamesthatwecall                                                    episodes are at most 200 steps long. If the agent steps over
                       the challenging set. It consists of the six hard exploration                                        the coin, it receives a reward of 1 and the episode termi-
                       games as deﬁned in (Bellemare et al., 2016), plus games                                             nates. In Fig. 5 we see the results of NGU with and with-
                       that require long-term credit assignment. More concretely,                                          out the new parameterization of its state-action value func-
                       the games we use are: Beam Rider, Freeway, Montezuma’s                                              tions. We report performance after 150 million frames. We
                       Revenge, Pitfall!, Pong, Private Eye, Skiing, Solaris, Sur-                                         compare the extrinsic returns for the policies that are the
                                                                                                                           exploitative (β           = 0) and the most exploratory (with the
                       round, and Venture.                                                                                                        j
                                                                                                                           largest β        in the family).             Even for small values of the
                                                                                                                                         j
                       In Fig. 4 we can see the performance progression obtained                                           exploration rates (max β ), this setting induces very dif-
                                                                                                                                                               j    j
                       fromincorporating each one of the improvements we make                                              ferent exploratory and exploitative policies. Maximizing
                       on top of NGU. Such performance is reported on the se-                                              the discounted extrinsic returns is achieved by taking the
                       lection of 10 games mentioned above. In the notation of                                             shortest path towards the coin (obtaining an extrinsic re-
                       the legend, NGU + bandit + separate nets + long trace is                                            turn of one), whereas maximizing the augmented returns
﻿                                                    Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
                                                                                  Figure 6. Solaris learning curves with small and long backprop
                                                                                  through time window sizes for both R2D2 and Agent57.
                                                                                  round the opponent snake, receive a reward, and start from
               Figure 5. Extrinsic returns for the exploitative (β = 0) and most
                                                              0                   the initial state, or keep wandering around without captur-
               exploratory (β31 = β) on “random coin” for different values of     ing the opponent, and thus visiting new states in the world.
               the intrinsic reward weight, β. (Top) NGU(Bottom) NGU with
               Separate networks for intrinsic and extrinsic values.              4.3. Backprop Through Time Window Size
               is achieved by avoiding the coin and visiting all remaining        In this section we analyze the impact of having a backprop
               states (obtaining an extrinsic return of zero). In principle,      through time window size. More concretely, we analyze its
               NGUshould be able to learn these policies jointly. How-            impact on the base algorithm R2D2 to see its effect with-
               ever, we observe that the exploitative policy in NGU strug-        out NGUoranyoftheimprovementswepropose. Further,
               gles to solve the task as intrinsic motivation reward scale        we also analyze its effect on Agent57, to see if any of the
               increases. As we increase the scale of the intrinsic reward,       improvements on NGU overlap with this change. In both
               its value becomes muchgreaterthanthatoftheextrinsicre-             cases, we compare using backprop through time window
               ward. As a consequence, the conditional state-action value         sizes of 80 (default in R2D2) versus 160, higher values en-
               networkofNGUisrequiredtorepresentverydifferentval-                 able credit assignment further back.
               ues depending on the β we condition on. This implies that
                                        j                                         In aggregated terms over the challenging set, its effect
               the network is increasingly required to have more ﬂexible
               representations. Using separate networks dramatically in-          seems to be the same for both R2D2 and Agent57: us-
               creases its robustness to the intrinsic reward weight that is      ing a longer backprop through time window appears to be
               used. Note that this effect would not occur if the episode         initially slower, but results in better overall stability and
               did not terminate after collecting the coin. In such case,         slightly higher ﬁnal score.     A detailed comparison over
               exploratory and exploitative policies would be allowed to          those 10 games is shown in App. H.2. This effect can be
               be very similar: both could start by collecting the coin as        seen clearly in the game of Solaris, as observed in Fig. 6.
               quickly as possible. In Fig. 4 we can see that this improve-       This is also the game showing the largest improvement in
               mentalsotranslatestothechallengingset. NGUachievesa                terms of ﬁnal score. This is again general improvement, as
               muchloweraverageCHNSthanitsseparatenetworkcoun-                    it enhances performance on all the challenging set games.
               terpart. We also observe this phenomenon when we incor-            For further details we report the scores in App. H.1.
               porate the meta-controller. Agent57 suffers a drop of per-
               formance that is greater than 20% when the separate net-           4.4. Adaptive Exploration
               workimprovementisremoved.                                          In this section, we analyze the effect of using the meta-
               We can also see that it is a general improvement: it does          controller described in Sec. 3.1 in both the actors and the
               not show worse performance on any of the 10 games of               evaluator. To isolate the contribution of this improvement,
               the challenging set. More concretely, the largest improve-         we evaluate two settings: R2D2 and NGU with separate
               ment is seen in the case of Surround, where NGU obtains            networks, with and without meta-controller. Results are
               a score on par with a random policy, whereas with the new          shown in Fig. 7. Again, we observe that this is a general
               parametrization it reaches a score that is nearly optimal.         improvement in both comparisons. Firstly, we observe that
               ThisisbecauseSurroundisacasethatissimilartothe“ran-                there is a great value in this improvement on its own, en-
               dom coin” environment mentioned above: as the player               hancing the ﬁnal performance of R2D2 by close to 20%
               makes progress in the game, they have the choice to sur-           CHNS.Secondly,weobservethatthebeneﬁtonNGUwith
﻿                                                    Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
                                                                                  Figure 8. Best arm chosen by the evaluator of Agent57 over train-
               Figure 7. Performancecomparisonforadaptiveexplorationonthe         ing for different games.
               10-game challenging set.
               separate networks is more modest than for R2D2. This in-
               dicates that there is a slight overlap in the contributions of     ent skills that are required to be performant on such diverse
               the separate network parameterization and the use of the           set of games: exploration and exploitation and long-term
               meta-controller. The bandit algorithm can adaptively de-           credit assignment. To do that, we propose simple improve-
               crease the value of β when the difference in scale between         mentstoanexistingagent, Never Give Up, which has good
               intrinsic and extrinsic rewards is large. Using the meta-          performance on hard-exploration games, but in itself does
               controller allows to include very high discount values in          not have strong overall performance across all 57 games.
               the set {γj}N . Speciﬁcally, running R2D2 with a high              These improvements are i) using a different parameteri-
                            j=0
               discount factor, γ = 0.9999 surpasses the human baseline           zation of the state-action value function, ii) using a meta-
               in the game of Skiing. However, using that hyperparameter          controller to dynamically adapt the novelty preference and
               across the full set of games, renders the algorithm very un-       discount, and iii) the use of longer backprop-through time
               stable and damages its end performance. All the scores in          windowtolearn from using the Retrace algorithm.
               the challenging set for a ﬁxed high discount (γ = 0.9999)          Thismethodleveragesagreatamountofcomputationtoits
               variant of R2D2 are reported in App. H.1. When using a             advantage: similarly to NGU, it is able to scale well with
               meta-controller, the algorithm does not need to make this          increasing amounts of computation. This has also been the
               compromise: it can adapt it in a per-task manner.                  case with the many recent achievements in deep RL (Sil-
               Finally, the results and discussion above show why it is           ver et al., 2016; Andrychowicz et al., 2018; Vinyals et al.,
               beneﬁcial to use different values of β and γ on a per-task         2019). While this enables our method to achieve strong
               basis. At the same time, in Sec. 3 we hypothesize it would         performance, an interesting research direction is to pursue
               also be useful to vary those coefﬁcients throughout train-         ways in which to improve the data efﬁciency of this agent.
               ing. In Fig. 8 we can see the choice of (β , γ ) produc-           Additionally, this agent shows an average capped human
                                                              j   j
               ing highest returns on the meta-controller of the evaluator        normalized score of 100%. However, in our view this by
               acrosstrainingforseveralgames. Somegamesclearlyhave                nomeansmarkstheendofAtariresearch,notonlyinterms
               a preferred mode: on Skiing the high discount combination          of efﬁciency as above, but also in terms of general perfor-
               is quickly picked up when the agent starts to learn, and on        mance. We offer two views on this: ﬁrstly, analyzing the
               Heroahighβ andlowγ isgenerally preferred at all times.             performance among percentiles gives us new insights on
               On the other hand, some games have different preferred             howgeneral algorithms are. While Agent57 achieves great
               modes throughout training: on Gravitar, Crazy Climber,             results on the ﬁrst percentiles of the 57 games and holds
               Beam Rider, and Jamesbond, Agent57 initially chooses to            better mean and median performance than NGU or R2D2,
               focus on exploratory policies with low discount, and, as           as MuZero shows, it could still obtain much better average
               training progresses, the agent shifts into producing experi-       performance. Secondly,aspointedoutbyToromanoffetal.
               ence from higher discount and more exploitative policies.          (2019), all current algorithms are far from achieving opti-
                                                                                  malperformanceinsomegames. Tothatend,keyimprove-
               5. Conclusions                                                     ments to use might be enhancements in the representations
                                                                                  that Agent57 and NGU use for exploration, planning (as
               Wepresenttheﬁrstdeepreinforcementlearningagentwith                 suggested by the results achieved by MuZero) as well as
               performance above the human benchmark on all 57 Atari              better mechanisms for credit assignment (as highlighted by
               games. The agent is able to balance the learning of differ-        the results seen in Skiing).
﻿                                                    Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
               Acknowledgments                                                    Burda, Y., Edwards, H., Storkey, A., and Klimov, O. Ex-
               We thank Daan Wierstra, Koray Kavukcuoglu, Vlad                       ploration by random network distillation. arXiv preprint
               Mnih, Vali Irimia, Georg Ostrovski, Mohammad Ghesh-                   arXiv:1810.12894, 2018.
               laghi Azar, Rémi Munos, Bernardo Avila Pires, Florent              Choi, J., Guo, Y., Moczulski, M., Oh, J., Wu, N., Norouzi,
               Altché, Steph Hughes-Fitt, Rory Fitzpatrick, Andrea Ban-              M., and Lee, H. Contingency-aware exploration in re-
               ino, Meire Fortunato, Melissa Tan, Benigno Uria, Borja                inforcement learning. arXiv preprint arXiv:1811.01483,
               Ibarz, Andre Barreto, Diana Borsa, Simon Osindero, Tom                2018.
               Schaul,andmanyothercolleaguesatDeepMindforhelpful                  Ecoffet, A., Huizinga, J., Lehman, J., Stanley, K. O.,
               discussions and comments on the manuscript.                           and Clune, J. Go-explore: a new approach for hard-
               References                                                            exploration problems. arXiv preprint arXiv:1901.10995,
                                                                                     2019.
               Achiam, J., Edwards, H., Amodei, D., and Abbeel, P.                Eysenbach, B., Gupta, A., Ibarz, J., and Levine, S. Di-
                  Variational option discovery algorithms. arXiv preprint            versity is all you need: Learning skills without a reward
                  arXiv:1807.10299, 2018.                                            function. arXiv preprint arXiv:1802.06070, 2018.
               Andrychowicz,M.,Baker,B.,Chociej,M.,Jozefowicz,R.,                 Ferret, J., Marinier, R., Geist, M., and Pietquin, O. Self-
                  McGrew,B.,Pachocki,J.,Petron,A.,Plappert,M.,Pow-                   attentional credit assignment for transfer in reinforce-
                  ell, G., Ray, A., et al. Learning dexterous in-hand ma-            mentlearning. IJCAI, 2020.
                  nipulation. arXiv preprint arXiv:1808.00177, 2018.              Fortunato, M., Azar, M.G., Piot, B., Menick, J., Osband, I.,
               Arjona-Medina, J. A., Gillhofer, M., Widrich, M., Un-                 Graves, A., Mnih, V., Munos, R., Hassabis, D., Pietquin,
                  terthiner, T., Brandstetter, J., and Hochreiter, S. Rudder:        O., et al. Noisy networks for exploration. arXiv preprint
                  Return decomposition for delayed rewards. In Advances              arXiv:1706.10295, 2017.
                  in Neural Information Processing Systems, pp. 13544–            Fortunato, M., Tan, M., Faulkner, R., Hansen, S., Badia,
                  13555, 2019.                                                       A.P.,Buttimore,G.,Deck,C.,Leibo,J.Z.,andBlundell,
               Aytar, Y., Pfaff, T., Budden, D., Paine, T., Wang, Z., and            C. Generalization of reinforcement learners with work-
                  deFreitas, N. Playing hard exploration games by watch-             ing and episodic memory. In Advances in Neural Infor-
                  ing youtube. In Advances in Neural Information Pro-                mation Processing Systems, pp. 12448–12457, 2019.
                  cessing Systems, pp. 2930–2941, 2018.                           Fu, J., Co-Reyes, J., and Levine, S. Ex2: Exploration with
               Barreto, A., Dabney, W., Munos, R., Hunt, J. J., Schaul, T.,          exemplar models for deep reinforcement learning. In
                  van Hasselt, H. P., and Silver, D. Successor features for          Advances in neural information processing systems, pp.
                  transfer in reinforcement learning. In Advances in neural          2577–2587, 2017.
                  information processing systems, pp. 4055–4065, 2017.            Garivier, A. and Moulines, E. On upper-conﬁdence bound
                                                                                     policies for non-stationary bandit problems, 2008.
               Barto, A. G. Intrinsic motivation and reinforcement learn-         Gregor, K., Rezende, D. J., and Wierstra, D. Variational in-
                  ing. In Intrinsically motivated learning in natural and            trinsic control. arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.07507, 2016.
                  artiﬁcial systems, pp. 17–47. Springer, 2013.
               Bellemare, M., Srinivasan, S., Ostrovski, G., Schaul, T.,          Harutyunyan, A., Dabney, W., Mesnard, T., Azar, M. G.,
                  Saxton, D., and Munos, R. Unifying count-based explo-              Piot, B., Heess, N., van Hasselt, H. P., Wayne, G., Singh,
                  ration and intrinsic motivation. In Advances in Neural             S., Precup, D., et al. Hindsight credit assignment. In
                  Information Processing Systems, pp. 1471–1479, 2016.               Advances in neural information processing systems, pp.
                                                                                     12467–12476, 2019.
               Bellemare, M. G., Naddaf, Y., Veness, J., and Bowling, M.          Horgan, D., Quan, J., Budden, D., Barth-Maron, G.,
                  The arcade learning environment: An evaluation plat-               Hessel, M., Van Hasselt, H., and Silver, D.           Dis-
                  formforgeneralagents. JournalofArtiﬁcialIntelligence               tributed prioritized experience replay.    arXiv preprint
                  Research, 47:253–279, 06 2013.                                     arXiv:1803.00933, 2018.
               Blundell, C., Uria, B., Pritzel, A., Li, Y., Ruderman,             Hung, C.-C., Lillicrap, T., Abramson, J., Wu, Y., Mirza,
                  A., Leibo, J. Z., Rae, J., Wierstra, D., and Hass-                 M., Carnevale, F., Ahuja, A., and Wayne, G. Optimiz-
                  abis, D.   Model-free episodic control. arXiv preprint             ing agent behavior over long time scales by transporting
                  arXiv:1606.04460, 2016.                                            value. Nature communications, 10(1):1–12, 2019.
﻿                                                                   Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
                    Jaderberg, M., Dalibard, V., Osindero, S., Czarnecki,                                 Pohlen, T., Piot, B., Hester, T., Azar, M. G., Horgan, D.,
                       W. M., Donahue, J., Razavi, A., Vinyals, O., Green,                                    Budden, D., Barth-Maron, G., Van Hasselt, H., Quan, J.,
                                                                                                                  ˇ
                       T., Dunning, I., Simonyan, K., et al.                         Population               Vecerík, M., et al. Observe and look further: Achiev-
                       based training of neural networks.                      arXiv preprint                 ing consistent performance on atari.                     arXiv preprint
                       arXiv:1711.09846, 2017.                                                                arXiv:1805.11593, 2018.
                    Kapturowski, S., Ostrovski, G., Quan, J., Munos, R., and                              Pritzel, A., Uria, B., Srinivasan, S., Puigdomènech, A.,
                       Dabney, W. Recurrent experience replay in distributed                                  Vinyals, O., Hassabis, D., Wierstra, D., and Blundell,
                       reinforcement learning. In International Conference on                                 C. Neural episodic control. ICML, 2017.
                       Learning Representations, 2018.                                                    Puigdomènech Badia, A., Sprechmann, P., Vitvitskyi, A.,
                    Ke, N. R., Goyal, A., Bilaniuk, O., Binas, J., Charlin,                                   Guo, D., Piot, B., Kapturowski, S., Tieleman, O., Ar-
                       L., Pal, C., and Bengio, Y.                  Sparse attentive back-                    jovsky, M., Pritzel, A., Bolt, A., and Blundell, C. Never
                       tracking: Long-range credit assignment in recurrent net-                               give up: Learning directed exploration strategies.                        In
                       works. arXiv preprint arXiv:1711.02326, 2017.                                          International Conference on Learning Representations,
                                                                                                              2020.
                    Liu, Y., Luo, Y., Zhong, Y., Chen, X., Liu, Q., and                                   Puterman, M. L. Markov decision processes. Handbooks
                       Peng, J. Sequence modeling of temporal credit assign-                                  in operations research and management science, 2:331–
                       mentforepisodicreinforcementlearning. arXivpreprint                                    434, 1990.
                       arXiv:1905.13420, 2019.
                    Mnih, V., Kavukcuoglu, K., Silver, D., Rusu, A. A., Ve-                               Salimans, T., Ho, J., Chen, X., Sidor, S., and Sutskever,
                       ness, J., Bellemare, M. G., Graves, A., Riedmiller, M.,                                I.  Evolution strategies as a scalable alternative to rein-
                       Fidjeland, A. K., Ostrovski, G., et al. Human-level con-                               forcement learning. arXiv preprint arXiv:1703.03864,
                       trol through deep reinforcement learning. Nature, 518                                  2017.
                       (7540):529, 2015.                                                                  Savinov, N., Raichuk, A., Marinier, R., Vincent, D., Polle-
                    Munos,R., Stepleton, T., Harutyunyan, A., and Bellemare,                                  feys, M., Lillicrap, T., and Gelly, S. Episodic curiosity
                       M. Safe and efﬁcient off-policy reinforcement learning.                                through reachability. arXiv preprint arXiv:1810.02274,
                       In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems,                                  2018.
                       pp. 1046–1054, 2016.                                                               Schaul, T., Borsa, D., Ding, D., Szepesvari, D., Ostrovski,
                    Osband, I., Blundell, C., Pritzel, A., and Van Roy, B. Deep                               G., Dabney, W., and Osindero, S. Adapting behaviour
                       exploration via bootstrapped dqn. In Advances In Neural                                for learning progress, 2019.
                       Information Processing Systems, pp. 4026–4034, 2016.                               Schmidhuber, J. A possibility for implementing curiosity
                    Osband, I., Aslanides, J., and Cassirer, A. Randomized                                    and boredom in model-building neural controllers. In
                       prior functions for deep reinforcement learning. In Ad-                                Proc. of the international conference on simulation of
                       vances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pp.                                   adaptive behavior: From animals to animats, pp. 222–
                       8617–8629, 2018.                                                                       227, 1991.
                                                                                                          Schrittwieser, J., Antonoglou, I., Hubert, T., Simonyan, K.,
                    Ostrovski, G., Bellemare, M. G., van den Oord, A., and                                    Sifre, L., Schmitt, S., Guez, A., Lockhart, E., Hassabis,
                       Munos, R. Count-based exploration with neural density                                  D., Graepel, T., et al.           Mastering atari, go, chess and
                       models. InProceedingsofthe34thInternationalConfer-                                     shogi by planning with a learned model. arXiv preprint
                       ence on Machine Learning-Volume 70, pp. 2721–2730.                                     arXiv:1911.08265, 2019.
                       JMLR.org,2017.
                                                                                                          Silver, D., Huang, A., Maddison, C. J., Guez, A., Sifre, L.,
                    Oudeyer, P.-Y., Kaplan, F., and Hafner, V. V. Intrinsic mo-                               VanDenDriessche,G.,Schrittwieser, J., Antonoglou, I.,
                       tivation systems for autonomous mental development.                                    Panneershelvam, V., Lanctot, M., et al. Mastering the
                       IEEE transactions on evolutionary computation, 11(2):                                  game of go with deep neural networks and tree search.
                       265–286, 2007.                                                                         nature, 529(7587):484–489, 2016.
                    Plappert, M., Houthooft, R., Dhariwal, P., Sidor, S., Chen,                           Strehl, A. L. and Littman, M. L. An analysis of model-
                       R. Y., Chen, X., Asfour, T., Abbeel, P., and Andrychow-                                based interval estimation for markov decision processes.
                       icz, M. Parameter space noise for exploration. arXiv                                   Journal of Computer and System Sciences, 74(8):1309–
                       preprint arXiv:1706.01905, 2017.                                                       1331, 2008.
﻿                                               Agent57: Outperforming the Atari Human Benchmark
              Tang, H., Houthooft, R., Foote, D., Stooke, A., Chen,
                O. X., Duan, Y., Schulman, J., DeTurck, F., and Abbeel,
                P. # exploration: A study of count-based exploration for
                deep reinforcement learning. In Advances in neural in-
                formation processing systems, pp. 2753–2762, 2017.
              Toromanoff, M., Wirbel, E., and Moutarde, F. Is deep re-
                inforcement learning really superhuman on atari? arXiv
                preprint arXiv:1908.04683, 2019.
              Vinyals, O., Babuschkin, I., Czarnecki, W. M., Mathieu,
                M., Dudzik, A., Chung, J., Choi, D. H., Powell, R.,
                Ewalds, T., Georgiev, P., et al. Grandmaster level in star-
                craft ii using multi-agent reinforcementlearning. Nature,
                575(7782):350–354, 2019.
              Wang, Z., Schaul, T., Hessel, M., Van Hasselt, H., Lanc-
                tot, M., and De Freitas, N. Dueling network architec-
                tures for deep reinforcement learning.   arXiv preprint
                arXiv:1511.06581, 2015.
              Weber, T., Heess, N., Buesing, L., and Silver, D. Credit
                assignmenttechniquesinstochasticcomputationgraphs.
                arXiv preprint arXiv:1901.01761, 2019.
              Xu, Z., van Hasselt, H. P., and Silver, D. Meta-gradient re-
                inforcementlearning. In Advances in neural information
                processing systems, pp. 2396–2407, 2018.
